<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss">

  <title><![CDATA[Alistair MacLeod, MM0HAI: Posts tagged android]]></title>

  <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/tag/android/index.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mm0hai.net/"/>
  <updated>2013-05-29T19:13:28-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/tag/android</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alistair N. MacLeod]]></name>
  </author>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Coderace, and trying an Android phone for navigation]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/08/04/Coderace.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/08/04/Coderace.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2012-08-04T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/08/04/Coderace</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img width="640" src="http://www.coderace.co.uk/images/Event2012/Screenshot2.jpg" alt="Final game map" /></p>

<p>Today I participated in an event called <a
href="http://www.coderace.co.uk/">Coderace</a> with a team from the <a
href="http://edinburghhacklab.com/">Edinburgh Hacklab</a>.</p>

<p>The game used an Android app which showed points on a map. Each point had a
clue which could be answered using information available at the indicated
location, for example text on a sculpture or building. Cycling was recommend,
and all but one of us did. A car was used to reach the furthest points.</p>

<p>There were only two teams. The hacklab won 18 to 4, which was amusing because
we were not regular cyclists and the other team had people dressed up
as road racers.</p>

<p>It was sunny and ideal conditions for cycling. There were problems with the
application crashing, position tracking failing, and with phones but it mostly
worked. It was a good way to get some exercise and an idea of what can be done
with these devices. Thanks to Napier University for running it.</p>

<p><img width="640" src="http://www.coderace.co.uk/images/Event2012/DSC00459.JPG" alt="Bikes
and phones" /></p>

<p>I borrowed a phone for the game. My normal phone is a Sony Ericsson W800i and I
had never really used a smartphone before. I had been thinking about a general
purpose computing interface for my touring bike so it was interesting to try
an Android phone as this was one of the main ideas. I borrowed a Samsung
Galaxy S II (GT-I9100).</p>

<p>There were several problems, which without changing things make this system
rather poor. I could hardly see the screen in sunlight. My O2 connection only
allowed 50MB per day, and offered no option to pay for more. This was used in
1.5 hours of occasional map usage. I would think navigation with moving map
is a standard use case for these devices so clearly the limit is not enough
for normal use. The battery was also nearly flat after 1.5 hours, from a near
full charge. The battery in this phone is tiny compared to the screen size. It
seems that a solar or dynamo charging system is not just needed for extend off
grid operation but even when used in a city.</p>

<p>Mobile networks still don't get it when it comes to data. It used to be that
they charged about £3/MB, which is as good as infinite. I suspect what
happened is they had the idea people would want to use WAP and they made up a
price such that the per page cost was what they wanted. This of course made
the tariff useless for actual web browsing. I thought that with the
introduction of smart phones they would have sorted this out but although it's
an order of magnitude less bad it needs another two. The most they offer if
pre arranged is 1GB / month for £10.</p>

<p>And if you want to use it to navigate when cycling through more than one
country you can forget it - back to £3/MB, or something on the order of £1000
/ day. It would be possible if the maps are preloaded but still you can see
the situation is ridiculous.</p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
</feed>
