<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss">

  <title><![CDATA[River MacLeod, MM0HAI: Posts tagged rainbow]]></title>

  <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/tag/rainbow/index.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mm0hai.net/"/>
  <updated>2014-04-11T01:16:00+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/tag/rainbow</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[River MacLeod]]></name>
  </author>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Wind and Fire]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/03/17/Wind-and-Fire.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/03/17/Wind-and-Fire.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2013-03-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/03/17/Wind-and-Fire</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I could feel something today. Some energy in the air, like something was going
to happen. Everyone could feel it. The wind was building and shaking the
trees. It had been building for days.</p>

<p>The wind drove us to eat in a huddle in the camp, sensibly breaking the
protocol of eating in the exposed, sandblasted, main circle. It felt like a
tribe coming together in the face of adversity. It was. The wind blew all
night and bounced my hammock.</p>

<p>The next morning, I broke up with my girlfriend. We were sitting in camp. As I
was talking, something hit me in the back. A girl sat up in my hammock. My now
ex-gf left to make her own camp, and I talked to my friend.</p>

<p>She was sleeping there, she told me, on account of being very tired from the
previous night's activity. She had sex with a guy she liked, and the girl he
was with. She felt very free now. Free from jealousy, ego and social
limits. It sounds like it was a very liberating experience, and a cleansing
from the past. Past problems blown away with the wind.</p>

<p>Later, I was dwelling on the past. As I was thinking about what went wrong
with the gf, ruminating, a pan whacked me on the head. Stop it! Be present
now! The wind had blown it from the tree.</p>

<p>That night, there was an orange glow in the distance. With the wind coming
from there, it was not long before it brought the fire to the camp. Everyone
was driven out. Anything left behind was burnt. Many people lost things,
attachments maybe, and many moved on that morning.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8543751136/" title="DSCF3623 by
mm0hai, on Flickr"><img
src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8522/8543751136_b140416fd0_z.jpg"
width="640" height="480" alt="DSCF3623"></a></p>
]]></content>
   <georss:point>15.927404 -95.632076</georss:point>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Oaxaca Healing Rainbow]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/03/16/Oaxaca-Healing-Rainbow-Gathering.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/03/16/Oaxaca-Healing-Rainbow-Gathering.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2013-03-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/03/16/Oaxaca-Healing-Rainbow-Gathering</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8542647331/" title="Rainbow
Welcome by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img
src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8087/8542647331_1bf5f02ec0_z.jpg"
width="640" height="481" alt="Rainbow Welcome"></a></p>

<p>Somewhere over the rainbow, I found a coconut palm beach. Tropical, on the
pacific coast, warm sea and freshwater lagoon, plentiful coconuts and mangoes,
and rainbows living there.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8546100414/" title="DSCF3667 by
mm0hai, on Flickr"><img
src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8105/8546100414_b26a1edde2_z.jpg"
width="640" height="480" alt="DSCF3667"></a></p>

<p>This was a Healing Rainbow Gathering. This meant that there was no smoking,
alcohol, sugar or caffeine. The food was not all raw, but that was an option,
and it was of course all vegan. The gathering felt happier, calmer and more
relaxed than Palenque. There were far fewer people, and they were not coming
and going all the time.</p>

<p>I stayed there for a week. Meditating, reading, drinking tea, eating coconut,
swimming, and I learnt something about energy healing.</p>

<p>Whenever I used to hear people talk of healing, I did not know what they
meant. People do all sorts of things for healing: energy healing, music
therapy, laughter therapy and diets such as raw food, for example. I didn't
understand this because I thought healing is something you do or need if you
are injured or ill. I did not think I needed to be healed.</p>

<p>However, I came to realise that there are things that can be improved, and
what is taken to be normal is a far worse state than it should be. Many people
are not happy. They argue and fight and do not feel good about life. There is
something wrong which can be fixed. I think it is this sort of thing that
people mean when they talk of healing. I asked someone what it meant, and he
said something about increasing your vibrational frequency. I'm not sure what
that means though.</p>

<p>Someone ran an energy healing workshop. I didn't know what this was, but I
thought I might as well go and try it. The technique was to try and reach a
state of mind without ego, and then allow energy, or qi, or the great spirit,
or whatever you want to call it, to guide your hands over the patient. I think
the idea was to guide energy to flow in some way such as to heal. He explained
that you were not really doing anything, and were more like a conduit.</p>

<p>I tried it. I could feel, or imagined I could feel - it is hard to tell -
something when I held my hands over someone. I didn't think too much about
what I was doing. Asking her, it seems that there was no effect on my patient,
but the experience certainly left me feeling different. I attained a very
relaxed, meditative state of presence which lasted for some time afterwards. I
didn't feel much when I was worked on.</p>

<p>A couple of people I have spoken to about things like this have spoken of
intention. The idea is that what you do does not really matter, what matters
is your intention, and what you give your attention to. He spoke of putting
his hand on an injury, and focusing on it with an intention to heal. I would
guess that things like this have a strong placebo effect in credulous patients
and could indeed make people feel better. Ultimately the purpose of medicine is
to make people feel better, so you could say that this is useful, even if it
does not physically do anything.</p>

<p>Another interesting thing about this gathering was that I did not get ill. I
was eating some raw food prepared by innumerable dirty hippies who were not
washing their hands with soap, and probably some where not washing hands at
all. I felt healthy the whole time. Since I have been back in civilisation I
have had soft stools and been farting a lot, and generally not feeling as
good. I have not been sleeping as well either. Artificial food and light
really do seem to be bad for me. Maybe it is the tap water here which I
consume in small quantities from things like washed vegetables and tooth
brushing. At the rainbow though I drank well water and accidentally swallowed
some from the laguna than many birds swam in, and I did not get ill.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8544851505/" title="DSCF3658 by
mm0hai, on Flickr"><img
src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8235/8544851505_f9b04fae13_z.jpg"
width="640" height="480" alt="DSCF3658"></a></p>

<p>I was also introduced to coconut cheese. Some people discovered that some old
coconuts taste like gorgonzola. The texture is similar to cheese as well. This
was considered a delicacy, but I was a bit suspicious of it. It could be
marketed as a vegan cheese replacement, and I am surprised it has not been
already, as it is very good.</p>

<p>I slept in my hammock most of the time. I slept well. It turns out thought that
it was not very comfortable for two, because there was no space to move.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8544856681/" title="DD Frontline
Hammock by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img
src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8086/8544856681_e83c8aa46c_z.jpg"
width="640" height="480" alt="DD Frontline Hammock"></a></p>

<p>Overall, I enjoyed this gathering. I was much happier than at the Palenque
one, and I learnt some things. It was good to be by the sea after so long in
the mountains.</p>

<p>There was some excitement at the end of the gathering too. I'll write about
that in a further blov post.</p>
]]></content>
   <georss:point>15.927404 -95.632067</georss:point>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Palenque Rainbow Gathering]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/01/03/Palenque-Rainbow-Gathering.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/01/03/Palenque-Rainbow-Gathering.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2013-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/01/03/Palenque-Rainbow-Gathering</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I spent the last two weeks at the Palenque Rainbow Gathering. Unfortunately I
didn't enjoy it very much. There were times I did - the few days I was not ill
I enjoyed swimming and slacklining over the river. Most of the time though I
was ill with various ailments. I suspect I had Giardia from the river, and
then a cold. Sanitation is difficult with so many people living in a temporary
camp.</p>

<p>Some amusing moments though included going for a night out at the theatre, in
the forest, singing and listening to music, and a music therapy session. I
also tried to fix Mykal's dynamo to USB voltage regulator, but I didn't have
any gas for my soldering iron.</p>

<p>I spent some time asking people about hammocks and trying some out,
because I was thinking of replacing my tent with one. I had to get something
new anyway, because I found my tent now leaks badly and is not a comfortable
home.</p>

<p>One day I went for a walk up the road to a wee village. It was the first time
I felt I was seeing Mexico. There were horses on the road and it generally
felt rural and like it was really Mexico, not just another town.</p>

<p>I visited the Mayan ruins one day as well. I didn't enjoy it much though
because I was generally in a bad mood at least partly because of illness, and
because it was so hot I found it tiring to walk. I also didn't like how there
were so many people trying to sell things.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8362733937/" title="DSCF3053 by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8080/8362733937_29a136bb45_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="DSCF3053"></a></p>

<p>I learnt something about how palm oil is produced. The gathering was in a palm
plantation, and one day some people came round with a donkey to harvest the
nuts from which oil is extracted.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8362701093/" title="DSCF3024 by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8378/8362701093_2e4e3d9fb6_z.jpg" width="480" height="640" alt="DSCF3024"></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8362703347/" title="DSCF3025 by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8186/8362703347_7b85d7f92f_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="DSCF3025"></a></p>

<p>I had a couple of quite special experiences. One evening I participated in an
Angel Walk. Another day I had a good experience when I decided to stop thinking
and follow my feelings, which led to an interesting result. I might write
about these later.</p>
]]></content>
   <georss:point>17.483017 -91.925139</georss:point>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Intimate Shitting]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/23/Intimite-Shitting.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/23/Intimite-Shitting.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2012-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/23/Intimite-Shitting</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<!--- date approximate -->


<p>Someone told me one special Rainbow experience I had to have was sharing a
shit pit. She said if you haven't been elbow to elbow with someone on the next
trench then you don't know them, or something like that.</p>

<p>Ten minutes later I was using the shit pit and someone came along and asked if
he could join me, so I said yes. Of everyone this could have been, he was a
nurse, and apart, therefore, from being an expert on shit, he seemed to have a
particular interest.</p>

<p>Unprovoked, he explained his ideas. He thought illness could be a beautiful
thing because an inability to do things yourself such as wiping your bum means
you must become closer to other people. He thought illnesses were for a
reason, and must teach you something or have some benefit.</p>

<p>Another nurse I spoke to said she hated wiping bums. She quit to go
travelling.</p>

<p>I'm afraid I didn't take a photo for this post.</p>
]]></content>
   <georss:point>17.483017 -91.925139</georss:point>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Gods]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/22/Gods.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/22/Gods.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2012-12-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/22/Gods</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I don't believe in any gods, and think religion is dangerous and very
harmful. The Rainbow Gathering had a good selection of them though. There were
temples for Hare Krishna, Shiva, and even a few Jesuses and Marys around. This
flippant attitude changed though, at the End of the World.</p>

<p>When everything is wet, it feels like it will never stop raining, you are
vomiting and the jungle is trying to eat you, Gods seem to come back. I like
sacred songs whatever I think of the content. In the dark I prayed to the rain
to stop, and apologised to Krishna for singing but not believing.</p>

<p>A Christian minister once told me, when questioned, that praying is something
people do because it is all they can do. Find a real way to control the
environment and prayer is useless.</p>

<p>Gods aren't disappearing directly because of science taking over as a method
of understanding the world, they are disappearing because there is less
suffering. Modern life gives more comfort and less disease. With control of
your environment, waterproof roofs, heating, and factory farming, there is no
desperation, and no need for gods of rain and corn.</p>
]]></content>
   <georss:point>17.483017 -91.925139</georss:point>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Great Flood and a Rainbow]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/21/End-of-the-World.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/21/End-of-the-World.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2012-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/21/End-of-the-World</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One reason I left on <a href="/blog/tag/cyclewho/">this trip</a> before I was
ready was to get to Palenque in time for the end of the world. There is a
Mayan prophecy about the end of an era of Babylon, the broken world, and the
transformation to a new world where people live consciously. I made it to the
Rainbow Gathering near Palenque a few days before the 21st.</p>

<p>The 21st of December 2012 was to be the end of the world. In the morning there
was going to be a ceremony at the Palenque ruins. Before that, a global
meditation at 0411, I think it was. That is not a time when I would find it
easy to get up. Someone suggested going to sleep at the main circle so I might
wake up, so I went out there with my bivvy bag.</p>

<p>I lay down to sleep, and it started to rain. I was not concerned about this,
because I had previously tested this bivvy bag up a hill in Scotland when it
rained all night and I remained dry, so I tried to go to sleep.</p>

<p>The rain started to become very heavy. I could feel the lumps of water
whacking into me. I started to get wet. I don't think it was coming in the
opening - probably it was so hard it was forced through the material. I stayed
for a while anyway hoping it would stop, but after maybe half an hour it was
still raining heavily.</p>

<p>The drummers had left and the previously strong fire had been extinguished by
the rain. I was now on my own in the dark, getting cold in the heaviest rain I
had every seen, which showed no sign of stopping. I started to wonder if this
was the end. If you want to clean the world ready for a new one rain might be
a good way to do it. It would not be the first time there had been a Great
Flood for something like this.</p>

<p>I decided to get up before I became hypothermic. I made it back to my camp on
the paths which were now mud rivers. My tent was still there, but full of
water. I slept in my damp sleeping bag and missed the morning ceremonies.</p>

<p>The world seemed the same in the morning, but then I realised that actually
anything could have happened. Maybe the rest outside the Rainbow had gone. I
would have to check it out later.</p>
]]></content>
   <georss:point>17.483017 -91.925139</georss:point>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Going to the Palenque Rainbow Gathering]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/18/To-the-Rainbow.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/18/To-the-Rainbow.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2012-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/18/To-the-Rainbow</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>When the earth is ravaged and the animals are dying, a new tribe of people
shall come unto the earth from many colors, classes, creeds, and who by
their actions and deeds shall make the earth green again. They will be known
as the warriors of the Rainbow.
-- Native American Prophecy, seen <a
href="http://www.welcomehome.org/rainbow/">here</a>.</p></blockquote>

<p>The Palenque Rainbow Gathering is one reason I came to Mexico now, to begin
cycling at the End of the World.</p>

<p>I arrived in Palenque by overnight bus, had breakfast and set off down the road.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8339829385/" title="Beginning of
the dirt road to the Rainbow by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img
src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8213/8339829385_0530a24c5b_z.jpg"
width="640" height="480" alt="Beginning of the dirt road to the Rainbow"></a></p>

<p>Leaving Palenque there was a short section of main road before reaching the
turnoff for the Rainbow. Then the road was awful. Very bumpy surface, rocks,
and it went up and down. My bike was heavily loaded and I was not particularly
fit. On the way up the road, though, I met a friend I last saw in Europe a
year ago, who was walking to town. :)</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8339845737/" title="DSCF3008 by
mm0hai, on Flickr"><img
src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8359/8339845737_314e8af703_z.jpg"
width="640" height="480" alt="DSCF3008"></a></p>

<p>Eventually I arrived, and one of the first things I did was go for a swim in
 the river pools.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8384100203/" title="DSCF3203 by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8189/8384100203_7f75dba767_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="DSCF3203"></a></p>

<p>I went for a walk around to explore and look for a campsite. On the way back
to get my bike and things I met three other cycle tourists who had just
arrived. <a href="http://chaingethecycle.org/">Mykal and Nico</a>, who were
cycling to Guatemala to help build an earth ship, and Lance, who was cycling
to Panama. We set up camp together. I stayed for the next two weeks.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8364983083/" title="DSCF3133 by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8055/8364983083_4131357bf4_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="DSCF3133"></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8366114804/" title="DSCF3146 by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8083/8366114804_cc0cd31ccb_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="DSCF3146"></a></p>
]]></content>
   <georss:point>17.510204 -91.98104</georss:point>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
