<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss">

  <title><![CDATA[River MacLeod, MM0HAI: Posts tagged edinburgh]]></title>

  <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/tag/edinburgh/index.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mm0hai.net/"/>
  <updated>2013-10-16T02:45:28-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/tag/edinburgh</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[River MacLeod]]></name>
  </author>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Python Edinburgh Mini Conference]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2011/05/22/Python-Edinburgh-Mini-Conference.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2011/05/22/Python-Edinburgh-Mini-Conference.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2011-05-22T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2011/05/22/Python-Edinburgh-Mini-Conference</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This weekend we had the <a
href="http://www.pythonedinburgh.org/wiki/2011-May-Mini-Conference">Python
Edinburgh Mini Conference</a>. I don't really use python, as I typically use
perl for the sorts of things I might want it for, but I thought it would be
interesting to go along and see what was happening in the python world.</p>

<p>I thought it would probably be helpful if I actually knew some python, so on
Friday night after the pub I went home to learn. It's just pseudocode with
spaces, right? I wasn't actually a complete beginner - I had a play with it a
couple of months ago when I wrote map and reduce scripts to implement a search
indexer with Hadoop and solved a few of the Project Euler problems.</p>

<p>It looked like the conference was going to have a large django component so I
did the <a
href="http://docs.djangoproject.com/en/dev/intro/tutorial01/">tutorial</a>. It
was very straightforward and I had an application running that evening. My
main concern with the tutorial was that there was no magical pony on a stick.</p>

<p><img alt="Django pony"
src="http://dl-web.dropbox.com/u/10320/django/wallpaper/magic-django-pony-iphone.png"
/></p>

<p>I discovered <a href="http://www.tipfy.org">Tipfy</a>, a framework for Google
App Engine. One of the things that got me wondering if I should be using more
python and less perl is that there are PaaS providers only for the former, so
this is probably worth looking at more closely. I've also heard good things
about <a href="http://www.nltk.org">NLTK</a> which I would like to play with
some time.</p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
</feed>
