<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss">

  <title><![CDATA[River MacLeod, MM0HAI: Posts tagged edinburgh]]></title>

  <link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/tag/edinburgh/index.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://localhost:4000/"/>
  <updated>2018-02-07T17:59:26+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://localhost:4000/blog/tag/edinburgh</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[River MacLeod]]></name>
  </author>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Imbolc at Roslin]]></title>
    <link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2016/02/01/Green-Men-Roslin.html"/>
    <updated>2016-02-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2016/02/01/Green-Men-Roslin</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/6/5692/30807680401_1b5b012ba5_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="Rosslyn Chapel in the Snow" /></p>

<p><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/6/5327/30594839350_c2c7a67eac_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="Rosslyn Glen Snow" /></p>

<p>I spent the weekend at a cottage on the edge of Roslin village, right beside
the chapel. The house is dated 1660. There was graffiti scratched on my
bedroom window dated 1899. It’s interesting to think about all the people who
must have stayed here. It used to be an inn, and a Freemason lodge met
here. Now it is rented out.</p>

<p>I found a book in the house about green men. It said there are 103 green men
in the chapel, and only one Jesus. The Green Man appears in the Beltane Fire
Festival in Edinburgh, and in another form as the Summer King at Samhuinn. I
was interested to learn more about this character. Roslin chapel lies above a
forested glen, which is also a place of magical interest, and somewhere you
might see a green man. :)</p>

<p><img src="https://c6.staticflickr.com/6/5535/30895940765_d94cfb454b_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="A Green Man in Rosslyn Chapel" /></p>

<p><img src="https://c6.staticflickr.com/6/5807/30260529893_afb2ac57c1_z.jpg" width="480" height="640" alt="A Green Man in Rosslyn Chapel" /></p>

<p>There is a circle of stones in the garden that looks like it used to be a
well. There is a tradition of visiting holy wells at Imbolc, so it was
interesting to find one here. I walked round it.</p>
]]></content>
   <georss:point>55.855662 -3.160596</georss:point>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[IndieWebCamp Edinburgh]]></title>
    <link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2015/07/26/Indie-Web-Camp-Edinburgh.html"/>
    <updated>2015-07-26T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2015/07/26/Indie-Web-Camp-Edinburgh</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img width="640" src="https://indieweb.org/images/8/84/2015-07-25_Edinburgh.jpg" alt="IndieWebCamp Edinburgh group photo" /></p>

<p>At the weekend, I attended an <a href="https://indieweb.org/2015/Edinburgh">IndieWebCamp in Edinburgh</a>.</p>

<p>IndieWeb basically seems to be the idea that people should have their own
websites - what we used to call homepages - instead of using things like
Facebook, Twitter, etc. It is some ideas of how to do things, and some minimal
standards to allow for sites to interoperate.</p>

<p>One of the most important ideas is that your url and site are you
identity. You should own your url and content. There is a system to allow you
to authenticate to other sites as your domain name. Other standards allow, for
example, comments to be posted on other sites, syndication of posts (read
sites with a feed reader like RSS), and many others.</p>

<p>One thing not yet developed on the IndieWeb is a way to have friends-only or
other private type posts. We had some discussions about how to do this. We
also had some talk about static sites. I think most IndieWeb sites are
dynamically generated, but mine and certainly some others are static.</p>

<p>My site is generated with Jekyll, and then served as static pages. This has
some limitations, but not as many as you might think, and it has many
advantages regarding security and efficiency of hosting.</p>

<p>I also made some basic improvements to the indiewebyness of my site this
weekend, fixing <a href="http://microformats.org/">microformats</a>, and other
general work on the site.</p>

<p>I would certainly recommend going to one of these camps to anyone interested
in building or running a website themselves, which they can have control over.</p>
]]></content>
   <georss:point>55.935481 -3.180439</georss:point>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Python Edinburgh Mini Conference]]></title>
    <link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2011/05/22/Python-Edinburgh-Mini-Conference.html"/>
    <updated>2011-05-22T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2011/05/22/Python-Edinburgh-Mini-Conference</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This weekend we had the <a href="http://www.pythonedinburgh.org/wiki/2011-May-Mini-Conference">Python
Edinburgh Mini Conference</a>. I don’t really use python, as I typically use
perl for the sorts of things I might want it for, but I thought it would be
interesting to go along and see what was happening in the python world.</p>

<p>I thought it would probably be helpful if I actually knew some python, so on
Friday night after the pub I went home to learn. It’s just pseudocode with
spaces, right? I wasn’t actually a complete beginner - I had a play with it a
couple of months ago when I wrote map and reduce scripts to implement a search
indexer with Hadoop and solved a few of the Project Euler problems.</p>

<p>It looked like the conference was going to have a large django component so I
did the <a href="http://docs.djangoproject.com/en/dev/intro/tutorial01/">tutorial</a>. It
was very straightforward and I had an application running that evening. My
main concern with the tutorial was that there was no magical pony on a stick.</p>

<p><img alt="Django pony" src="http://dl-web.dropbox.com/u/10320/django/wallpaper/magic-django-pony-iphone.png" /></p>

<p>I discovered <a href="http://www.tipfy.org">Tipfy</a>, a framework for Google
App Engine. One of the things that got me wondering if I should be using more
python and less perl is that there are PaaS providers only for the former, so
this is probably worth looking at more closely. I’ve also heard good things
about <a href="http://www.nltk.org">NLTK</a> which I would like to play with
some time.</p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
</feed>
