<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss">

  <title><![CDATA[River MacLeod, MM0HAI: Posts tagged river]]></title>

  <link href="https://mm0hai.net/blog/tag/river/index.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://mm0hai.net/"/>
  <updated>2016-12-15T20:16:23+00:00</updated>
  <id>https://mm0hai.net/blog/tag/river</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[River MacLeod]]></name>
  </author>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Nacimiento de un río]]></title>
    <link href="https://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/10/15/Rio.html"/>
    <updated>2013-10-15T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>https://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/10/15/Rio</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I am very happy today, because it is my birthday. Well, technically it was
yesterday, but it was so late that this is the first new day.</p>

<p>When I was in Mexico, at least six months ago, I was thinking about changing
my name, and to River. I can’t remember exactly why, but I think it was
because I was talking to someone about the importance of words and sounds. I
was interested in seeing if a change in name would change how people saw me,
and treated me, and how I acted and felt about myself.</p>

<p>I forgot about this idea while I was travelling, but was reminded of it again
In Panama where I met someone who had given herself a hippie name and
encouraged me to use my new name. I started to do so, in earnest, when I got on
the boat to Colombia. I crossed the water and entered a new continent with a
new name.</p>

<p>I only used it with new people though. I still wasn’t totally sure whether to
completely change it. I knew I wanted to, but I thought I should check whether
this was the right name - maybe there is a better one - and what people think
about it. I asked a few people, but I really didn’t consider any other
names. I think I came up with the name when I was thinking about flowing, and
the idea of the bike and I flowing through the world. Now though it felt like
there was not really a choice - this was just meant to be.</p>

<p>Someone sent me a song about a río. I went to sleep with the sound of the
river outside my window. I changed my name.</p>

<p>It felt like a relief. I no longer had this pressure of thinking about who I
was. I feel freed of the past. I was not particularly happy for most of
the nearly three decades past. I am happier now, and don’t need to carry this
any more.</p>

<p>I am already finding things I like about this name. I think of rivers
differently - now they are brothers and sisters. :) I say hello to the river
when I walk past, and to the bamboo, and the bananas, and the other plants
that grow around it.</p>

<p>I went to one of the organic hipster veggie restaurants around here, to
celebrate my birthday. I’m writing here now. After I sat down, I noticed that
I can hear the river and see the bamboo from my table. The water dispenser has
stones in the bottom.</p>

<iframe width="640" height="360" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/S6L9wccThyA?feature=player_detailpage" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>
]]></content>
   <georss:point>6.207265 -75.565822</georss:point>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
