<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss">

  <title><![CDATA[Alistair MacLeod, MM0HAI: Posts tagged diving]]></title>

  <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/tag/diving/index.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mm0hai.net/"/>
  <updated>2013-08-14T23:15:50-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/tag/diving</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alistair N. MacLeod]]></name>
  </author>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Utila]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/06/07/Utila.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/06/07/Utila.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2013-06-07T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/06/07/Utila</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>DMT</strong>: Dimethyltriptamine, a psychedelic.</p>

<blockquote><p>"subjective effects can range from short-lived milder psychedelic states to
powerful immersive experiences; these are often described as a total loss of
connection to conventional reality with the encounter of ineffable
spiritual/alien realms." -- wikipedia</p></blockquote>

<p><strong>DMT</strong>: Divemaster in Training.</p>

<blockquote><p>People who accompany you in an immersive experience of encounters with
strange creatures in an alien realm. -- me</p></blockquote>

<p>Underwater, perception changes. Everything is 33% bigger, sound is different
and faster, gravity can be countered allowing you to fly, and everything
tastes of salt. The trees are pink, and the birds are very strange.</p>

<p>I'm on the boat at the end of my holiday trip to Utila. I feel a bit sad, but
I don't think I'll miss the place. I didn't think I could stand the dorm room
for more than a couple of days, but then I realised I stayed for twelve.</p>

<p>I learned to scuba dive here. It's not something I had ever thought about
before, but since the Yucatan, people were talking about it. You can dive in
the Cenotes there - gateways to the Mayan underworld, and there is also the
Mesoamerican reef that runs all down the cost from Mexico to Honduras. I
learnt that Utila is the cheapest place in the world to take diving courses,
so I thought I might as well try it.</p>

<p>I did some snorkelling first, off Caye Caulker, Belize. This was a good
introduction, because once you get used to a mask and breathing through a
tube, it doesn't really make much difference to how it feels on your face
whether the tube is connected to the atmosphere or a tank. The reef was more
alive with fish and animals here than in Utila, too.</p>

<p>I took the PADI Open Water course, the entry level qualification that lets you
dive with a buddy. (Solo diving is highly discouraged by most people, and
should only be done with redundant equipment and extra training.) I decided to
do the Advanced course too, after some thought, because I wanted to do some
diving after the training, and the course didn't cost too much more than just
paying for some dives. It allows diving in more places too, and deeper.</p>

<p>I particularly liked a wall dive we did. It is a unique feeling to be able to
dive off a cliff and not fall. Swimming along the top of the coral, then
turning 90 degrees down, still swimming. The world rotates and you are free of
up and down.</p>

<p>We also visited a wreck, and did a night dive. The scene of everyone
descending into a circle on the bottom with beams of light from torches
resembled something from a sci fi film; maybe a space ship landing, or a team
going to recover a crashed ship.</p>

<p>I also found that there are some good people in Honduras, who don't just try
to steal from you, like the taxi drivers and the person who tried to take my
camera out its bag in La Ceiba. There are still the people coming into what
was my home for a while to try and sell me weed or failing that crack, and
people stealing from the kitchen, but there is the occasional pretty
engineering nerd and nyancat fan around too.</p>

<p>Actually I think diving is a bit of a geeky hobby. I met a couple of
engineers, a physics teacher, a biologist / bird watcher, and a web
designer. It's not really a sport, being much like a casual stroll would be on
land. It probably appeals to geeks because of the equipment and the required
knowledge of physics, chemistry and biology. Looking at fish is the underwater
equivalent of bird watching, too.</p>

<p>I'm on my way back to the mainland now anyway. I think I'll make a brief
foray into the jungle, then rejoin my bike and return to the cycling life. I
forgot about cycling after a day or two here - it was a distant memory of a
past life, but it is resurfacing now. I'm not sure I want to be working away
in the sun and dust again, rather than floating weightless in the sea, but it
seems to be what I'm doing.</p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
</feed>
