<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss">

  <title><![CDATA[River MacLeod, MM0HAI: Posts tagged colombia]]></title>

  <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/tag/colombia/index.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mm0hai.net/"/>
  <updated>2014-10-16T05:06:39+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/tag/colombia</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[River MacLeod]]></name>
  </author>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Nacimiento de un río]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/10/15/Rio.html"/>
    <updated>2013-10-15T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/10/15/Rio</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I am very happy today, because it is my birthday. Well, technically it was
yesterday, but it was so late that this is the first new day.</p>

<p>When I was in Mexico, at least six months ago, I was thinking about changing
my name, and to River. I can't remember exactly why, but I think it was
because I was talking to someone about the importance of words and sounds. I
was interested in seeing if a change in name would change how people saw me,
and treated me, and how I acted and felt about myself.</p>

<p>I forgot about this idea while I was travelling, but was reminded of it again
In Panama where I met someone who had given herself a hippie name and
encouraged me to use my new name. I started to do so, in earnest, when I got on
the boat to Colombia. I crossed the water and entered a new continent with a
new name.</p>

<p>I only used it with new people though. I still wasn't totally sure whether to
completely change it. I knew I wanted to, but I thought I should check whether
this was the right name - maybe there is a better one - and what people think
about it. I asked a few people, but I really didn't consider any other
names. I think I came up with the name when I was thinking about flowing, and
the idea of the bike and I flowing through the world. Now though it felt like
there was not really a choice - this was just meant to be.</p>

<p>Someone sent me a song about a río. I went to sleep with the sound of the
river outside my window. I changed my name.</p>

<p>It felt like a relief. I no longer had this pressure of thinking about who I
was. I feel freed of the past. Alistair was not particularly happy for most of
the nearly three decades past. I am happier now, and don't need to carry this
any more.</p>

<p>I am already finding things I like about this name. I think of rivers
differently - now they are brothers and sisters. :) I say hello to the river
when I walk past, and to the bamboo, and the bananas, and the other plants
that grow around it.</p>

<p>I went to one of the organic hipster veggie restaurants around here, to
celebrate my birthday. I'm writing here now. After I sat down, I noticed that
I can hear the river and see the bamboo from my table. The water dispenser has
stones in the bottom.</p>

<iframe width="640" height="360"
src="//www.youtube.com/embed/S6L9wccThyA?feature=player_detailpage"
frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>

]]></content>
   <georss:point>6.207265 -75.565822</georss:point>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Cycles Closing in Colombia]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/10/12/Cycles-Closing-Colombia.html"/>
    <updated>2013-10-12T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/10/12/Cycles-Closing-Colombia</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I keep finding myself talking about things which happened in the Canary
Islands. It's at least partly because many things started there, and now they
are coming to some completion.</p>

<p>I went to the Canaries to try and hitch a lift on a boat to South America. I
didn't manage that, but nearly two years later, I arrived in Colombia on a
sailing catamaran.</p>

<p>When I was in La Tomatera, Las Palmas de Gran Canaria, I learned to make
macramé, and started to decorate my computer power cable. On the boat to
Colombia, I finished it. About half an hour after completion, the cable
failed. It held out just long enough to allow me to complete it.</p>

<p>I also made a bracelet, which I have worn permanently since then. Today, I
gave it away to a stranger I met on the metro in Medellín, Colombia. I really
don't know why. I didn't know her name, and do not expect to see her again. I
said she could have it if she could get it off. The knot untied.</p>

<p>Now I think where that bracelet had been - so many places. Beaches, mountains,
cities, forests. Up to about 35,000 feet, and down to 30 meters under the
sea. Boats, trains, cars, planes, and of course the bike. Three continents,
and two oceans, and too many islands to remember. Many beds and hammocks, of
which most mine. But this is all past. I shouldn't be dwelling on it. I am
here now.</p>

<p>In Las Palmas, I learned to make dreadlocks and had one made for me. In Costa
Rica, I made one for someone.</p>

<p>In Costa Rica also, I ate fruit given to us, the rainbow caravan, by market
sellers. Today, in Colombia, I bought some bananas and gave them to a beggar
who told me she was hungry, and whom I saw foraging unsuccessfully near the
river, where there are some banana plants.</p>

<p>I have been cycling my bike. Maybe that will end soon too. I don't know, that
is for the future.</p>
]]></content>
   <georss:point>8.857256 -75.635376</georss:point>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Sailing San Blas]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/09/30/San-Blas.html"/>
    <updated>2013-09-30T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/09/30/San-Blas</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There are various ways to get from Panama to Colombia: flying, cargo boat in
the Pacific, small cargo launches between islands in the Caribbean, and a
sailing yacht in the Caribbean are some of the options. Travel by land is a
serious undertaking and very rarely done. The area between the countries is
called the Darien Gap: here there is a break in the Panamerican Highway, and
nothing but thick jungle and various natural and man made dangers. The <a
href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Darien_scheme">difficulty Scots had living
here</a> is one reason why Scotland joined with England and became Great
Britain.</p>

<p>I wanted to take a boat anyway, and preferably a bigger sailing to keep my
bike away from the salt. I tried hitchiking from Portobelo and Puerto Lindo,
but in the end decided just to pay the tourist rate for a berth on the
Santana. Although very expensive, it was not a bad decision. The San Blas
islands along the Panama coast are the classic tropical islands, many with
nothing but sand and a few palm trees.</p>

<p>I joined the boat in Puerto Lindo. It turned out the wrapping was not really
necessary.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/9990470005" title="Bike under
tarp, tied to rail on Santana by River, on Flickr"><img
src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7325/9990470005_1bfcdabc15_z.jpg"
width="640" height="480" alt="Bike under tarp, tied to rail on Santana"></a></p>

<p>Officially leaving Panama was the easiest border so far. The captain took our
passports to this office while we did nothing.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/9990480846" title="The Migration
Office in the San Blas by River, on Flickr"><img
src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3702/9990480846_5f91746548_z.jpg"
width="640" height="480" alt="The Migration Office in the San Blas"></a></p>

<p>It is obviously a popular place for cruisers.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/9990900024" title="Panama Flag
in San Blas by River, on Flickr"><img
src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2887/9990900024_4f563753f9_z.jpg"
width="640" height="480" alt="Panama Flag in San Blas"></a></p>

<p>The Kuna people inhabit these islands. I don't know how they manage with so
little resources, but one thing they do now is sell lobsters and beaded
jewellery to tourists on the big boats.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/9990446474" title="Kuna Canoe by
River, on Flickr"><img
src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3834/9990446474_cd215d3b55_z.jpg"
width="640" height="480" alt="Kuna Canoe"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/9991107533" title="Kuna canoe by
River, on Flickr"><img
src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2834/9991107533_255abfe2e8_z.jpg"
width="640" height="480" alt="Kuna canoe"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/9991217535" title="Kuna house
with Solar Panel, San Blas by River, on Flickr"><img
src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7354/9991217535_4f94d4039c_z.jpg"
width="640" height="479" alt="Kuna house with Solar Panel, San Blas"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/9991201765" title="Santana by
River, on Flickr"><img
src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3694/9991201765_2dd2e70e23_z.jpg"
width="640" height="480" alt="Santana"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/10108067576" title="Framed by
palms by River, on Flickr"><img
src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2857/10108067576_8ebdbbc2d7_z.jpg"
width="480" height="640" alt="Framed by palms"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/10108165163" title="Bird visits
the boat by River, on Flickr"><img
src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7293/10108165163_ef71b92793_z.jpg"
width="640" height="480" alt="Bird visits the boat"></a>
k</p>
]]></content>
   <georss:point>9.954 -77.061</georss:point>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
