<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss">

  <title><![CDATA[River MacLeod, MM0HAI: Posts tagged mobile]]></title>

  <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/tag/mobile/index.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mm0hai.net/"/>
  <updated>2015-07-25T12:26:37+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/tag/mobile</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[River MacLeod]]></name>
  </author>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Coderace, and trying an Android phone for navigation]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/08/04/Coderace.html"/>
    <updated>2012-08-04T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/08/04/Coderace</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img width="640" src="http://www.coderace.co.uk/images/Event2012/Screenshot2.jpg" alt="Final game map" /></p>

<p>Today I participated in an event called <a
href="http://www.coderace.co.uk/">Coderace</a> with a team from the <a
href="http://edinburghhacklab.com/">Edinburgh Hacklab</a>.</p>

<p>The game used an Android app which showed points on a map. Each point had a
clue which could be answered using information available at the indicated
location, for example text on a sculpture or building. Cycling was recommend,
and all but one of us did. A car was used to reach the furthest points.</p>

<p>There were only two teams. The hacklab won 18 to 4, which was amusing because
we were not regular cyclists and the other team had people dressed up
as road racers.</p>

<p>It was sunny and ideal conditions for cycling. There were problems with the
application crashing, position tracking failing, and with phones but it mostly
worked. It was a good way to get some exercise and an idea of what can be done
with these devices. Thanks to Napier University for running it.</p>

<p><img width="640" src="http://www.coderace.co.uk/images/Event2012/DSC00459.JPG" alt="Bikes
and phones" /></p>

<p>I borrowed a phone for the game. My normal phone is a Sony Ericsson W800i and I
had never really used a smartphone before. I had been thinking about a general
purpose computing interface for my touring bike so it was interesting to try
an Android phone as this was one of the main ideas. I borrowed a Samsung
Galaxy S II (GT-I9100).</p>

<p>There were several problems, which without changing things make this system
rather poor. I could hardly see the screen in sunlight. My O2 connection only
allowed 50MB per day, and offered no option to pay for more. This was used in
1.5 hours of occasional map usage. I would think navigation with moving map
is a standard use case for these devices so clearly the limit is not enough
for normal use. The battery was also nearly flat after 1.5 hours, from a near
full charge. The battery in this phone is tiny compared to the screen size. It
seems that a solar or dynamo charging system is not just needed for extend off
grid operation but even when used in a city.</p>

<p>Mobile networks still don't get it when it comes to data. It used to be that
they charged about £3/MB, which is as good as infinite. I suspect what
happened is they had the idea people would want to use WAP and they made up a
price such that the per page cost was what they wanted. This of course made
the tariff useless for actual web browsing. I thought that with the
introduction of smart phones they would have sorted this out but although it's
an order of magnitude less bad it needs another two. The most they offer if
pre arranged is 1GB / month for £10.</p>

<p>And if you want to use it to navigate when cycling through more than one
country you can forget it - back to £3/MB, or something on the order of £1000
/ day. It would be possible if the maps are preloaded but still you can see
the situation is ridiculous.</p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Native Mobile App Development with HTML5]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2011/09/11/Native-Mobile-Web-Apps-with-PhoneGap.html"/>
    <updated>2011-09-11T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2011/09/11/Native-Mobile-Web-Apps-with-PhoneGap</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A while ago I was having a play with CSS 3D transforms and I made a <a
href="/blog/2011/08/08/Torchwood-Triangle-with-CSS-3D-Transforms.html">spinning
triangle symbol</a> as seen on the TV show Torchwood. Last night, someone
tweeted me about it saying he wanted a version for his phone. I'd done some
mobile web app development before (my <a href="/life/life.html">HTML5 Game of
Life</a>) but had never made a native app. Learning native app development was
not my top priority but I knew it was possible to make native apps using HTML
and Javascript so thought I would try it.</p>

<h2>Mobile Web Apps and Native Apps</h2>

<p>Native apps are written to a device specific API and use a device specific
runtime and packaging system. This means they must be rewritten for every
platform which is required. They are not a part of the web. This means that
their resources cannot be linked to, for example.</p>

<p>Mobile web apps use standard web technologies. They can run on many different
platforms and interoperate with the rest of the web. They are created in much
the same way as a normal web app but they can be designed to also work
offline. The key technology to enable this is the HTML5 offline application
cache. Further enhancements can be made to make mobile web apps look like
native apps, for example providing an icon to use when installing the app in a
home screen.</p>

<p>I believe that whenever possible mobile web apps should be used in preference
to native apps. This is because:</p>

<ul>
<li>They are mostly cross platform.</li>
<li>You don't need to learn a totally different development ecosystem and, in
the case of iOS, Objective-C.</li>
<li>They interoperate with the web. Does not need to silo data, can be linked to.</li>
<li>Morally better: they reduce wasted time redoing work for other
platforms. This is time developers could be using to be creating something
new to benefit the world.</li>
</ul>


<p>Mobile web apps have some disadvantages though:</p>

<ul>
<li>Users are less familiar with them: this may reduce installs and they may not
understand they can be used offline.</li>
<li>Not all device features are available through the DOM, e.g. a phone camera.</li>
<li>Payment infrastructure: The Apple App Store, for example, makes it easy to
sell apps.</li>
</ul>


<p>Thankfully, there is a way to develop using web standards as far as possible
and then bundle the functionality in a native app. This preserves some of the
benefits of web apps, such as reduced development time for many platforms,
allows the apps to be included in app stores, and permits access to device
features.</p>

<p>There are many frameworks designed to do just this - here is wikipedia's list:
<a
href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Multiple_phone_web_based_application_framework">Mobile
web based application frameworks</a>.</p>

<h2>Using PhoneGap</h2>

<p>I decided to use <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/PhoneGap">PhoneGap</a>
for the Torchwood triangle project. This is something that could be
done as a web app, in fact <a href="/misc/torchwood-spinning-triangle/">I did
that too</a>, but I wanted to learn about the technology.</p>

<p>If I had needed to use features not available to web apps, I could have done
so with PhoneGap. It adds javascript objects to the DOM to provide additional
features, for example, here is how to <a
href="http://docs.phonegap.com/phonegap_camera_camera.md.html">access a
camera</a>.</p>

<p>First, I had to install the Android SDK. I also installed the eclipse plugins
as the documentation suggested this would probably be the quickest way to get
started. I usually prefer to work with emacs and the command line but this
dealt with generating the boilerplate. I then downloaded and copied the
necessary parts of PhoneGap to the project. This was all straightforward,
following the <a href="http://www.phonegap.com/start#android">PhoneGap getting
started guide</a>.</p>

<p>I then copied my html, css and image to the project and ran it in the
simulator. It was very slow to start, and failed with an error the first time
but it did eventually work.</p>

<h3>Packaging</h3>

<p>I now had an Android application which worked in the simulator. I now had to
work out how to package it and get it onto real devices. The android
developers guide <a
href="http://developer.android.com/guide/publishing/preparing.html">publishing
section</a> was helpful at this stage.</p>

<p>Some points to note:</p>

<ul>
<li>Signing applications is mandatory but is typically done with a self signed
key you create yourself.</li>
<li><a href="http://developer.android.com/guide/publishing/versioning.html">Set
versions</a> correctly.</li>
<li>Remove unneeded permissions from <code>AndroidManifest.xml</code>.</li>
<li>Optimise performance by using <a
href="http://developer.android.com/guide/developing/tools/zipalign.html">zipalign</a>.</li>
</ul>


<h3>Distribution</h3>

<p>I now had a <code>.apk</code> file but I wasn't sure how these could be
distributed. I tested in the emulator and found that they can simply be
downloaded with a web browser and the device offers to install the app. The
usual way to do it is probably to upload to the Android Marketplace but unlike
the Apple equivalent this is not required.</p>

<p>The only problem I had now was that I don't actually have an Android device!
I'll try and get someone to test it out for me tomorrow but here is the
possibly working app for you to try just now: <a
href="/misc/torchwood-spinning-triangle/Torchwood_Triangle.apk">Torchwood
Triangle for Android</a>.</p>

<p>Update: I'm afraid the Android app doesn't show the triangle. See further
comments on <a
href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2011/08/08/Torchwood-Triangle-with-CSS-3D-Transforms.html">this
post</a>.</p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
</feed>
