<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss">

  <title><![CDATA[Alistair MacLeod, MM0HAI: Posts tagged water]]></title>

  <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/tag/water/index.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mm0hai.net/"/>
  <updated>2013-08-14T23:15:50-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/tag/water</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alistair N. MacLeod]]></name>
  </author>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Minimising Water Usage when Travelling]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/06/01/Saving-Water.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/06/01/Saving-Water.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2013-06-01T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/06/01/Saving-Water</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Here are some tips on using less water when travelling, by bike or with
backpack. I learnt them from other travellers, and myself through necessity.</p>

<h2>Ration Sweat</h2>

<p>Ration sweat, so you don't need to drink as much. In hot places, don't cycle
in midday sun. Instead, sleep, read, or write, under shelter from the
sun. Start cycling as soon as it gets light, and also in the evening, and you
should have enough time to get in the distance you want. In Central America, I
think I need to drink about 1 litre an hour, except around midday, maybe 1130
to 1500, when 2 litres an hour is about right if cycling.</p>

<h2>Washing Up</h2>

<p>Avoid frying - this makes washing up tractable. To cook vegetables, add them
to the boiling rice or pasta you are making. This also saves time cooking.</p>

<p>To wash a pan with only a few millilitres of water, first scrape it out with
your spoon as well as you can. Then add very little water. Rub with fingers,
or a scrubber if you have one. Remove debris with fingers. Repeat maybe once
or twice. At his stage the pan will be mostly clean, but there will probably
still be some bits of food stuck on from cooking. Now make a cup of tea in the
pan. The boiling water will remove what's stuck, and sterilise the pan. The
tea will cover any slight taste from the food. You had to drinking something
anyway, so this uses the drinking water for cleaning too. Use a lid if
available to minimise water loss as steam.</p>

<h2>Water Bottles</h2>

<p>When you need some water for washing hands, or small quantities for washing
other things, there is a technique for dispensing it.</p>

<p>Using a normal bottle of water with a screwtop, do not remove the lid. Unscrew
it just enough to allow drips of water out when you squeeze the bottle. If you
then hold the bottle between your legs, you have a tap with controllable flow
under which you can wash your hands. Better, especially if you have a large
bottle, is to put it sideways on some raised platform. Turn the lid as a tap
and wash hands under it.</p>

<h2>Paper</h2>

<p>Paper is much lighter than water. Many things you would use water for at home
can be done with tissue paper instead. For example, cleaning some things to a
good enough standard. When brushing teeth, it can be used to remove toothpaste
foam from the face.</p>

<h2>Showers</h2>

<p>This one is actually about using lots of water, but it's fun. :-) If you are
living on a beach and feel the need for the luxury of a fresh water shower:</p>

<ol>
<li>Carry large bottle of water to the beach.</li>
<li>Get naked.</li>
<li>Get someone to pour it over you.</li>
</ol>


<p>I leaned this one when I was arriving at a hippie beach in Tenerife, and the
first person I saw was a girl doing this in the moonlight. She didn't mind,
and invited me for dinner with them.</p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
</feed>
