<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Alistair MacLeod, MM0HAI: Posts tagged food]]></title>

  <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/tag/food/index.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mm0hai.net/"/>
  <updated>2013-03-11T22:45:29-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/tag/food</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alistair N. MacLeod]]></name>
  </author>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Fruit is not Allowed]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/12/Fruit-is-not-allowed.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/12/Fruit-is-not-allowed.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2012-12-12T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/12/Fruit-is-not-allowed</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>"Fruit is not allowed", the customs officer said dissaprovingly. This seems
true not only of imports, but generally in Cancun. There are plenty of small
shops but they pretty much just sell crisps and sugary drinks. I ate mostly
sugar and felt sick.</p>

<p>I quickly gave up on finding vegan food and tried for vegetarian. I ordered
some quesadillas after carefull study of the menu and dictionary, but still
got meat. I ate it anyway. I think not to would be adding insult to injury. I
wouldn't be very impressed if someone killed me for food and then decided to
throw me in the bin instead. I felt sick.</p>

<p>Tortilla vegetariano for breakfast, served with refried beans. Interesting,
but eggs and cheese. Felt a bit sick.</p>

<p>Then I found Walmart. Here fruit is allowed - it is quite overwhelming. It's
stacked high - it would crush you if it fell over - and is all perfect. Every
apple is shiny and without blemish, and lit by green light. They must be
genetically engineered, irradiated, and coated with insectiside. Nevertheless,
I imagine the scale of the place and quantity of food could make a hungy
person cry.</p>

<p>The last time I tried to use a McDonalds drive through (in Penrith (England))
they wouldn't let me. Here they did. McDonalds was a theme on my last cycle tour
I wanted to avoid this time, but it seem to have happened already. I wanted
food without having to leave my bike. I didn't want to try the street vendors
because I have plenty of things to do for the moment without being sick. I
tried to order a vegeburger but they didn't understand. It was not the
langugae, I tried Spanish and English, they did not understand the concept of
not eating meat. I ordered chicken and felt nothing. It tasted of nothing, was
probably mostly breadcrumbs. I need to get out of here.</p>

<p>My water bottle holder does not work well for coffee cups. There is another
gadget to rig up.</p>

<p>In Nigeria if there is no meat in a meal people will be unimpressed and think
you are poor. I suspect poor countries go through a phase of everyone wanting
meat as a sign of affluence. Maybe they will grow out of it.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Vegan Crunk Night]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/05/02/Vegan-Crunk-Night.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/05/02/Vegan-Crunk-Night.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2012-05-02T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/05/02/Vegan-Crunk-Night</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/58967572@N03/7135620371/" title="Vegan
Crunk Night by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img
src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7076/7135620371_13a888b2f4_z.jpg"
width="640" height="480" alt="Vegan Crunk Night"></a></p>

<p><q>I organise a vegan crunk night.</q></p>

<p>Now that I am eating vegan, I feel like I can somewhat legitimately organise a
vegan crunk night. I still don't know what one is meant to be, but that didn't
stop me and on Saturday we had one. There were tasty vegan noms, potluck
style. Apparently crunk is a kind of southern hip-hop, but none of us were
keen on that so we decided table top games would be a reasonable
substitute. :)</p>

<p>If you don't know what I'm talking about you need to watch this excellent
video.</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315"
src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/lVmmYMwFj1I" frameborder="0"
allowfullscreen></iframe>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Vegan]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/05/02/Vegan.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/05/02/Vegan.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2012-05-02T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/05/02/Vegan</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Nearly three weeks ago I adopted a vegan diet. Since the 12th of April I
have not eaten anything containing animal products, except for a few vitamin
pills until I got hold of some vegan ones.</p>

<p>I'm not sure why I am doing this. I just had a feeling it was the thing to
do. Usually I don't pay too much attention to feelings and would make
decisions based on conscious reasoning but as an experiment I am trying to pay
more attention to feelings. So this diet could be called a meta-experiment.</p>

<p>If I had to rationalise this notion, I would note that I had a vegetarian diet
for much, perhaps even most, of the time when I was <a
href="/blog/2011/11/15/Serendipitous-Blaggagio.html">travelling
recently</a>. This was simply because of what was available and
practical. Meat and milk do not survive well if you live outside in a hot
climate. I felt good when I was away and perhaps associated eating less meat
with this, even if there is no causal relation.</p>

<p>When I returned to this meat eating household I was very aware of when I ate
meat. In some cases, such as ready meals, it seemed slightly unappealing.</p>

<p>I had also become more aware of food in general, particularly if it was
expensive or rare, like fish for example. I did not object completely to
eating it, but thought that if one is going to eat something of which there is
a limited supply, and which is not necessary, then it ought to be
appreciated. If the reason to eat a certain fish is flavour and pleasure,
making oneself happy, then one should pay attention to the eating and enjoy
it, not watch TV while doing so, otherwise it is mindless destruction.</p>

<p>Whatever the reason, I decided to eat vegan, with the idea I would probably
try it for a month and see how I felt. I started because of a feeling so
I will also use that criterion to decide when to stop, if at all.</p>

<p>I am not calling myself a vegan. Partly this is because I am trying to be
careful not to over-use labels, but mostly it is because this one does not seem
to apply. The Vegan Society says, <q
cite="http://www.vegansociety.com/become-a-vegan/why.aspx">A vegan is someone
who tries to live without exploiting animals, for the benefit of animals,
people and the planet.</q>. The definition requires a certain intention, not
just action. I don't think I am motivated by the given reasons. It is probably
the simplest way to describe my diet though. I am not a vegan, I just eat like
one.</p>

<p>I had some problems in the first few days. On days two and three I woke up
unusually hungry. Someone later told me when he was vegan for a month he was
hungry all the time and ate lots of sugar to relieve it, but I found this
resolved itself by the fourth day and it has not recurred. For the first week
perhaps, I was also producing Type 6 on the <a
href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bristol_Stool_Scale">Bristol Stool
Scale</a> and needed to go to the toilet more often. Perhaps I was eating much
more fibre than I was used to, but that is probably a good thing. It seems to
have settled down now. Otherwise, I have found it quite easy so far and learnt
some things about food, cooking and veganism.</p>

<p>I don't seem to crave meat or cheese. If tasty animal food was put in front of
me, such as good quality meat or some cheese for Mellis's cheesemonger, I would
like to eat it, but I rarely think about it otherwise. I miss eggs and butter
on toast.</p>

<p>One thing that requires some effort though is cooking. This is probably not
because vegan cooking is inherently more difficult than cooking with any
ingredients, but because the things I know how to cook are not
vegan. Therefore I need to learn a lot, fast, to avoid becoming bored with a
few dishes. It's also hard to learn because the way I learnt to cook many
things I know is by discovering them somewhere, like a restaurant, and then
cooking it myself. That way I knew what I liked and what it was meant to be
like. I do not have the experience of vegan food to know what is good and what
things should come out like when I try recipes.</p>

<p>The positive side is that I am being forced to learn. I have discovered new
ingredients I would never have tried before and have probably diversified my
diet. I have become a fan of chickpeas and lentils, and would eat these more
even if I also ate meat. I've tried various grains, beans, soya flour, soya
milk, oat milk, agave syrup, and tempeh. I've also started cooking Indian
food, which I had been meaning to do for some time.</p>

<p>I also eat less processed food. Ready meals and other prepared foods often
have animal products in them, or in many cases, unspecified "flavourings". Not
eating these is probably a significant health benefit. Another side effect of
the diet is reading ingredients carefully. I have learnt what some E numbers
are, and in some cases they are things I would not want to eat whether vegan
or not.</p>

<p>It's also a good excuse to <a
href="/blog/2012/05/02/Vegan-Crunk-Night.html">organise a Vegan Crunk Night</a>!</p>

<p>I've got lots more to say on this subject but will leave it at that for now.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
