<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Alistair MacLeod, MM0HAI: Posts tagged radio</title>
 <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/tag/radio/index.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://mm0hai.net"/>
 <updated>2012-03-20T20:12:23+00:00</updated>
 <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/tag/radio</id>
 <author>
   <name>Alistair N. MacLeod</name>
   <email>anm@mm0hai.net</email>
 </author>

 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 <entry>
   <title>SGC SG-211 Mini Smartuner Teardown</title>
   <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2011/06/02/SGC-211-autotuner.html"/>
   <updated>2011-06-02T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2011/06/02/SGC-211-autotuner</id>
   <content type="html">My&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; SGC autotuner had an accident when I stupidly put it down on a
bench. The boat heeled and it landed on the connector, bending it. Luckily the
connector was mounted on the case and wired up, rather than soldered directly
to the board, so there was no damage other than a bent box. I took it apart
so I could straighten it out and thought I might as well take some photos
while I was at it.

The item in question is an &lt;a
href=&quot;http://www.sgcworld.com/211ProductPage.html&quot;&gt;SG-211&lt;/a&gt;. I'm not going
to review it or say much other than it is pretty good and the case is soft
aluminium.

&lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow&quot; href=&quot;http://www.flickr.com/photos/58967572@N03/5788517160/&quot; title=&quot;Top of board&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://farm3.static.flickr.com/2327/5788517160_677a9ff43e_z.jpg&quot; width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;428&quot; alt=&quot;Top of board&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow&quot; href=&quot;http://www.flickr.com/photos/58967572@N03/5788523098/&quot; title=&quot;Bottom of board&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://farm4.static.flickr.com/3273/5788523098_208ab1258e_z.jpg&quot; width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;441&quot; alt=&quot;Bottom of board&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

The relays are interesting. I have been meaning to design an automatic ground
tuner for my &lt;a
href=&quot;/blog/2011/03/25/HF-Bicycle-Mobile-Experiment-Part-3.html&quot;&gt;bike&lt;/a&gt; but
one problem I have is the inability to find any latching relays. It seems SGC
either had their own made, or have had some branded to hide where they get
these mythical devices.

&lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow&quot; href=&quot;http://www.flickr.com/photos/58967572@N03/5787968241/&quot; title=&quot;Custom relays?&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://farm3.static.flickr.com/2440/5787968241_e4bbc34dee_z.jpg&quot; width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;236&quot; alt=&quot;Custom relays?&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow&quot; href=&quot;http://www.flickr.com/photos/58967572@N03/5787972187/&quot; title=&quot;Bottom half of case&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://farm6.static.flickr.com/5230/5787972187_20fb28eaa0_z.jpg&quot; width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;436&quot; alt=&quot;Bottom half of case&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

The white wire is connected to a front panel toggle switch which was added by
SGC. The new switch disables retuning to avoid a problem where it would retune
in the middle of an over. I'm not sure if the uninsulated wires above this are
part of the mod. I hope they are not fixing a bad board. The switch is useful
but I'm a bit concerned about what this will do for durability. The controller
is a PIC.

&lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow&quot; href=&quot;http://www.flickr.com/photos/58967572@N03/5788529612/&quot; title=&quot;PIC&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://farm6.static.flickr.com/5264/5788529612_7265d6aa5f_z.jpg&quot; width=&quot;415&quot; height=&quot;640&quot; alt=&quot;PIC&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

A reference / dummy load?

&lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow&quot; href=&quot;http://www.flickr.com/photos/58967572@N03/5787974261/&quot; title=&quot;Reference / load?&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://farm6.static.flickr.com/5229/5787974261_2a675e013d_m.jpg&quot; width=&quot;240&quot; height=&quot;149&quot; alt=&quot;Reference / load R?&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;


--

&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; Actually borrowed, but he'll never know my bending was that good. :-)</content>
 </entry>
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 <entry>
   <title>HF Bicycle Mobile Experiment - Part 3 - Illustration</title>
   <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2011/03/25/HF-Bicycle-Mobile-Experiment-Part-3.html"/>
   <updated>2011-03-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2011/03/25/HF-Bicycle-Mobile-Experiment-Part-3</id>
   <content type="html">Today the unusually good weather required me to take the bike out for
a spin. I took some photos and video of the station while I was
out. It's described in more detail in &lt;a rel=&quot;start&quot;
href=&quot;/blog/2011/03/19/HF-Bicycle-Mobile-Experiment-Part-1.html&quot;&gt;Part
1&lt;/a&gt;.

&lt;iframe title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; width=&quot;480&quot; height=&quot;390&quot;
src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/4OeF0XLYJO8&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot;
allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

Pay no attention to the audio behind the wind-noise - I think all I
said was that I was using the FT-817 and 5W.

&lt;img
src=&quot;http://farm6.static.flickr.com/5309/5557283960_fc600b3d91.jpg&quot;
width=&quot;375&quot; height=&quot;500&quot; alt=&quot;HF Bike Mobile on Blackford Hill&quot; /&gt;

15m 1/4 wave and 2 J-Pole. The latter is held together with masking
tape - I'll need to fix that better as well. Two sections of pole is
the minimum for the J-Pole. Three sections seems to be ok on most
roads. Four sections, as shown here, hits trees on some roads. It is
no higher than a bus though so should be ok on main roads.

&lt;img
src=&quot;http://farm6.static.flickr.com/5252/5557297492_6a1be9e006.jpg&quot;
width=&quot;375&quot; height=&quot;500&quot; alt=&quot;101_0474.JPG&quot; /&gt;

The ground tuning capacitor. Red goes to coax braid, yellow to frame.

Everything survived being bashed down the back of the hill, where
there are now steps, some of which I rode over. Low trees ripped off
the J-Pole though.

&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.flickr.com/photos/58967572@N03/sets/72157626343215344/&quot;&gt;More photos&lt;/a&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 <entry>
   <title>HF Bicycle Mobile Experiment - Part 2</title>
   <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2011/03/21/HF-Bicycle-Mobile-Experiment-Part-2.html"/>
   <updated>2011-03-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2011/03/21/HF-Bicycle-Mobile-Experiment-Part-2</id>
   <content type="html">This evening I tested the antenna system described in my &lt;a
rel=&quot;prev&quot; href=&quot;/blog/2011/03/19/HF-Bicycle-Mobile-Experiment-Part-1.html&quot;&gt;last
post&lt;/a&gt;, as well as a 2m J-pole.

Immediately on leaving the house I was answered on 2m by GM8OTI. This
was an unexpectedly good start - most often when I have tried 2m bike
radio I get nothing. The J-Pole was probably much better than previous
antennas and he said he had seen my post on SOTA watch so was
expecting me. I extended only one section of the mast for the journey,
which was just enough for the J-pole.


&lt;iframe style=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;425&quot; height=&quot;350&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot;
scrolling=&quot;no&quot; marginheight=&quot;0&quot; marginwidth=&quot;0&quot;
src=&quot;http://maps.google.co.uk/maps?f=q&amp;amp;source=s_q&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;geocode=&amp;amp;q=&amp;amp;sll=55.982293,-3.196529&amp;amp;sspn=0.000407,0.00121&amp;amp;gl=uk&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;t=h&amp;amp;ll=55.982313,-3.196528&amp;amp;spn=0.000263,0.00057&amp;amp;z=20&amp;amp;output=embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

I planned to operate in the vicinity of Newhaven Lighthouse in the
hope that proximity to sea water would provide a good ground
plane. When I arrived at the lighthouse I could start operating very
quickly as I only had to extend the mast. This is in contrast to the
usual faff of setting up for &lt;a href=&quot;/sota&quot;&gt;SOTA&lt;/a&gt; which involves guy lines.

The band (15 meters) sounded dead - I heard no stations at all. I
thought conditions must be bad but I tried calling CQ anyway and,
although rather slow, I got some results!

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th&gt;Time&lt;/th&gt; &lt;th&gt;f&lt;/th&gt; &lt;th&gt;Station&lt;/th&gt;&lt;th&gt;Sent&lt;/th&gt; &lt;th&gt;Received&lt;/th&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;~1830&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;145.500&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;GM8OTI&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;59&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;59-57&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;~1915&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;21.280&lt;/td&gt;  &lt;td&gt;GM8OTI&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;21&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;?&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;1929&lt;/td&gt;  &lt;td&gt;21.280&lt;/td&gt;  &lt;td&gt;KA1ANW&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;57&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;57&lt;/td&gt; &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;1942&lt;/td&gt;  &lt;td&gt;21.280&lt;/td&gt;  &lt;td&gt;WD8BEY&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;59&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;59&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;2007&lt;/td&gt;  &lt;td&gt;21.315&lt;/td&gt;  &lt;td&gt;N8YHY&lt;/td&gt;  &lt;td&gt;58&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;59? Did not note&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;2009&lt;/td&gt;  &lt;td&gt;21.290&lt;/td&gt;  &lt;td&gt;C06LC&lt;/td&gt;  &lt;td&gt;59&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;59&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

I had never heard the CO prefix before but didn't think much of it
until I got home and looked it up. QRZ.com tells me C06LC is in Cuba,
4441 miles away. I think voltage was down to about 10V or less at this
point so I probably wasn't even using the nominal 5W I usually
claim. I think that is my furthest contact - QRP or otherwise. It's at
least 888 miles / watt and probably over 1000.

&lt;img class=&quot;centre&quot;
src=&quot;http://farm6.static.flickr.com/5016/5548844826_fa0f65df1a_z.jpg&quot;
width=&quot;480&quot; height=&quot;640&quot; alt=&quot;Newhaven Lighthouse&quot; title=&quot;Newhaven
Lighthouse&quot; /&gt;

Effectiveness varied greatly with location. Near the lighthouse
was good but when I tried moving north west along the coast it was far
worse. I heard N8YHY at S1 - when I moved back to the lighthouse it
increased to S8.

I spent some time after these contacts listening on bands from 160m to
10m. I was surprised to hear stations on 160 meters with my short
antenna - one who sounded English on SSB and several morse which I
didn't try and decode. I also tried adding a miracle whip tuner. I
think it tuned on 17m and 20m but battery was now flat so could not
test properly.

It was generally a pleasant evening - warm and dry but windy. The sky
was clear giving good star display and a shooting star. There were
some very good photos I would like to have taken - with railings, bike
and mast in the foreground, lighthouse beyond that and stars behind -
but my camera phone was not up to the job. I was not, on this
occasion, questioned by police or public about my unusual activities,
nor about the fact my bike had wires on it. As we now know, &lt;a
href=&quot;http://afp.google.com/article/ALeqM5i_pDxEAYSiWgBNlLs8ALAyGID7Lw&quot;&gt;wires
are evil&lt;/a&gt; unless they come in a box with the name of a big company
on it.

In conclusion, I declare this operation successful and intend to
experiment further.

&lt;div class=&quot;centre&quot;&gt; 
&lt;img src=&quot;http://farm6.static.flickr.com/5103/5548844604_b085b8452f_z.jpg&quot;
width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;480&quot; alt=&quot;Bicycle mobile - FT-817 in bar bag&quot;
title=&quot;The clock is on GMT + 1 (local time was GMT)&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Solar Data&lt;/h3&gt; For future reference / comparison, the solar data
from N0NBH for this evening (2115 UTC I think it was but I can't find
historical data to check) was:

SFI 101
SN 47
A-Index 3
K-Index 1

15 meter conditions were pronounced to be fair.

&lt;a
rel=&quot;next&quot; href=&quot;/blog/2011/03/25/HF-Bicycle-Mobile-Experiment-Part-3.html&quot;&gt;Part
3 - Illustration - Photos and Video on Blackford Hill&lt;/a&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 <entry>
   <title>HF Bicycle Mobile Experiment - Part 1</title>
   <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2011/03/19/HF-Bicycle-Mobile-Experiment-Part-1.html"/>
   <updated>2011-03-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2011/03/19/HF-Bicycle-Mobile-Experiment-Part-1</id>
   <content type="html">Today I decided to make an HF antenna for my bike. I did an experiment
with this once last year but it was not terribly successful. That
experiment used the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.g4ilo.com/atx.html&quot;&gt;ATX
antenna&lt;/a&gt;. No contacts were made but I learned something about
grounding.

I decided to use the frame as a ground. &lt;a
href=&quot;http://www.qrz.com/callsign/G4AKC&quot;&gt;G4AKC&lt;/a&gt; says that this can
be improved by tuning the frame. I found that with a variable capacitor
in series with the frame I could adjust for low SWR with the ATX set
up as in the instructions. I can't remember what bands I tried it on.

The primary aim this time was to improve the ground. Last time, I had
a very temporary setup with croc clips to the frame so I decided to
improve it with fixed wires. I cleaned and sanded around a bolt on the
carrier and two brazons on the frame and connected the points with
some mains wire. I also attached a flexible wire to connect to the
antenna system.

While I was pondering how best to connect the aerial and earth with
the very limited selection of BNC parts I had I decided I might as
well make a proper antenna, which would make this easier. I took some
of the sections of the fishing pole I use for SOTA and duct taped them
to the carrier. The longest I thought I could reasonably get away with
was 4m which is what I used. I decided to use the lowest HF band I
could with the given antenna space, as the higher bands seem to be
open far less often, so I decided on a 1/4 wave for the 21MHz band.

I started with 3.5m of wire and found the tuning was way off. I
decided to try and tune it against a good earth so I drove in an earth
stake. This actually made it slightly worse. I then laid out three
radials and tried various combinations before giving up on finding an
improvement. I then started trying to tune to what I had. I had to cut
away quite a lot of wire but got the SWR down to 1.1. This was with
the capacitor in series with the frame.

I tied a SLAB to the carrier and put the FT-817 in the bar bag and set
off for a maiden voyage. The SWR remained constant despite shaking,
moving of antenna and presumably different ground, although I did only
go around the block. I could hear several American stations and one in
Africa but my CQs were not answered. Eventually though, some
unexpected success! I replied to N8RA in Connecticut and received a
(contest) 59. He had no trouble copying my callsign first time so it
must have been a reasonable signal. I tried for a while longer but
with no further contacts so stopped for the day.

&lt;h3&gt;Future Work&lt;/h3&gt;
Some ideas:

* Other bands - I think I can fit in 17m and 10m may be useful now too.

* Replace top section of fibreglass and wire with bendy steel
  wire. This should reduce wind resistance, weight and effect of
  crashing into trees.

* Try other earth tuning arrangements. Measure earth current -
  possibly with a clip on ferrite transformer I got from the
  electricity company.

* Physical improvement - replace duct tape. I require a system
  for easy removal, connection and disconnection. Must also be
  weather, oil and dirt proof. Should not reduce load carrying
  capacity of rack - needs to stay out the way of panniers.

&lt;a
rel=&quot;next&quot; href=&quot;/blog/2011/03/21/HF-Bicycle-Mobile-Experiment-Part-2.html&quot;&gt;Part
2 - Testing by the Sea&lt;/a&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
</feed>
