<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss">

  <title><![CDATA[River MacLeod, MM0HAI: Posts tagged sailing]]></title>

  <link href="https://mm0hai.net/blog/tag/sailing/index.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://mm0hai.net/"/>
  <updated>2018-02-07T17:59:18+00:00</updated>
  <id>https://mm0hai.net/blog/tag/sailing</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[River MacLeod]]></name>
  </author>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Boat Life]]></title>
    <link href="https://mm0hai.net/blog/2018/01/12/boat-life.html"/>
    <updated>2018-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://mm0hai.net/blog/2018/01/12/boat-life</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4617/38954774364_5feccd0c4f_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="IMG_20180108_091225" /></p>

<p>There is sailing, and there is living on a boat. I’ve done both recently, but
you might be surprised how little these normally go together. Anyway, this is
what I think of living on a boat after doing it for most of a year.</p>

<p>Mostly, I really like it.</p>

<p>The boat is the first place I have had for myself. It was strange to realise
that I now own a fridge, and an oven, and a vacuum cleaner. I’ve been
travelling for a while, and still do, but now I do it with an oven. :)</p>

<p>I feel like living on a boat is the way you can have the most control over
your environment - the only way you can really own your place. People talk
about owning houses, but I don’t think it is really possible, certainly not in
places I have seen like British cities. Is it really yours when you have
council tax, planning permission, conditions in deeds, factors, residents
associations? Some places you have almost no control over what you can do with
“your” flat, and are made to pay other people for the right to exist. This is
not ownership. With the boat, I can do what I want with it, and put it where I
want. Yes, there are harbour fees, but these are optional, and it’s easy to
move if you don’t like a place. There is also the ancient right to anchor
pretty much anywhere, and except in some places noöne can take money from you
or interfere.</p>

<p>I can provide everything for myself. Electricity from solar panels. Water can
be collected from rain or desalinated on solar power. Toilets, plumbing,
communications is all within your own control. I have my own network on the
boat with backhaul by wifi, mobile networks, or potentially satellite or HF
radio.</p>

<p>On the boat I have everything I need almost literally within arms reach. I can
easily carry food for months. I could, and have, anchored somewhere for weeks
without needing anything from the outside world.</p>

<p><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4612/25759462778_fbd5b27091_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="Napoleon Viken" /></p>

<p>I have also noticed how much energy and water I use, compared to on land. On
the boat I have footpumps for water, and can control exactly how much I
use. On land, the tap flows constantly while using it, and at a much greater
rate. The amount of energy used for heating houses is ridiculous. A whole
house can be heated just for one or two people. On the boat, even if I heat it
all, the space is much smaller, but mostly I don’t even do that. I blow hot
air inside a blanket or cloak, or just sit on an electric blanket. Also tea is
a very efficient way to transfer heat into the body.</p>

<p>The main restriction to freedom with the boat life is, I think, simply owning
something. Anything, and especially a boat, is something that needs to be
looked after, maintained, repaired, stored, checked on… It’s slower to move
the boat that to hitchhike for example. Probably the way to be most free is to
have nothing and trust in the universe. It probably comes with less comfort
than always having your own bed with you when you travel, though.</p>

<p>Most of the time on the boat I was living with a girlfriend. I think this is a
good idea and works well as long as you get on well enough. More recently
though I’ve been on my own, which I also like. It’s an excellent way to be a
hermit. After my first passage on my own I tied up on a small lake off the
Kiel canal. There were no other boats there, and I was very happy on my own. I
had a party with myself and the boat and the lake and the trees.</p>

<p>Problems I’ve had with this particular boat more recently are condensation and
mould. Living on a boat in the winter it really should be insulated. It’s also
cold, but now that it is properly cold, I actually sort of like the ice on the
windows and frost on deck.</p>

<p>Another thing I like is the general awareness of nature that comes from being
on the boat. Apart from explicitly checking the weather when sailing, I still
notice much more just being on the boat. I discovered seasons are a real
thing. This is largely because of being in Scandinavia instead of Scotland,
where we only have a vague idea of seasons - winter is a bit wetter and
colder, but it is a gradual thing and just a matter of degree. Around
Scandinavia it can be Summer one day and Autumn the next. On Samhain eve (the
end of Summer / Autumn) it was warm, in the morning there was ice on the
deck. I notice the temperature of course, but last night I woke up because the
wind changed. The boat makes slightly different sounds, the waves slap the
hull from a different angle, things tap differently. Even when tied up
somewhere calm with no plans to sail I still feel where the wind is coming
from when I’m asleep.</p>

<p>Another good thing about a boat is that you can avoid winter totally if you
want. Just move house to where it is Summer at that time of the year!</p>

<p><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4631/24794473507_a2f5220c10_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="Kiel Canal" /></p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Year in Review: 2017]]></title>
    <link href="https://mm0hai.net/blog/2017/12/31/2017.html"/>
    <updated>2017-12-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://mm0hai.net/blog/2017/12/31/2017</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I have not been blogging for ages, so I think once a year post might be the
new target. Here is 2017.</p>

<p>I began the year feeling quite sick in the tower that is the Hamburg Radisson,
which I was forced into after vomiting on the floor of the congress
centre. The original plan was to hitchhike to Berlin after the party and
couchsurf, but I wasn’t up to that, and this was the only place that had any
rooms free on no notice at New Year. It was also quite convenient. :) I felt
better after the first night but got worse again, possibly because of trying
too hard at breakfast - but I had to make an effort as it cost more than I
might typically spend on food for a week. We also amused ourselves by ordering
the fanciest pillows from the pillow menu (yes, apparently a pillow menu is a
thing), which were delivered with a salute.</p>

<p>After my annual CCC congress holiday in Hamburg, I returned to this winter’s
home of Gran Canaria and toured the island some more. I made my first visit to
Gui Gui, the hidden hippie beach. It was worth going. Pretty windy and wetter
than I would like though. Had a good spa day of massage with sand. :) There
were puppies and kittens! The mother dog took the puppies for walks on the
beach without any humans involved - they lived at a house further inland. Also
explored more caves around the island, did some walking.</p>

<p><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4627/27892873099_93e4781689_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="Puppies!" /></p>

<p><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4613/39640547332_6fc7f1e4ac_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="Sunset at Gui Gui" /></p>

<p><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4661/39671563251_b684d833e5_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="Shelter at Gui Gui" /></p>

<p><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4720/25799608568_283e3a3128_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="Bicycle not made for two" /></p>

<p><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4769/39671217291_016604d132_z.jpg" width="360" height="640" alt="Caveman with Fire" /></p>

<p>Went to Scotland for the rest of the winter / spring, where I didn’t do much
until it was time to go back to Sweden, with some essential supplies.</p>

<p><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4622/25722005958_58cfc83db5_z.jpg" width="480" height="640" alt="Stocking up on Vittles from Blighty" /></p>

<p>There was plenty to do on the boat. Painting the keel and antifouling
everything. This was made harder by the temperature - the paints needed
minimum 5C or more. I think the vactan needed 15C to work properly, or at
least 10C. While trying to sort this out, it was snowing. We managed, just, by
building a heat tent around the keel.</p>

<p><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4748/39564004672_2d94a5316a_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="Boat in Snow" /></p>

<p>Lots of other jobs in the boat - I think I’ll post about that separately.</p>

<p>While working on the boat, we lived in a tent nearby. Sleeping on the boat at
the yard was not allowed, and would also be hard with the state of it
sometimes. There was snow on the tent.</p>

<p><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4741/25722901078_3b0b7b710f_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="Winter home in Stockholm" /></p>

<p>Eventually we launched, and then lifted out again to fix a leak, and then
launched again, and finally left Stockholm.</p>

<p><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4700/39593187301_67edc7fcc4_z.jpg" width="640" height="360" alt="Launching (2017)" /></p>

<p><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4656/39601163952_9e76827d65_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="Leaving Stockholm" /></p>

<p>I enjoyed the archipelago, particularly an island with a wood fired sauna that
was open to the public, with a good view over the sea. We went out every so
often over a period of hours to check on how the sunset was getting on. It got
redder for a while, then started getting lighter again.</p>

<p><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4664/24762580697_d060d9a171_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="Tied to an island" /></p>

<p><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4695/38922900804_5b12c3c7ab_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="Sunset in the Stockholm Archipelago" /></p>

<p><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4623/39631231301_d50da42c4b_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="Dragets kanal" /></p>

<p>Generally learned how to sail the boat and how to tie up to islands in the
Baltic style. The water was very smooth in the archipelago, so we didn’t
really get our first taste of waves until we went to Gotland.</p>

<p><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4656/25761100178_4120c11b22_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="Approaching Bornholm at the start of a gale" /></p>

<p><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4650/25760963368_5e442f83d7_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="Fire at a gapahuk on Öland" /></p>

<p><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4604/27854643739_6e4d5b5c40_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="Approaching Kalmar at about 1 kt" /></p>

<p><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4745/38924189744_e978796105_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="Tandem tour, Bornholm" /></p>

<p>After Gotland we went to Öland, Bornholm, and Rügen. We tried and failed to
get to Poland after that. A strong wind was coming from out destination and we
made very bad progress with the rolled up genoa. Really need to get a working
jib and storm sails. Instead we went round Rügen. After Kiel I was on my own,
and it was getting on for the end of the season, so I looked for somewhere
close for the winter. I would have like to stay in Kiel, but the monopoly
harbours do not provide electricity in the evening or night during the
winter. Seems they really don’t want you to stay on your boat. Instead I took
the boat along the canal to Rendsburg. Rendsburg is super boring, but good for
the boat as they have a bubble marina to try and stop the boat being damaged
by ice. I enjoyed motoring along the canal on my own. Didn’t handle tying up
in the locks very elegantly, but I managed it.</p>

<p><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4704/25791302618_2b3274121a_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="Ship on Kiel Canal" /></p>

<p><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4702/38954513274_40051dafb2_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="Rendsburg RVR" /></p>

<p>Visited Edinburgh for Christmas, which is something I’ve not done for a long
time. Somehow felt like it this year. Generally felt like facing winter rather
than avoiding it.</p>

<p>Wasn’t sure if I’d go to congress because I was a bit tired of it after going
for four years, but I finally decided to go in the end when discovered a
friend would be there I hadn’t seen for some time. It was a good decision, to
return to society a bit and talk to more people after mostly hermiting
recently. I felt better after it, even though it was not as good as previous
years and I didn’t much like the Leipzig Messe. “Je Suis CCH”, as a sticker
said.</p>

<p><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4754/38766438045_90a79e0ae2_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="CCL Leipzig" /></p>

<p><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4706/38766443805_88aa5f61a4_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="Teahouse, books, big cat blanket" /></p>

<p>I got back to the boat in time for fireworks over the lake.</p>

<p><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4749/39633054542_f35bb9d787_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="Fireworks over Rendsburg" /></p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Brygge]]></title>
    <link href="https://mm0hai.net/blog/2017/11/06/Brygge.html"/>
    <updated>2017-11-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://mm0hai.net/blog/2017/11/06/Brygge</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In English, it’s hard to know what to call that thing you are tying your boat
up to. It could be:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Pier</li>
  <li>Jetty</li>
  <li>Berth</li>
  <li>Dock</li>
  <li>Wharf</li>
  <li>Quay</li>
  <li>Pontoon</li>
  <li>Mole</li>
  <li>Slip (American English)</li>
</ul>

<p>The definitions of all these terms depend on if you are speaking English or
American, and also seem to be rather fuzzy. However, there is an easy solution:</p>

<p><strong>Brygge</strong></p>

<p>It’s much easier if you just use the Scandinavian term. Everything is a brygge
(or brygga, bryggen). It’s possible, but not necessary to be more precise
about what kind of brygge it is, for example a flytebrygge is a floaty brygge,
or pontoon, but it’s always a brygge. This word I have imported into English,
and it makes life a lot easier.</p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[2 Cats 1 Boat]]></title>
    <link href="https://mm0hai.net/blog/2016/09/25/two-cats-one-boat.html"/>
    <updated>2016-09-25T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>https://mm0hai.net/blog/2016/09/25/two-cats-one-boat</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://c5.staticflickr.com/6/5836/30583122980_5ebe6a8ef3_z.jpg" width="640" height="360" alt="2 Cats 1 Boat - Scampi 30" /></p>

<p>After sailing on other people’s boats for a while, I finally got my own. I’m
planning to live aboard and travel. It seems like a good way to have more
comfort than most ways of travelling - you take your bed, kitchen, etc. with
you - but you are not stuck in one place as you are with a house. For the
moment the boat is on land in Stockholm, but in the Spring we should be ready
to go.</p>

<p>The boat is a Shipman Scampi, better known as Albin Scampi, as Albin also
built them. 30ft, made in Sweden around 40 years ago. Quite light displacement
and meant for racing, but hopefully will serve for cruising. She needs some
work, but overall not a bad deal.</p>

<p>I bought this boat after hitchhiking around Sweden, looking mostly at the Albin
Vega, until Autumn when prices on larger boats like this dropped. I heard
Sweden is a good place to buy a boat, and they certainly do seem cheaper here
than in the UK and probably most of Europe. Swedish boats do not, however,
seem to be well equipped to go to sea, as British ones more often are. I think
this is because they are usually just used around the islands here, so there
is more work to do, like adding anchors, tender, vhf radio!</p>
]]></content>
   <georss:point>59.324140 18.045904</georss:point>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Sailing San Blas]]></title>
    <link href="https://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/09/30/San-Blas.html"/>
    <updated>2013-09-30T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>https://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/09/30/San-Blas</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There are various ways to get from Panama to Colombia: flying, cargo boat in
the Pacific, small cargo launches between islands in the Caribbean, and a
sailing yacht in the Caribbean are some of the options. Travel by land is a
serious undertaking and very rarely done. The area between the countries is
called the Darien Gap: here there is a break in the Panamerican Highway, and
nothing but thick jungle and various natural and man made dangers. The <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Darien_scheme">difficulty Scots had living
here</a> is one reason why Scotland joined with England and became Great
Britain.</p>

<p>I wanted to take a boat anyway, and preferably a bigger sailing to keep my
bike away from the salt. I tried hitchiking from Portobelo and Puerto Lindo,
but in the end decided just to pay the tourist rate for a berth on the
Santana. Although very expensive, it was not a bad decision. The San Blas
islands along the Panama coast are the classic tropical islands, many with
nothing but sand and a few palm trees.</p>

<p>I joined the boat in Puerto Lindo. It turned out the wrapping was not really
necessary.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/9990470005" title="Bike under tarp, tied to rail on Santana by River, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7325/9990470005_1bfcdabc15_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="Bike under tarp, tied to rail on Santana" /></a></p>

<p>Officially leaving Panama was the easiest border so far. The captain took our
passports to this office while we did nothing.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/9990480846" title="The Migration Office in the San Blas by River, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3702/9990480846_5f91746548_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="The Migration Office in the San Blas" /></a></p>

<p>It is obviously a popular place for cruisers.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/9990900024" title="Panama Flag in San Blas by River, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2887/9990900024_4f563753f9_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="Panama Flag in San Blas" /></a></p>

<p>The Kuna people inhabit these islands. I don’t know how they manage with so
little resources, but one thing they do now is sell lobsters and beaded
jewellery to tourists on the big boats.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/9990446474" title="Kuna Canoe by River, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3834/9990446474_cd215d3b55_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="Kuna Canoe" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/9991107533" title="Kuna canoe by River, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2834/9991107533_255abfe2e8_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="Kuna canoe" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/9991217535" title="Kuna house with Solar Panel, San Blas by River, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7354/9991217535_4f94d4039c_z.jpg" width="640" height="479" alt="Kuna house with Solar Panel, San Blas" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/9991201765" title="Santana by River, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3694/9991201765_2dd2e70e23_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="Santana" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/10108067576" title="Framed by palms by River, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2857/10108067576_8ebdbbc2d7_z.jpg" width="480" height="640" alt="Framed by palms" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/10108165163" title="Bird visits the boat by River, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7293/10108165163_ef71b92793_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="Bird visits the boat" /></a>
k</p>
]]></content>
   <georss:point>9.954 -77.061</georss:point>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
