<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss">

  <title><![CDATA[River MacLeod, MM0HAI: Posts tagged travel]]></title>

  <link href="https://mm0hai.net/blog/tag/travel/index.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://mm0hai.net/"/>
  <updated>2016-11-11T02:02:22+01:00</updated>
  <id>https://mm0hai.net/blog/tag/travel</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[River MacLeod]]></name>
  </author>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hællæ]]></title>
    <link href="https://mm0hai.net/blog/2016/11/09/haellae.html"/>
    <updated>2016-11-09T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>https://mm0hai.net/blog/2016/11/09/haellae</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Jeg er i Fredrikstad. Jeg lære meg noen Norsk. Jeg liker knekkebrød og syltetøy.</p>

<p><img src="https://c8.staticflickr.com/6/5647/30783134311_f59e99d474_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="Fredrikstad" /></p>
]]></content>
   <georss:point>59.220538 10.934319</georss:point>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[2 Cats 1 Boat]]></title>
    <link href="https://mm0hai.net/blog/2016/09/25/two-cats-one-boat.html"/>
    <updated>2016-09-25T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://mm0hai.net/blog/2016/09/25/two-cats-one-boat</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://c5.staticflickr.com/6/5836/30583122980_5ebe6a8ef3_z.jpg" width="640" height="360" alt="2 Cats 1 Boat - Scampi 30" /></p>

<p>After sailing on other people’s boats for a while, I finally got my own. I’m
planning to live aboard and travel. It seems like a good way to have more
comfort than most ways of travelling - you take your bed, kitchen, etc. with
you - but you are not stuck in one place as you are with a house. For the
moment the boat is on land in Stockholm, but in the Spring we should be ready
to go.</p>

<p>The boat is a Shipman Scampi, better known as Albin Scampi, as Albin also
built them. 30ft, made in Sweden around 40 years ago. Quite light displacement
and meant for racing, but hopefully will serve for cruising. She needs some
work, but overall not a bad deal.</p>

<p>I bought this boat after hitchhiking around Sweden, looking mostly at the Albin
Vega, until Autumn when prices on larger boats like this dropped. I heard
Sweden is a good place to buy a boat, and they certainly do seem cheaper here
than in the UK and probably most of Europe. Swedish boats do not, however,
seem to be well equipped to go to sea, as British ones more often are. I think
this is because they are usually just used around the islands here, so there
is more work to do, like adding anchors, tender, vhf radio!</p>
]]></content>
   <georss:point>59.324140 18.045904</georss:point>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Only in Norway]]></title>
    <link href="https://mm0hai.net/blog/2016/08/03/norway.html"/>
    <updated>2016-08-03T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://mm0hai.net/blog/2016/08/03/norway</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://c8.staticflickr.com/6/5570/30263959703_fb5e544db7_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="Oslo City Bike and Brunost" /></p>

<p>Smooth electric trains with good views of fjords.</p>

<p>Everything is clean. Oslo has public slacklines in the city. They are not
broken or vandalised. You can leave bags lying around and they probably won’t
be stolen. It’s like the opposite of Colombia. UK is somewhere inbetween -
closer to Norway, but not as close as I would have thought.</p>

<p><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/6/5786/30863634296_eb6cf477ff_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="Aker" /></p>

<p>People play croquet in parks. Someone on benefits can live in a nice flat in a
good part of town, and afford to drink beer, which is about 10GBP / pint. I
am told NAV - the equivalent of the Jobcentre in the UK, are actually nice,
and not trying to <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2014/sep/09/david-clapson-benefit-sanctions-death-government-policies">kill
you</a>. Teslas are charging in the street here too. My cat complains, that
she only has a dingy with an outboard, all her friends had their own
speedboats, which are needed to get around when at the hytta, which could also
be a summer house. Everyone has at least one hytta.</p>

<p>Food is several times more expensive than almost anywhere else, in some cases,
like tacos, about 25x the price in Mexico.  Sprøstekt løk - fried onions - are
tasty. They cost 3 kroner a bag. Nothing else costs less than 10.</p>

<p>The nature is beautiful. It’s not unlike Scotland, but with more sea and
islands and forest, and less rain and grey. One thing I remember is seeing
sunlight reflected off the sea as it was setting, which cast a double shadow
on the rock.</p>

<p>There are lots of boats, and berries. Blueberries everywhere in the
forest. People actually pick them! I think most people in the UK are scared of
food that does not come in plastic.</p>

<p><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/6/5827/30601754120_7be97890a8_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="Hytta evening" />&lt;/a&gt;</p>

<p>I’ve still not been to Kenya.</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/hPtBnhehPOU" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

]]></content>
   <georss:point>59.913062 10.750778</georss:point>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Free Food]]></title>
    <link href="https://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/08/12/Free-Food.html"/>
    <updated>2012-08-12T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/08/12/Free-Food</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This post is about getting food for free, that is without spending money, but
actually I mean more than that by free food. Food is the key thing which keeps
many people in slavery. You need it to live (although some people dispute
that) and the current system is set up such that you need to pay for it. This
requires money, which in turn requires you to participate in the economic
system which binds people to jobs they don’t want and generally makes people
so many people miserable. When you know how to get food for free, you become
more free.</p>

<p>I don’t claim that the methods I outline in this post will fix the system or
work if everyone were to do this, but for now they can at least help some of
us.</p>

<h2 id="skipping">Skipping</h2>

<p>In Europe this is called recycling, in America, dumpster diving. The best
places to go are supermarkets at closing time. Huge amounts of good food are
thrown away every day. This might be because an apple is bruised or a banana is
deemed too brown. Much of it will be food that has reached its best before
date. Apart from the fact that these dates are usually very conservative and
therefore the food will probably be good for some time, if you go at closing
time you get food which was on the shelves only minutes earlier, so it may not
even go out of date until the next day. You can live on entirely on what you
find in these bins.</p>

<p>There are some things you will very rarely find, like dried foods and things
with a long shelf life. It’s nice to be able to buy these things, but it’s a
luxury.</p>

<h2 id="growing">Growing</h2>

<p>If you are settled, you can of course grow food. Not much good if you are
travelling though.</p>

<h2 id="foraging">Foraging</h2>

<p>Depending on where you are, you may be able to find fruit, mushrooms, and
other foods growing wild.</p>

<h2 id="asking-in-restaurants-and-shops">Asking in Restaurants and Shops</h2>

<p>This is similar to skipping, but you get it before it is thrown in the
bin. Going to bakeries at closing time is often very worthwhile. Some
restaurants will also cook lots of food that if unsold gets thrown away.</p>

<h2 id="charity">Charity</h2>

<p>There are charities which give food to “the homeless” (whatever that
means). Some temples and churches do this. It is not something I really like
because, unlike skipping, the food has been paid for by someone. I’m not
really comfortable with the idea of other people buying food for me. If you
need it though, you should know these places are there.</p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Living and Travelling without Money]]></title>
    <link href="https://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/08/11/Living-for-Free.html"/>
    <updated>2012-08-11T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/08/11/Living-for-Free</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Many people assume that travel is expensive, but it doesn’t need to be. I
wintered in the Canary Islands for three months and spent almost nothing. It’s
just a matter of learning how to live without using money. You won’t be
staying in five star hotels all the time, but it is quite possible to be happy
and there are actually many advantages of a money free lifestyle.</p>

<p>Without money, I think you are likely to meet more people, see more of the
places you travel to, and learn more. If you stay in an hotel and go on guided
tours you see the inside of an hotel and meet tourists. Then you come home a
week later because you can’t afford any more and you think you’ve got to do
some job you would rather not be doing right then. If you sleep on a beach, in
a cave, or even on the street you will certainly have a more interesting
experience. You’ll probably meet other travellers or locals who can help you
with things and show you interesting places.</p>

<p>Money forces things. This is maybe ok if you know exactly what you want all
the time, but you probably don’t. The most obvious example is where to go. I
left Edinburgh with the idea of going to Patagonia. If I had bought a flight,
I would have gone straight there. I attempted to hitchhike, and because I was
not successful I had other adventures and learnt and did things which I might
not have otherwise. I think what should have happened did. Things tend to work
out for the best.</p>

<p>I think I’ll write separately about the practicalities of living without
money. The main expenses which need to be removed are accommodation, <a href="/blog/2012/08/12/Free-Food.html">food</a>, and transport. For now I’ll
cover more general ideas.</p>

<h2 id="the-bare-necessities-of-life-will-come-to-you">“The bare necessities of life will come to you.”</h2>

<p>I’ve worked some of this out for myself on my recent travels, but I’m hardly
unique in doing so. First, I’ll tell you a story. I met a guy in Las Palmas
called Toto. He helped me at a lower point with his story.</p>

<p>A few years ago he left home with 20 euros and his bike. Since then he has
travelled round the world. He sailed from Australia to Europe, then to the
Caribbean and back to Europe, and probably other places he didn’t talk
about. He did some busking and when I met him had 100 euros. He didn’t have
any special performing skill, he just did some silly dance. It’s not really
important where he went, the story is that this is possible.</p>

<p>“Even if I only ate bread one day it doesn’t matter, maybe I’ll find something
else the next day.”</p>

<p>I met another guy who makes a bit of money from playing music on the
street. You might call him homeless if you saw him, but since I’ve been back
in Edinburgh working on my geek bike project, he’s been flying all over
Europe. He’s probably happier than most people who work in an office.</p>

<p>It is important to be positive. You’ll be interacting with people for things
like hitchhiking, and people like happy people. “You won’t get a boat with a
sad face.” It’s also important for your own motivation.</p>

<h2 id="the-kindness-of-strangers">The kindness of Strangers</h2>

<p>When I was in the marina one day I went and said hello to some people. After I
short conversation I had to go and buy some food. They said no, you don’t need
to, we have food. I was reluctant to take it from people who may need to more
than me but they insisted and later I found it is not really in short supply.</p>

<p>On La Palma I wanted some sort of shelter to take walking with me in the
wetter Northern part of the island. I mentioned this to someone I had just met
and so within a few minutes of meeting he had lent me his tent and a better
sleeping bag. I nearly skipped over the fact that this happened in a house I
was staying in - where I had been invited to stay by someone else I had just
met. There are many more examples but you’ll need to read them in my other
blov entries when I get round to writing more.</p>

<h2 id="what-you-do-need-money-for">What you do need money for</h2>

<p>Basically, it comes down to convenience and speeding things up. There are a
few things you probably need it for though.</p>

<p>If you want food, you don’t need money. If you want something particular to
eat, you’ll probably need to buy it. If you want something now, you need to
buy it. If you can wait until you find it in a skip, you don’t. If you have
time to hitchhike, you’ll get there in the end. If you want to go now, you
have to pay for a bus. Of course, if you don’t know where you are going,
hitchhiking is better anyway.</p>

<p>Things you pretty much do need money for are transport, some foods, and
medicines. Sometimes you might need to pay for transport: a ferry, for
example. It’s very rare to find certain things in a bin, e.g. alcohol, coffee,
cooking oil, dried foods, and things with a long sell by date, but you can
live without these.</p>

<p>This post is rather unfocused because I have a lot to say on this subject and
I’m just trying to get some ideas out for now. Hopefully it is enough to show
you that this is possible. If you go out into the world with nothing but a
good attitude and an open mind you’ll probably do very well.</p>

<p>I’ll end with a particularly impressive story from a friend, and a link to
another blog post about this sort of thing, “<a href="http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=18463814">The
Universe Is Conspiring to Help Us”.</a></p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“The magic is FULL ON when u arrive in a city and we have no where to sleep
and a beautiful girl called Ling comes up to u and says: I heard u play music
its is beautiful! Do u have anywhere to sleep? U can have my apartment for the
weekend when i go visit my boyfriend! So she gave us the key. AMAZING
LIFE!!!”</p>
</blockquote>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
</feed>
