<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss">

  <title><![CDATA[River MacLeod, MM0HAI: Posts tagged life]]></title>

  <link href="https://mm0hai.net/blog/tag/life/index.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://mm0hai.net/"/>
  <updated>2016-11-28T02:35:12+01:00</updated>
  <id>https://mm0hai.net/blog/tag/life</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[River MacLeod]]></name>
  </author>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Nacimiento de un río]]></title>
    <link href="https://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/10/15/Rio.html"/>
    <updated>2013-10-15T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/10/15/Rio</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I am very happy today, because it is my birthday. Well, technically it was
yesterday, but it was so late that this is the first new day.</p>

<p>When I was in Mexico, at least six months ago, I was thinking about changing
my name, and to River. I can’t remember exactly why, but I think it was
because I was talking to someone about the importance of words and sounds. I
was interested in seeing if a change in name would change how people saw me,
and treated me, and how I acted and felt about myself.</p>

<p>I forgot about this idea while I was travelling, but was reminded of it again
In Panama where I met someone who had given herself a hippie name and
encouraged me to use my new name. I started to do so, in earnest, when I got on
the boat to Colombia. I crossed the water and entered a new continent with a
new name.</p>

<p>I only used it with new people though. I still wasn’t totally sure whether to
completely change it. I knew I wanted to, but I thought I should check whether
this was the right name - maybe there is a better one - and what people think
about it. I asked a few people, but I really didn’t consider any other
names. I think I came up with the name when I was thinking about flowing, and
the idea of the bike and I flowing through the world. Now though it felt like
there was not really a choice - this was just meant to be.</p>

<p>Someone sent me a song about a río. I went to sleep with the sound of the
river outside my window. I changed my name.</p>

<p>It felt like a relief. I no longer had this pressure of thinking about who I
was. I feel freed of the past. I was not particularly happy for most of
the nearly three decades past. I am happier now, and don’t need to carry this
any more.</p>

<p>I am already finding things I like about this name. I think of rivers
differently - now they are brothers and sisters. :) I say hello to the river
when I walk past, and to the bamboo, and the bananas, and the other plants
that grow around it.</p>

<p>I went to one of the organic hipster veggie restaurants around here, to
celebrate my birthday. I’m writing here now. After I sat down, I noticed that
I can hear the river and see the bamboo from my table. The water dispenser has
stones in the bottom.</p>

<iframe width="640" height="360" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/S6L9wccThyA?feature=player_detailpage" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>
]]></content>
   <georss:point>6.207265 -75.565822</georss:point>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Cycles Closing in Colombia]]></title>
    <link href="https://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/10/12/Cycles-Closing-Colombia.html"/>
    <updated>2013-10-12T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/10/12/Cycles-Closing-Colombia</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I keep finding myself talking about things which happened in the Canary
Islands. It’s at least partly because many things started there, and now they
are coming to some completion.</p>

<p>I went to the Canaries to try and hitch a lift on a boat to South America. I
didn’t manage that, but nearly two years later, I arrived in Colombia on a
sailing catamaran.</p>

<p>When I was in La Tomatera, Las Palmas de Gran Canaria, I learned to make
macramé, and started to decorate my computer power cable. On the boat to
Colombia, I finished it. About half an hour after completion, the cable
failed. It held out just long enough to allow me to complete it.</p>

<p>I also made a bracelet, which I have worn permanently since then. Today, I
gave it away to a stranger I met on the metro in Medellín, Colombia. I really
don’t know why. I didn’t know her name, and do not expect to see her again. I
said she could have it if she could get it off. The knot untied.</p>

<p>Now I think where that bracelet had been - so many places. Beaches, mountains,
cities, forests. Up to about 35,000 feet, and down to 30 meters under the
sea. Boats, trains, cars, planes, and of course the bike. Three continents,
and two oceans, and too many islands to remember. Many beds and hammocks, of
which most mine. But this is all past. I shouldn’t be dwelling on it. I am
here now.</p>

<p>In Las Palmas, I learned to make dreadlocks and had one made for me. In Costa
Rica, I made one for someone.</p>

<p>In Costa Rica also, I ate fruit given to us, the rainbow caravan, by market
sellers. Today, in Colombia, I bought some bananas and gave them to a beggar
who told me she was hungry, and whom I saw foraging unsuccessfully near the
river, where there are some banana plants.</p>

<p>I have been cycling my bike. Maybe that will end soon too. I don’t know, that
is for the future.</p>
]]></content>
   <georss:point>8.857256 -75.635376</georss:point>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Vipassana]]></title>
    <link href="https://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/08/05/Vipassana.html"/>
    <updated>2013-08-05T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/08/05/Vipassana</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/9392460997/" title="Cushion-25 by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5496/9392460997_3ab694ea18_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="Cushion-25" /></a></p>

<p>I spent 10 full days sitting on a cushion meditating, on a course run by
S. N. Goenka (by audio recording) and his assistant teacher, Mirjam Berns, who
was present in Costa Rica. I had heard about these courses several times from
travellers over the past year and a half, and now I was near one I thought it
was time to try it.</p>

<p>I didn’t really know what meditation was before this course and that is why I
went - curiosity.  There are many forms of meditation. I think what they have
in common, at least those I know of, is concentrating on something. It could
be an image in the mind, a sound like a mantra or drum, breathing, or in the
case of vipassana, the sensations on the body. They have different purposes,
the simplest being to develop discipline of the mind and an ability to
concentrate. I don’t know much more about meditation in general though, so
will talk about what we were taught on this course.</p>

<p>The first thing we did was ānāpāna meditation. This meant focusing on the
breath, and specifically the sensations of it moving inside the nostril, and
on the upper lip. It is not about controlling the breath, only observing it as
it comes naturally. The purpose was to develop discipline, and improve our
ability to feel sensations on the body. We did this for most of four days. It
hurt, physically, especially in the knees because of sitting for so long. The
pain was worse because there was no distraction. It was also very boring. I
spent most of the time thinking rather than concentrating.</p>

<p>On the evening of the fourth day and for almost all of the rest of the course,
we were taught and practised vipassana. This involves observing sensations all
over the body. Sensation means any feeling such as hot, cold, itching, pain,
movement of air, etc. While doing this, we were to maintain equanimity and the
awareness of anicca, a Pali word which means change. Equanimity meant we were
not to judge sensation as good or bad, not to be averse to pain, or crave
pleasant sensations. We were also to observe that all sensations are temporary
- they will go away eventually. This was one way to avoid reacting too much to
the pain.</p>

<p>The theory is that, as Goenka says Gautama Buddha taught, suffering is caused
by desire. This could be craving for something not there, or aversion to
something that is. By learning to avoid these feelings, suffering can stop. I
wondered why just observe the sensations on the body? The idea is that all
thoughts or emotions will manifest in the body in some way. By learning not to
react to feelings in the body, all reactions should be covered.</p>

<p>The reactions of craving and aversion are called sankaras. They also said that
sankaras build up - there is a store of old ones. This causes continued
suffering, and rebirth. If you can get rid of them all, then you will be free
of suffering and not have to be reborn. They said that when you stop creating
new sankaras, the new ones come to the surface, and if you remain equanimous,
they disappear.</p>

<p>I found that they did surface. I had maybe five or so in total. When my mind
was clear, they would come suddenly as an image or word out of nowhere, not
connected to any previous thought. The first one I had, for example, was the
image of a dropped mobile phone. Obviously I felt some aversion or pain that I
may have broken an expensive thing.</p>

<p>The sensations on the body can be of two types. “Gross” and “subtle”. The
gross sensations are things like pain. There is also a feeling that I got when
there was nothing else, a slight pleasant tingling. When this happens all over
the body, interesting things happen. At one point, briefly, on day eight I
think, I felt my whole body shaking, and oscillating around a vertical line
through the middle. It was rather like a feeling I have had occasionally when
falling asleep - the whole body spins.</p>

<p>The interpretation given by the teacher was that the subtle tingling is you
feeling subatomic particles, and that the shaking and vibrating is feeling the
underlying fabric of the universe. There is a common idea amongst some
spiritual people that the universe is fundamentally “vibrational”, and
improving you life or increasing your consciousness means to operate at a
higher frequency. They never say what it is that is meant to be vibrating
though. Maybe it is something like string theory. Maybe that’s where string
theory came from, I don’t know. Anyway, I don’t take this feeling as evidence
of the nature of the universe - it could also be explained by the brain
failing to function correctly after being subjected to this unusual practice.</p>

<p>If you practice more, it is possible for the effect to go much further. Rather
than just the surface, if you can feel only subtle sensation inside the body
as well, then it can feel like the whole body has dissolved. As far as I
understand it from asking people, you don’t really feel a physical body
anymore.</p>

<p>As far as I practised the technique, I did have experiences consistent with
what the teachers said. I don’t see any reason why they would lie about the
rest, so it seems that with further practice I could experience, or think I
was experiencing, the universe at a more fundamental level, and free myself of
suffering. Maybe I would even clear old sankaras from past lives, which when
it happens apparently allows you to remember those lives. I still don’t know
that I agree with all the theory though. One thing the teacher said on one of
his talks though, was that if you don’t like the theory just ignore it - the
practice will still work.</p>

<p>Will I keep practising? They say you should do two hours a day. I’m not
sure. I can see that there could be benefits, but on the other hand it
hurts. This is not relaxing, it is not easy. It is physically and mentally
painful and unpleasant. I had a rather unpleasant image at the end of the
course and decided to give my mind a rest for a while. Maybe I’ll try it again
sometime, but I am not very keen. On the other hand, if the theory is all
correct, this technique is how I can free myself from suffering and escape the
cycle of rebirth and endless suffering, so if true it seems that it is the
most important, or only thing I should do. That would mean becoming a monk, or
at least devoting significant time to meditating.</p>

<p>I also want to describe the way the course was run. It was like living the
life of a monk for 10 days. Men and women were separated. Talking was not
allowed. Food was eaten at breakfast and lunchtime, but not after 12pm, except
a little fruit for new students (those on their first 10 day course). Reading,
writing, music and any other communications were not allowed. Really, there was
nothing to do but meditation, eat, and rest. The teaching was almost entirely
from S. N. Goenka, in the form of audio recordings. Sometimes he taught during
meditation sessions, but he spoke mostly in the evening discourse, which was
sometimes a lesson, and often rather like a sermon. On the last full day, the
tenth, we were allowed to talk again and genders were no longer separated in
some public spaces. Everyone seemed quite happy to talk, but I found the noise
rather overwhelming initially.</p>

<p>On the last full day I saw a sloth! It was climbing a tree right beside the
path in the centre. I have never seen one before but I like them. I like how
they are lazy and imagining that they just hang out in trees all day being
fluffy and cuddly.</p>

<p>I got the bus back to San Jose the next day, the eleventh, after tidying up
and things in the morning. I didn’t want to think about meditation or do it
more. On the bus though, I found my mind was very quiet.  I tried meditating
for lack of anything else to do - I didn’t want to read or write - but I
couldn’t because of the movement of the bus. It covered the sensations in the
body I was looking for. Maybe it is acceptable to feel the bus shaking you
around. Anyway, I didn’t want to think about it or write about it for some
time and did other things until now, just over a week later.</p>
]]></content>
   <georss:point>9.328286 -83.749638</georss:point>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Mother Aya, Aunt Jurema]]></title>
    <link href="https://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/08/05/Mother-Aya.html"/>
    <updated>2013-08-05T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/08/05/Mother-Aya</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/9497148473/" title="Magic Potions from the Rainforest by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7439/9497148473_c779f76ed7_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="Magic Potions from the Rainforest" /></a></p>

<p>Burning bush? Yes, you can talk with plants.</p>

<p>It tasted like black treacle, but sweeter, and with a hint of marmite.</p>

<p>I had read “DMT: The Spirit Molecule”, and wondered if I would experience any
of the common patterns. Maybe I would meet alien entities, or find myself in a
nursery. Maybe I would learn the secrets of the universe. What is its true
nature? What is it all about?</p>

<p>I started to feel the effect of the Ayahuasca in my body after the first dose,
but did not notice any mental effect until shortly after the second, which was
double the size and washed down with a glass of the bitter, astringent,
Jurema. I am wary of mixing things, especially if I’ve not had them before,
but these plants both contain the same chemically active ingredient, DMT, and
spiritually I guess they are sisters so I thought they would be able to get
along.</p>

<p>At first all was black, but then colour noise appeared - red, green and blue
dots, always switching on and off. Then these formed into lines, which made up
constantly changing shapes. They were square and triangular and zig
zag. Seemed quite binary, angular, computer generated. The lines were in
rainbow colours, the rainbows moved and sparkled. It was very beautiful. With
open eyes, the picture seem quantised into simpler geometrical shapes. Leaves
and gaps between them angular, and they moved like an animation with
insufficient framerate. The images were very beautiful, and if I would have
noticed pain, my face would probably have been hurting from smiling.</p>

<p>I enjoyed this a lot, but I didn’t just want pretty pictures. I wanted to
learn something. I said this and asked, “what can you show me?”. I didn’t get
a direct answer - no voice or character speaking to me - but the answer became
obvious. You are a baby. You know nothing about how the world works. You’re
not ready for that sort of thing. Here - play with the pretty sparklies. I
realised I knew nothing, and I might as well enjoy it. When I accepted it, I
realised that being a baby is wonderful. You don’t need to do anything or
worry about anything. You are looked after. Like any mother, Mother Aya just
wants her babies to healthy and happy.</p>

<p>I thought I was just happy because of the beauty, but then I realised it was
not just beauty, it was love. I thought I was loving the pictures, but then I
realised that was ridiculous - I am just a tiny spec - almost nothing - how
could I produce so much love? It was clear that this was all there - an
immense field of love - is this what everything is made of? I could only bathe
in it.</p>

<p>Ayahuasca is what is politely called purgative, or cleansing. I was sick
once. When I crawled out of the circle to vomit I felt like a snake. It was
worse for the boy next to me though, who had diarrhoea which at one point
splatted on my face. At first I tried to work out some way in which that had
not actually just happened, but my attempt to deny reality was clearly not
going to work.</p>

<p>There was a lesson though. I had been thinking earlier about how a baby has an
easy life, but it does things like shitting and pissing everywhere. Now I
experienced that this is not always enjoyable for everyone else who has to be
around it. While it is good and right to be a baby when you have to, when you
can you should grow up. I saw birds hatching and flying and making new nests.</p>

<p>I think it is clear that humans as a race are babies. How can we be told the
secrets of the universe when we can’t even look after ourselves? We are
shitting all over this planet and can’t even feed ourselves without making
such a mess that it will kill us all and everything else that lives
here. Maybe in a few million years, if we survive that long, we will will be
ready to understand.</p>

<p>I asked someone to heat water for me so I could wash my hair and face. Someone
else fed me chocolate. I could enjoy being looked after a little more, but
tomorrow I must grow up.</p>
]]></content>
   <georss:point>8.764126 -83.014069</georss:point>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Dreads]]></title>
    <link href="https://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/07/12/Dreads.html"/>
    <updated>2013-07-12T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/07/12/Dreads</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I have dreadlocks. The first one appeared on the 1st of December 2011. They
are more interesting than just hair, and I am still learning from them.</p>

<p>Not many people in Scotland have dreads. One of the first times I remember
seeing them was at my first university mountaineering club meet. She had long
blonde dreads. I didn’t know what to think - I didn’t think - but I felt like
she was some magical creature from another dimension.</p>

<p>When I went to the Canary Islands a few years later, I met lots of dready
travellers. One morning, I woke up on the beach. I washed my hair and applied
conditioner and hairbrush to stop it knotting itself up. This was rather a
fuss. Other people just got up and were ready.</p>

<p>I noticed some other practical advantages. They are a good way of identifying
people who might be interesting to talk to. There is a good chance someone
with dreads is a fellow traveller, or will know things like where to get free
food and good places to sleep, where the squats are, and the local juggling
club. It’s sort of like a club itself - when you notice other people with
dreads on the street, you can say hi.</p>

<p>In Belize I discovered it’s a bit more than that, because people think you are
Rasta. Many people confuse the terms, and call the hair “rastas”. Really,
Rasta is a religion, and dreadlocks are commonly worn by people who follow
it. You can have dreads without being Rasta though, and you can be Rasta
without dreads. It’s probably better not to argue though, when someone is so
happy to meet a Rastaman, and blesses you in the name of Jah.</p>

<p>I think Belize must have some of the friendliest beggars in the world. “When I
see you I don’t see a white man. I see a brother from another mother.” Yes, he
then asked me for money, but I don’t think it totally invalidates what he was
saying. As the only white man in some of the places I visited, the locks made
me feel a bit more comfortable, and perhaps the locals where a bit friendlier
because of it. I don’t know for sure, of course.</p>

<p>I never really decided to get dreads, but I was thinking about it and
mentioned it to people. One night in the marina in Las Palmas, the night
before Mariella was going to sea, heading for another continent, she took a
wooden bead from her hair and gave it to me, “for when you get dreads”. I
asked her to braid it in for the moment, but she actually made my first dread
while we sat on a boat under the stars. The rest followed. Many of them were
made by friends, and they are named after them.</p>

<p>There are other ways they record memories. I have other beads in my hair, and
know where they came from. Some are ferrite cores from a recycled computer in
La Tomatera, a wonderful squat I lived in for a while. I remember hacking the
machine apart, and wrapping enameled magnet wire around someone else’s hair.</p>

<p>A guy who made one of my dreads swaps his with people. They cut one off, swap
and reattach with a crochet hook. When we met, he had thirteen different
people’s hair on his head. The variety of colours looked beautiful, and each
was a memory and a connection to a friend.</p>

<p>Dreads are like living things. They grow and change. They develop kinks and
twists, or straighten and flatten. They can join together or be split
apart. They also look like leaves, or grass, or tree branches or coral. They
exhibit gnarl.</p>

<p>There is a saying, that dreads grow in, not just out of your head. They grow
into your brain. People see you differently, and this no doubt changes your
behaviour. I started eating a vegan diet a few months after getting dreads. I’m
not saying dreads caused a diet change, but maybe they are somewhat related.</p>

<p>I think dreads are strongly associated with spiritual, or conscious people. By
conscious, I mean people who do things having given thought to their effects,
rather than by default. Food is a good example - I find it slightly strange
when I see someone with dreads eating meat. This also means doing things
because you think they are right, not because society told you to. Many parts
of society would avoid someone with dreads, for example I guess it would be
harder to get some jobs. This also shows commitment to doing what is right -
not sacrificing principles for money. Someone told me that in India, if you
dreads are long enough to wrap round your head three times, you can travel on
the trains for free. They respect a commitment to a spiritual life.</p>

<p>I think the main reason I like dreadlocks though is because they are
beautiful. It is hard not to just stare and wonder at all the shapes, and maybe
colours, that they form.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/6506498593/" title="The Fairy by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7147/6506498593_a347a0411c_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="The Fairy" /></a></p>

<p>A few days ago I was sitting on the street one night in a village by the
Pacific Ocean in Costa Rica. Someone was talking about getting dreads again. I
made one impulsively, under the stars.</p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Honduras]]></title>
    <link href="https://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/06/19/Honduras.html"/>
    <updated>2013-06-19T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/06/19/Honduras</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Honduras is a funny country. I couldn’t find its identity. Most countries have
some stereotypical things about them that you can think of, like clothes, or
food, or music, or some quality of the people. I had no idea about Honduras
before I got there, and I still didn’t when I left. It seems to be some sort
of generic Central America, with a great <a href="/blog/2013/05/24/USA-Calling.html">influence from the USA</a>, and not
much of its own. It was however the home to some of the most exciting and
dangerous riding I did.</p>

<p>San Pedro Sula has at least some years been rated the most violent city in the
world. It is controlled by drug cartels. Someone I met later who had to go to
hospital there told of how he was asked to sit on a trolley which was covered
in blood. Apparently the staff thought this was pretty much normal, because it
was full of people who had been shot. The Daily Mail says there are 3.3
murders per day, and will show you pictures of this if you care to
search. Riding through the city is not really something to be recommended, but
there isn’t much choice but to cross it somehow.</p>

<p>I wanted to make sure I got there before dark, so I left early and didn’t muck
about. Approaching the city I started to see the cars with blacked out windows
and no number plates. Some are often fitted with bulletproof glass, which I saw
advertised. The driving standard was not good. I got the impression from the
way I was passed that everyone just drove as if I was not even there. Several
times I would have been hit if I had not ducked out the way at the last
minute. I heard that to take out a hit on someone here costs about $25, so the
value of my life was less than what it might cost someone to fix some
scratched paint on their car.</p>

<p>On the outskirts of town I stopped in an Honduran fast food type place for a
second breakfast / mid-morning meal and was amused to see a gringo who looked
pretty much exactly like a CIA agent from a Bond film. I doubt a group of
three middle aged men, each arriving here in their own vehicle to meet in an
unnoticeable place on the edge of town were on holiday, anyway.</p>

<p>In town, a car full of girls were shouting and taking photos of me. Apparently
the girls like gringos here, or possibly people crazy enough to cycle.</p>

<p>I found my prebooked hostel fairly easily. It was surrounded by a high wall
topped with spikes, razor wire and an electric fence. They told me this is an
affluent residential area. Leaving the hostel meant taking a taxi to the mall,
which was a relatively safe place where only rich people could go. There were
armed guards of course. The banks had lockers outside for you to put your
pistol in before you entered, and a few larger ones if you had a shotgun.</p>

<p>I read a spoof story about the opening of the city mall, in which the people
stormed it and cut up the benches for fire wood. I can almost imagine that
happening - just up the road I had seen people carrying bundles of wood on the
back of their bikes.</p>

<p>One day I decided I wanted to see this city, not just the American fast food
chains that lined the circunvalacion I rode down. I cycled into centre of
town. On the way I saw a naked man kneeling with his hands in the gutter. At
first thought it was some sort of extreme begging, but he was facing the
traffic, and was ignored. Maybe a yogi? But why practice yoga in the gutter?</p>

<p>I had some idea about wanting to sit in a cafe in the main square but there
was only a McDonald’s there too. Money changers and aggressive “Professional
Photographers” stalked in the zocalo.</p>

<p>The next city was Tegucigalpa, the capital. Here it was ok to walk outside, in
some areas, but not at night, so more taxis to Pizza Hut, which has a salad
bar which will feed a touring cyclist for $5. The approach to the city though,
was the most exciting and dangerous cycling I have ever done.</p>

<p>From San Pedro Sula, I had to cross mountain passes, maybe 1500m of climbing at
a glace at the profile. This gave a long fast descent, which continued down
from the mountains into the city. Here there was extreme high speed traffic
dodging including overtaking at least two motorbikes, and avoiding the wheel
sized manholes which had their covers stolen for scrap metal. When it levelled
out, I was then navigating back streets in one of the most dangerous cities in
the world, all under time pressure to make sure I had somewhere secure to
sleep before it got dark.</p>

<p>In La Ceiba, I came the closest to being robbed (that I know of). Someone
tried to get my camera out of its bag while I carried it, but he was very ham
fisted and I felt the tugging. Here was also where I found myself surrounded
by three armed guards.</p>

<p>I went to a mall to buy some new sandals because my last ones had fallen
apart. I was sitting on a bench researching it on my phone, when one of them
objected that I wasn’t allowed to be there without shoes on. At first I
decided I didn’t understand him. Then he went and got two of his mates. So now
there I was, barefoot sitting on a bench, and surrounded by three armed men. I
considered seeing what would happen if I just sat there - a protest against
the ridiculousness of it - but as I happened to be there to buy sandals anyway
I decided to go and do that now. So I remembered how to speak Spanish, and
they agreed to let me buy some, but not on my own. I was escorted by one of
the guards to the shoe shop, and he waited outside until I came out with them
on. Of course noone would actually tell me why.</p>

<p>On <a href="/blog/2013/06/07/Utila.html">Utila</a>, one of the Bay Islands of
Honduras, I learned to scuba dive. I wouldn’t really consider this Honduras
though. It was British until quite recently, and is only really officially
Honduran. A Honduran I spoke to in La Ceiba said if he wanted to get the ferry
there, he would be questioned first, under the assumption that his purpose was
to rob the gringos.</p>

<p>This was the same guy who tried to befriend me and walked around town with me
for about an hour before asking for money. He kept asking what I wanted -
weed, drugs, women, … He seemed frustrated that I didn’t really want
anything - I suppose this is what the consumer society is all about too - make
people want things so you can control them - or in his case make some
profit. At least he did help me by telling me not to go for a walk down the
beach, which was going into a particularly bad area controlled by the crack
dealers and pimps.</p>

<p>I did a a river rafting trip one day, which turned out to be rather more
serious that I expected of a typical organised tourist activity. Maybe because
I was on my own the guide didn’t hold back. It involved a a non-trivial partly
overhanging rock climb out of the river, to a ledge he told me was 11 meters
above the water, and then jumping into the rapids. My heart really was
pounding before I did this, but really I had no choice - I certainly couldn’t
climb down - I only just made it up, and there was no other way down. This was
not an old lady tour as it appeared in the brochure.</p>

<p>Honduras was also a country of buckets of water. Buckets for showering by
pouring it over your head, and buckets for flushing the toilet. The showering
is actually really good - better than a conventional one because you get so
much more water in one go, but I didn’t much like the toilet flushing this
way. Before I had worked out this was what was done, I did a jobby in a
restaurant and couldn’t flush it. They had given me some food for free “a
present”, so I thought I would be leaving them a present in return, but later
realised there was a barrel of water outside.</p>

<p>Honduras is the country where I first encountered bedbugs, lack of basic
plumbing, US fast food beside starving beggars, and some fear at what I think was
an actually real threat of violence, but it also has islands also look like this,</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8908097643/" title="Water Cay from Boat by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3747/8908097643_279a18f871_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="Water Cay from Boat" /></a></p>

<p>and rivers like this for swimming,</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/9001628671/" title="DSCF4872 by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5446/9001628671_4b2c3d737a_z.jpg" width="480" height="640" alt="DSCF4872" /></a></p>

<p>in which the locals also bathe and wash their clothes, presumably because they
have no other choice.</p>
]]></content>
   <georss:point>14.779530 -87.182007</georss:point>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[An emotional day]]></title>
    <link href="https://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/05/15/An-Emotional-Day.html"/>
    <updated>2013-05-15T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/05/15/An-Emotional-Day</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I thought this day might be interesting as an example of some thoughts and
feelings experienced during a day of cycle touring.</p>

<p>This morning I left a hostel where I had been staying for several days. I
didn’t miss it, but when leaving somewhere I usually do think about what I
might not have done there that I might have liked to do. Also, I am usually
slightly anxious about leaving something. I check several times that I haven’t
left anything.</p>

<p>I went to the post office to send a letter and post card. The pretty stamps
made me happy, as did completing a task. Then I had breakfast at “Amor y
Cafe”. They lived up to their name with some heart shaped ice cubes made of
coffee. I liked that, but was not totally relaxed because I didn’t want to
miss the boat back to the mainland.</p>

<p>The sea is beautiful around there - mostly green, not blue - and I enjoyed the
ride back. I had a lunch sandwich and spoke a little to the guy at my table in
the ferry terminal. I had decided earlier that I would try and hitchhike to
Belmopan. I had already cycled this road, and where I was could be considered
a side trip, so this would not compromise a claim of having cycled all the way
south, and I didn’t want to cycle this road again. It was not too bad, but I
had seen it before and it was not very interesting. I thought hitching a lift
would be easy because people in Belize are generally friendly, and I think
interested in the cyclist they see. More than one person I have met has said
they saw me cycling at some point. It is a small country with few roads.</p>

<p>Anyway, my expectation of it being easy was exceeded - the man asked me if I
wanted to stay at his place in Belmopan before I asked anything. I mentioned
hitchhiking and he offered a lift, which I accepted. So I didn’t even mount the
bike before I got a lift, and it was to nearly exactly where I wanted to go.</p>

<p>When we got going I was really happy. I enjoyed moving so fast,
effortlessly. I felt the universe was looking after me today, in providing
exactly what I asked for. I laughed to myself at the drivers singing to the
radio.</p>

<p>I had offered him some money when he filled up petrol in Belize City. Around
here, at least in most other Central American countries, I believe pure
hitchhiking is not common. People generally expect to be paid what it would
cost in a bus. Busses here are really cheap, so I was thinking of offering a
couple of dollars. He said when we arrived I could give him something
depending on my means.</p>

<p>We arrived and he asked for money. I offered Quetzales, which I didn’t need,
and thought he would because he travelled to Guatemala often. He said he
didn’t want them, and wanted trustworthy currencies. He must have seen my
emergency 100 EUR not in my wallet, because he then asked for Euros. I offered
three dollars, and he said he wanted 20. 20 would pay for a bus journey to
Guatemala, about four times the distance we just did. This didn’t seem like
the deal I was expecting. In the end I gave him ten, which I think is about
double what the bus would have cost. He then walked away without saying
anything.</p>

<p>I cycled off, but had a bad feeling now. I couldn’t quite work out why to
start with. Initially I kept checking and rechecking I hadn’t lost anything -
things that might have fallen off in his car, or been taken my his friend when
we were at the shop near the house we stopped at. I finally convinced myself I
had everything, but still had a bad feeling. After further thinking, I worked
out that the source of this feeling was seeing that man again. I knew if I did
it would be a bad thing. Either me returning because I had lost something,
which I had now ruled out, or him coming down the road to rob me. I remembered
that the first thing he asked in the cafe was how much did my bike cost. That
is always an unpleasant question. Then he had seen I had a lot of money, and
was demanding it. He know where I was going. Maybe he would get back in the
car later, maybe at dusk with his mate, and come for my bike and money.</p>

<p>Then I started to have other thoughts, like what if I had been drugged. I
didn’t think he really had a good opportunity to do this - it is a pretty
unlikely thing. I was being a bit paranoid now, but that is the point of this
story, to show how some emotions can occur and probably be rather too
strong. I was thinking about this because I had heard stories about the use of
a drug on travellers that makes them like zombies. They will then do what they
are told by the attacker, such as taking all the money out their bank account
and giving it to them. Someone I met in Oaxaca said this happened to him, and
the internet claims it is true also. I was feeling a bit funny too. Maybe I
was drugged - by myself with an unaccustomed amount of caffeine this morning.</p>

<p>At one point I remembered an idea a fellow traveller was talking about -
teleportation. If you had a teleporter, would you use it when travelling? I
felt that if I had it, I would right now jump to Edinburgh and not come back
till the morning, or maybe 24hours later to preserve a sort of continuity of
my journey.</p>

<p>Later, once I had examined and realised the source of the emotion - seeing the
man again, I could work out a logical solution to the problem. I was concerned
about being attacked on the road at dusk, so I only needed to find a really
good hidden campsite well before it got dark. Around here, that should not be
too hard. I suddenly felt much better.</p>

<p>Now I started to realise where I was. I became present. I noticed the beauty
of the forest I was cycling through. It was quite unlike the Selva Lacandon -
it was more open and pretty. I noticed the different coloured flowers. Then I
noticed the air. I really started to feel the air - a thick, significant
substance through which I moved, and I thought about how it came from the
trees. I considered how the air and the trees and everything are linked.</p>

<p>Not too much later, I saw a potentially good camp site. I stopped by the road
for a while to consider my location and possible distance for tomorrow, and
decide whether to stop here. I did.</p>

<p>I went into an orange grove. It looks like a really good campsite, because the
trees provide excellent cover from the road. Also, between the trees is
relatively flat ground where I could push the bike easily, and even cycle on a
track initially, so I got off the road fast and was not seen.</p>

<p>I was still not relaxed though, because I had various things to do before it
gets dark. Ideally I want to be in the hammock before dark, to avoid the
mosquitoes, and so that I can see to avoid snakes and spiders. There are some
very poisonous snakes all around Central America. So I cooked, brushed my
teeth, made tea and put up the hammock. Tonight I was pleased with myself
because I got everything squared away. The only things not packed in their
place on the bike now are my hammock, computer, which I’m using in the hammock
now, and clothes and shoes which I will put on in the morning.</p>

<p>I’m relatively relaxed in the hammock now, but somewhat alert to vehicle
noise. A vehicle playing music sounded like it stopped near here for a
while. I became concerned that it was a farmer going to come done the track I
did earlier, or maybe someone had seen the light of my computer screen (quite
unlikely} so I closed the computer and listened for a while. Then it moved on.</p>

<p>There we have a day of cycle touring. From a fairly neutral start, to something
approaching joy at a car ride, to fear and paranoia and wanting to magically
be somewhere else caused by a slight suspicion, to presence and joy in nature,
to relative, but wary calm in a campsite.</p>

<p>I think a lot of this would be easier if I had a friend with me. It would
allow a second opinion on the analysis of situations - did that guy seem
dodgy to you too? It would probably also reduce fear - having some backup in
case of a fight. I’m coming around to the idea of cycling with someone
else. Maybe if I decide to do so, the universe will provide.</p>
]]></content>
   <georss:point>17.163385 -88.756828</georss:point>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Some Recent Karma]]></title>
    <link href="https://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/03/29/Recent-Karma.html"/>
    <updated>2013-03-29T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>https://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/03/29/Recent-Karma</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I very rarely lose things, but recently I lost a cooking pot, by proxy. I lent
it to someone. The last thing I remember losing before that was a lighter. The
lighter I was given by someone at a house I stayed in, and it was lost when I
lent it to someone in another house.</p>

<p>The lost pot I bought, but then I remembered when I was on La Palma, I had
acquired a pot after a party, because I needed one to go walking in the
mountains. People told me it would be ok to take one if I asked around and
checked it did not belong to anyone in particular. I think it came from the
communal equipment collection at the nearby cave community, where many of the
people were Rainbow. I think my pot was taken by someone when it was left
lying around at the Oaxaca Rainbow gathering.</p>

<p>I started to wonder if I was going to lose the spoon I got on La Palma too,
but then I remembered I had given a KFS to someone at the Palenque Rainbow, so
it is probably safe. :)</p>

<p>Property seems to flow more when travelling. Property and people.</p>

<p>When I set off on this cycling journey I left a girl in Edinburgh. This
morning a girl left me to travel south.</p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Babylon by Bus]]></title>
    <link href="https://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/03/18/Babylon-by-Bus.html"/>
    <updated>2013-03-18T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>https://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/03/18/Babylon-by-Bus</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When it came time to leave the Oaxaca Rainbow Gathering, we were offered a
lift up the road. This turned out to be in an orange VW Bus called Gail, with
a figurehead of a ginger woman painted on the spare wheel.</p>

<p>We were given a joining briefing. She runs on gas, oil and love. Normally she
has a driver, driver’s assistant, navigator, and band who sit in the back. She
was certainly well used, and I can see that she really must be held together
with love, as the string may not otherwise have been strong enough. I can see
how you can love a bus like this. My dreads kept getting caught in something
on the roof. Maybe she wanted a lock of my hair. :)</p>

<p>As we went up the sandy road through the coconut palms a man told a travel
horror story, over the considerable noise of the engine.</p>

<p>We made it to the main road, and after saying hello to some people on another
bus, returned to Babylon on a bus where we had to pay a fare.</p>

<p>We arrived at Salina Cruz, and I went a bit mad. At the Rainbow I was eating
healthily, vegan food, no sugar or caffeine. Now there were bright lights,
food and smells. I thought I smelt popcorn. It was esquites - corn. I bought a
cup. Then I wanted to try everything I saw - ice cream, burgers, tortas,
coffee. I ate churros next, which are similar to donuts but shaped like a star
prism. I also drank coffee and ate a cheese torta which was recommended by a
local. I felt very strange and didn’t stop talking until asleep on the bus
home to San Cristobal.</p>

<p>I would like to travel by hippie bus one day.</p>
]]></content>
   <georss:point>15.970548 -95.621588</georss:point>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Wind and Fire]]></title>
    <link href="https://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/03/17/Wind-and-Fire.html"/>
    <updated>2013-03-17T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>https://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/03/17/Wind-and-Fire</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I could feel something today. Some energy in the air, like something was going
to happen. Everyone could feel it. The wind was building and shaking the
trees. It had been building for days.</p>

<p>The wind drove us to eat in a huddle in the camp, sensibly breaking the
protocol of eating in the exposed, sandblasted, main circle. It felt like a
tribe coming together in the face of adversity. It was. The wind blew all
night and bounced my hammock.</p>

<p>The next morning, I broke up with my girlfriend. We were sitting in camp. As I
was talking, something hit me in the back. A girl sat up in my hammock. My now
ex-gf left to make her own camp, and I talked to my friend.</p>

<p>She was sleeping there, she told me, on account of being very tired from the
previous night’s activity. She had sex with a guy she liked, and the girl he
was with. She felt very free now. Free from jealousy, ego and social
limits. It sounds like it was a very liberating experience, and a cleansing
from the past. Past problems blown away with the wind.</p>

<p>Later, I was dwelling on the past. As I was thinking about what went wrong
with the gf, ruminating, a pan whacked me on the head. Stop it! Be present
now! The wind had blown it from the tree.</p>

<p>That night, there was an orange glow in the distance. With the wind coming
from there, it was not long before it brought the fire to the camp. Everyone
was driven out. Anything left behind was burnt. Many people lost things,
attachments maybe, and many moved on that morning.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8543751136/" title="DSCF3623 by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8522/8543751136_b140416fd0_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="DSCF3623" /></a></p>
]]></content>
   <georss:point>15.927404 -95.632076</georss:point>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Oaxaca Healing Rainbow]]></title>
    <link href="https://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/03/16/Oaxaca-Healing-Rainbow-Gathering.html"/>
    <updated>2013-03-16T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>https://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/03/16/Oaxaca-Healing-Rainbow-Gathering</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8542647331/" title="Rainbow Welcome by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8087/8542647331_1bf5f02ec0_z.jpg" width="640" height="481" alt="Rainbow Welcome" /></a></p>

<p>Somewhere over the rainbow, I found a coconut palm beach. Tropical, on the
pacific coast, warm sea and freshwater lagoon, plentiful coconuts and mangoes,
and rainbows living there.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8546100414/" title="DSCF3667 by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8105/8546100414_b26a1edde2_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="DSCF3667" /></a></p>

<p>This was a Healing Rainbow Gathering. This meant that there was no smoking,
alcohol, sugar or caffeine. The food was not all raw, but that was an option,
and it was of course all vegan. The gathering felt happier, calmer and more
relaxed than Palenque. There were far fewer people, and they were not coming
and going all the time.</p>

<p>I stayed there for a week. Meditating, reading, drinking tea, eating coconut,
swimming, and I learnt something about energy healing.</p>

<p>Whenever I used to hear people talk of healing, I did not know what they
meant. People do all sorts of things for healing: energy healing, music
therapy, laughter therapy and diets such as raw food, for example. I didn’t
understand this because I thought healing is something you do or need if you
are injured or ill. I did not think I needed to be healed.</p>

<p>However, I came to realise that there are things that can be improved, and
what is taken to be normal is a far worse state than it should be. Many people
are not happy. They argue and fight and do not feel good about life. There is
something wrong which can be fixed. I think it is this sort of thing that
people mean when they talk of healing. I asked someone what it meant, and he
said something about increasing your vibrational frequency. I’m not sure what
that means though.</p>

<p>Someone ran an energy healing workshop. I didn’t know what this was, but I
thought I might as well go and try it. The technique was to try and reach a
state of mind without ego, and then allow energy, or qi, or the great spirit,
or whatever you want to call it, to guide your hands over the patient. I think
the idea was to guide energy to flow in some way such as to heal. He explained
that you were not really doing anything, and were more like a conduit.</p>

<p>I tried it. I could feel, or imagined I could feel - it is hard to tell -
something when I held my hands over someone. I didn’t think too much about
what I was doing. Asking her, it seems that there was no effect on my patient,
but the experience certainly left me feeling different. I attained a very
relaxed, meditative state of presence which lasted for some time afterwards. I
didn’t feel much when I was worked on.</p>

<p>A couple of people I have spoken to about things like this have spoken of
intention. The idea is that what you do does not really matter, what matters
is your intention, and what you give your attention to. He spoke of putting
his hand on an injury, and focusing on it with an intention to heal. I would
guess that things like this have a strong placebo effect in credulous patients
and could indeed make people feel better. Ultimately the purpose of medicine is
to make people feel better, so you could say that this is useful, even if it
does not physically do anything.</p>

<p>Another interesting thing about this gathering was that I did not get ill. I
was eating some raw food prepared by innumerable dirty hippies who were not
washing their hands with soap, and probably some where not washing hands at
all. I felt healthy the whole time. Since I have been back in civilisation I
have had soft stools and been farting a lot, and generally not feeling as
good. I have not been sleeping as well either. Artificial food and light
really do seem to be bad for me. Maybe it is the tap water here which I
consume in small quantities from things like washed vegetables and tooth
brushing. At the rainbow though I drank well water and accidentally swallowed
some from the laguna than many birds swam in, and I did not get ill.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8544851505/" title="DSCF3658 by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8235/8544851505_f9b04fae13_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="DSCF3658" /></a></p>

<p>I was also introduced to coconut cheese. Some people discovered that some old
coconuts taste like gorgonzola. The texture is similar to cheese as well. This
was considered a delicacy, but I was a bit suspicious of it. It could be
marketed as a vegan cheese replacement, and I am surprised it has not been
already, as it is very good.</p>

<p>I slept in my hammock most of the time. I slept well. It turns out thought that
it was not very comfortable for two, because there was no space to move.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8544856681/" title="DD Frontline Hammock by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8086/8544856681_e83c8aa46c_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="DD Frontline Hammock" /></a></p>

<p>Overall, I enjoyed this gathering. I was much happier than at the Palenque
one, and I learnt some things. It was good to be by the sea after so long in
the mountains.</p>

<p>There was some excitement at the end of the gathering too. I’ll write about
that in a further blov post.</p>
]]></content>
   <georss:point>15.927404 -95.632067</georss:point>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[<span title="My hobby: asking for Buddhist temples in German. If they don't understand then I try Chinese">gibt es einen buddhistischen Tempel in der Nähe?</span>]]></title>
    <link href="https://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/03/07/Buddhist.html"/>
    <updated>2013-03-07T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>https://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/03/07/Buddhist</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8549721861/" title="San Cristobal NKT Buddhist Centre by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8391/8549721861_29da425226_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="San Cristobal NKT Buddhist Centre" /></a></p>

<p>I noticed this Buddhist centre when I first came to San Cristobal. I am now
living very close to it so there was no excuse not to have a look. They have a
“guided meditation” each day at 10am. On Thursday I went to it.</p>

<p>The main room or hall of the centre had a shrine at the end, with cushions on
the floor at the front and some seats in rows behind them. The shrine had
golden Buddhas and Bodhisattvas, 3 sets of 7 water bowls, a chocolate bar at
the right side, and various other things. On the wall behind the central
Buddha was a portrait of Kelsang Gyatso. Another, lager, portrait of him sat
in front of the Buddha. The way it was displayed reminded me of pictures of
Saddam Hussein in Iraq.</p>

<p>The session was not what I was expecting. The type of meditation I have
encountered before is about presence, silently concentrating on the senses and
body. This was mostly chanting with a few shorter periods of silence to
contemplate what was said.</p>

<p>It was surprisingly like a christian church service. There was the equivalent
of a hymn book for the chants or songs, and it followed a set program from the
book. The main difference was there were some periods of silence to
contemplate. I’m afraid it also felt rather like church - something you go to
because you are required to for some reason but you don’t actually feel
anything or get the point. The order of service if you can call it that was
from a book by the founder of this type of Buddhism. I read the book
afterwards in a couple of hours and then researched it more on the web.</p>

<p>I discovered that this place was of the New Kadampa Tradition (NKT), founded
by Geshe Kelsang Gyatso in England in 1991 and now based in the Lake
District. This form of Buddhism seems to be somewhat controversial, and has
some aspects I do not like and which are somewhat suggestive of a cult. It
seems people are taught only to read the books by Kelsang Gyatso, and I
noticed in the centre all the books were by him.</p>

<p>The only book that did not have his name on the cover was by the Western
Shugden Society, which seems to be mostly run by Kadampa Buddhists. The
worship of Shugden seems to be a controversial issue. The Dalai Lama banned
it, but Kelsang Gyatso supported it.</p>

<p>I also found a story about a monk being financially exploited, and there are
websites for “recoverers”. I don’t know if these indicate systematic problems,
but the fact that there is an official <a href="http://www.newkadampatruth.org">site</a> which tries to defend against
various accusations does not look good.</p>

<h2 id="the-teachings">The Teachings</h2>

<p>In any case, it does not matter what the organisation is like unless the
teachings are good. Kelsang Gyatso seems to be distinguished by designing a
clearly organised 21 step meditation plan, or lamrim in Tibetan, which I read
in one of his books.</p>

<p>Many of the steps seem like a good idea, but there were a few I really didn’t
like, which I will point out below. This post may seem rather negative because
of this, and admittedly I was looking for problems. I think this is important
though, because I do not want to spend a lot of time on something if there are
basic problems with it. I don’t know how much of this is specific to NKT and
how much is common to other Buddhist traditions.</p>

<h3 id="fear">Fear</h3>

<p>The first point is entitled “Our precious human life” but in reality it is
designed to instil fear!</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“This feeling of fear is the object of our meditation. We then hold this
without forgetting it; our mind should remain on this feeling of fear
single-pointedly for as long as possible.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The fear he is talking about is that of a lower rebirth. I should explain
samsara - the idea that we are trapped in a continuous cycle of death and
rebirth. This is common to many religions. Birth can be in any of six realms -
God, demi-god, human, animal, hungry ghost, and hell. Buddhas have escaped
from this cycle, and the idea is that by following the lamrim, you can achieve
this.</p>

<p>Christian Heaven and Hell seems like a special case of samsara where the
number of births is exactly two, or possibly three if purgatory counts as
one. Churches use fear of hell as a method of controlling people. It seems
here that fear of lower rebirth is being used to convince people to follow this
path.</p>

<p>I don’t like this idea of instilling fear because it is not something
inherently good and it can be abused to control people. Is it really necessary
to invent something for people to fear? Are there not enough problems readily
apparent that we can fix? I can certainly see things in my life which I could
improve with some Buddhist teachings without having to fear hell. Rather than
creating fear, then running to Buddha and your guru (“taking refuge”), don’t
unnecessarily create fear to start with. You can still learn, reduce existing
fear, and love.</p>

<p>All of this assumes that samsara exists. I tried searching for evidence of
this, or even where this idea came from, but I didn’t find anything convincing
enough to base my life on it. Perhaps this is the religious part of Buddhism -
something you are just required to believe without evidence.</p>

<p>I found this on <a href="http://typing-sound.livejournal.com/63084.html">someones livejournal</a></p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Getting back to the NKT, I would advise anyone reading this to stay well
  away from it. If you don’t and they get you inside, you will find yourself
  locked in beliefs and fear. You will be overloaded with practices and
  commitments prematurely, and then you will be afraid not to do them for fear
  of hell. Once you’re deeply submerged in the NKT, it is very difficult to
  get out again, because in a way you get brainwashed.”</p>
</blockquote>

<h3 id="death">Death</h3>

<p>Gyatso would also have you meditate on death.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“I shall definitely die. There is no way to prevent my body from finally
decaying.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This seems negative and may cause fear. Some people argue it is not even true
that you must die. Maybe it won’t if you don’t believe it, or if you become
more than a normal human. Again there is a more positive alternative. Instead
of saying I must work hard because I will die soon, think, I will work hard to
improve my life now. This works whether you believe in rebirth or not.</p>

<h3 id="gurus">Gurus</h3>

<p>He claims that it is necessary to have a spiritual teacher - it is the only
way. I won’t say that it is not helpful to have a teacher, but I object to the
idea that it is absolutely necessary. Where did these teachers get their
knowledge from? It must be discoverable. The Buddha did not have a Dharma
teacher. Yes, he probably had several teachers he learned from, but he moved
between them and thought for himself to develop his ideas. He did not swear
loyalty to one guru who told him never to read the books of someone else.</p>

<p>I read that some schools practice guru yoga or worship, basically treating a
guru as a god. This doesn’t seem like a good idea to me at all.</p>

<p>They also seem a bit obsessed about the lineage of teachers - students
becoming teachers and continuing the line. I think they see this line leading
back to Buddha as something to establish their legitimacy.</p>

<p>From the same livejournal post quoted above:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“I did learn a valuable lesson from it all, which was not to believe
  anything that didn’t depend upon experience, otherwise you get trapped in
  fear. And I learned to be self-reliant, not reliant on some Guru without
  thinking for myself.”</p>
</blockquote>

<h3 id="absolute-statements">Absolute statements</h3>

<p>The book is filled with definite statements which are clearly not true. For
example, that following this lamrim is the only way to give your life
meaning. It is obvious that I can do many valuable things without practising
Buddhism. The requirement for a guru is another example.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“We need to practise Buddha’s teachings because there is no other real method
to solve human problems.” - Geshe Kelsang Gyatso, “Modern Buddhism”.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Obviously this is not true either.</p>

<h3 id="positive-teachings">Positive Teachings</h3>

<p>On the positive side, the rest of the steps of this lamrim may be good ideas,
although I have not read about all of them in enough detail. They include
loving everyone equally, believing in the kindness and love of others,
avoiding attachment, compassion and cherishing others rather than
yourself.</p>

<h2 id="money">Money</h2>

<p>They seem to be partly a way to sell “Buddhist Holidays”. The retreats they
are selling in Mexico are about 100 GBP a day. For comparison I pay about 75
GBP a month in rent for rooms here.</p>

<p>The lama said we were invited to a lesson. I went. Afterwards I was asked for
money, “only if I had it”, but they asked several times. I didn’t want to pay
for something I thought was free.</p>

<h2 id="conclusions">Conclusions</h2>

<p>Unless there is good evidence for some pain after death it does not make sense
change your behaviour because of this. Focus on fixing real problems you have
now.</p>

<p>One needs to be very careful in choosing gurus.</p>

<p>Whatever the nature of the teachings or philosophy, there is a great risk of
corruption and exploitation when a large organisation is created around
it. Good people can be corrupted. The power a guru can have over his students
can also attract people who intend to abuse that power.</p>

<p>There are a great variety of practices and beliefs within Buddhism. You need
to research the specific teachings of different teachers rather than rely on a
simple label like Buddhist or Kadampa.</p>

<p>I should research other forms of Buddhism to see if there is one with less
religion, power and fear, and more useful lessons for living this life.</p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[San Cristobal de las Casas]]></title>
    <link href="https://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/01/11/San-Cristobal-de-las-Casas.html"/>
    <updated>2013-01-11T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>https://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/01/11/San-Cristobal-de-las-Casas</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/9/9a/Flag_of_the_EZLN.svg" width="640" alt="EZLN Flag" /></p>

<p>The streets smell of roasting coffee, grown by the coöps in the surrounding
hills. I also smell chocolate and bread from the panaderias. There are punks
on bikes - real bikes, not rusting Mexican style ones. Restaurants advertise
vegetarian and vegan food. Colourful gnomes and greyed hippies sit in the
streets.</p>

<p>There are anarchist and squatting symbols painted on the walls. If you wear an
anarchist patch in Edinburgh it is ignored. Here, the town was actually
captured by rebels. I don’t think it would be a good idea to cycle past the
army base they built down the road on my own with Zapatista colours. There are
armed police and soldiers around, which is a nice reminder of what is
possible. The government is wary.</p>

<p>There are at least two places here devoted to permaculture, with a vegan
community. Until recently there was a community bike workshop.</p>

<p>I wandered into the yard of some casa, following the sound of a woman singing
reggae. There was a guy contact juggling, and silks hanging from a frame. The
smoke was the pleasant smelling kind - not tobacco. A menu on the wall listed
hummus and verduras.</p>

<p>I wandered on aimlessly, and reached a cafe. Now I’m drinking tea that tastes
of the earth where it came from.</p>

<p>Mexico is sick and makes me feel sick. The world is sick. San Cristobal is a
hill station for the recovery of humanity.</p>
]]></content>
   <georss:point>16.7385777 -92.6332806</georss:point>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Gods]]></title>
    <link href="https://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/22/Gods.html"/>
    <updated>2012-12-22T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>https://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/22/Gods</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I don’t believe in any gods, and think religion is dangerous and very
harmful. The Rainbow Gathering had a good selection of them though. There were
temples for Hare Krishna, Shiva, and even a few Jesuses and Marys around. This
flippant attitude changed though, at the End of the World.</p>

<p>When everything is wet, it feels like it will never stop raining, you are
vomiting and the jungle is trying to eat you, Gods seem to come back. I like
sacred songs whatever I think of the content. In the dark I prayed to the rain
to stop, and apologised to Krishna for singing but not believing.</p>

<p>A Christian minister once told me, when questioned, that praying is something
people do because it is all they can do. Find a real way to control the
environment and prayer is useless.</p>

<p>Gods aren’t disappearing directly because of science taking over as a method
of understanding the world, they are disappearing because there is less
suffering. Modern life gives more comfort and less disease. With control of
your environment, waterproof roofs, heating, and factory farming, there is no
desperation, and no need for gods of rain and corn.</p>
]]></content>
   <georss:point>17.483017 -91.925139</georss:point>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Cycle Who]]></title>
    <link href="https://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/10/Cycle-Who.html"/>
    <updated>2012-12-10T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>https://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/10/Cycle-Who</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I am cycling from Mexico to Patagonia, the southern most part of South
America. I have fitted the bike with a solar panel, and am adding more
electronic gadgets as I travel. I started my trip on 10th of December 2012 and
have no plans about when it will finish. This is an introduction to what I am
doing and why.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8384962554/" title="Leaving Edinburgh by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8214/8384962554_1461cea29d_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="Leaving Edinburgh" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8272408443/" title="First test of solar charger by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8352/8272408443_0390543aa4_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="First test of solar charger" /></a></p>

<h2 id="exploring-lifestyles">Exploring Lifestyles</h2>

<p>There is a standard life pattern that where I’m people are expected to
follow. School, university, job. Buy house and car. Work most of
life. Retire. Die. Is this the best way to be happy? I’m pretty sure it’s not.</p>

<p>Some questions I would like to answer:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Do you need a house?</li>
  <li>Do you need to stay in one place?</li>
  <li>What are good forms of transport for a nomadic life?</li>
  <li>What makes me happy. What could make everyone happy?</li>
  <li>What is needed to allow more or even most people to be nomadic? What could be
done to make travellers lives easier? For example, I think more community
workshops, for bikes, electronics and other things, would help.</li>
  <li>How can people achieve freedom from:</li>
  <li>Work</li>
  <li>Location</li>
  <li>Oil</li>
  <li>Everything, as far as possible</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="promoting">Promoting</h2>

<ul>
  <li>Independent, sustainable travel.</li>
  <li>The bicycle as a practical means of transport - not just a toy.</li>
  <li>Alternative energy sources.</li>
  <li>Thought, and rational behaviour. I would like more people to think about how
they are living their lives - analyse them. Is what you are doing really what
is best for you, or are you doing what you have been told to do by society,
even though it’s making you miserable? How many people do you see smiling in
the morning on their way to work? It doesn’t need to be like that.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="where">Where</h2>

<p>After failing to get a lift across the Atlantic in a yacht last year, I still
wanted to go to Patagonia. In December I wanted to escape the Scottish winter
to somewhere warm. I knew there was going to be a Rainbow Gathering in
Palenque, Mexico, near a Mayan ruin site, around the time of the end of the
cycle of the Mayan Calendar. This, the climate and a very cheap flight to
Cancun came together to give me the start point of Palenque, at the End of the
World. Now I am heading down to another end.</p>

<p>I don’t suppose the exact location really matters though - it is probably most
important that it is just somewhere different from what I already know.</p>

<h2 id="why">Why</h2>

<p>I wanted to travel - actually I felt I had to. When I went travelling in the
Canary Islands I missed my bike too much - walking around can be very
tedious. So I decided to travel by bicycle.</p>

<p>I’m looking for happiness. I think that is ultimately what it is all
about. Therefore, I’m exploring different ways of living, and different
places, to see what could make me happy and the world a better place.</p>

<h2 id="what-can-you-contribute">What can you Contribute?</h2>

<p>I think I can inspire people and help them to be happier. I suspect most
people have ideas about how to have a better life but they just don’t do
it. Hopefully I can show that something apparently difficult, like cycling a
long way, is actually easily achievable, so more people will do what they know
they want to anyway.</p>

<p>Maybe I can learn things about happiness that I can pass on. Rather than
providing some fixed solution though, which is not likely to work for anyone
but me, getting people to think and improve their situation rather than
accept what is given would be an excellent result.</p>

<p>Happiness and love are contagious.</p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[.self]]></title>
    <link href="https://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/11/19/.self-Customising-Identity.html"/>
    <updated>2012-11-19T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>https://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/11/19/.self-Customising-Identity</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve been thinking about identity, that is the things which we consider
ourselves <em>to be</em>. For example, I could say: “I am a geek”, “I am an
engineer”, and many other things.</p>

<p>Is it a good idea to say things like this? Is it a good idea to have ideas
like this at all? Also, if I use these labels, what should their values be?</p>

<p>My main concern with using these labels is that rather than just describing
me, which could be useful, they could change my behaviour. I’ll take
“engineer” as an example here. I have sometimes found myself thinking things
like, “draw something? That is something artists do, I am an engineer, so I
can’t”. This is of course ridiculous. These sort of labels can be ingrained by
university, which is a good way to illustrate how ridiculous they are. Before
choosing a university course, many people are not sure what they want to
do. The course choice could be a toss up, but then a few years later they
think they can no longer do something they were capable of before university.</p>

<p>Gender is another obvious one. People seem to be very attached to their
gender, leading to things like not doing certain activities or convincing
yourself not to like some design or colour because it is meant to be for
another gender. I remember seeing a program on the BBC where they gave an
identical soft drink to boys and girls in two different bottles - one blue
called Rocket Pop and one pink called Princess Pop. Mostly, the boys preferred
the Rocket Pop and the girls the Princess Pop. What if I decide I can’t drink
Princess Pop because I am a man but actually I would otherwise think it tastes
better? I could end up being less happy for no good reason.</p>

<p>What if you give yourself some label of sexual preference and then you fancy
or fall in love with someone who doesn’t fit in with this label? This sort of
thing can cause a great deal of unnecessary suffering.</p>

<p>Another reason to be wary of “I am” statements is the effect on the ego. I
don’t know much about this really, but my understanding is that some people
and religions think that the ego is a sense of individual existence and being
separate from everything else. This is considered undesirable and some people
try to reduce it or achieve ego death or enlightenment. I suspect that
constantly attaching ideas and descriptions to “I” is only going to increase
ego. As well as avoiding these labels totally, maybe randomly changing the
settings could help to show that they are not immutable or necessarily part of
you.</p>

<p>If you don’t mind these labels though, how do you know you’ve got the right
ones? By the right ones, I mean the ones that make you happiest, or help you
achieve your goals. Have you even thought about them, or did you just take the
defaults?</p>

<p>Hackers spend a long time customising their environment with dotfiles. These
configuration files are carefully customised and curated to create a unique
environment that pleases the inhabitant of the computer system. If you do this
with software, why not yourself, which is far more important.</p>

<p>What are your default settings? Why not try changing them and see what they
do? I’ve decided to try doing this. Actually, I found I already had done some
before I started to think about it like this, but maybe I should try some
more.</p>

<p>Here are some suggestions for parameters to try adjusting in your .self</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Profession: e.g. engineer, artist. Even without changing jobs, this could be
experimented with by doing something from some other class, e.g. painting for
an engineer. Maybe there is also a different way to think about things -
it’s not just about what you do. Maybe I could try to judge things by their
aesthetic appeal, rather than their functionality. I’ve been trying to
answer questions like “what do you do” with a more direct description of
what I have been doing recently, rather than a possibly quite inaccurate
label I adopted some time ago.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Subcultural group memberships: e.g. geek, goth, hippie. (If you really want
to use these at all.)</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Social strata: Dress and mannerisms, and other factors may identify you as
“middle class”, “working class”, or something like that.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Religion: Most people get this randomly assigned based on the religion of
their parents. That’s clearly a setting worth investigating.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Gender: I am physically male. This is presumably what led my parents and
others to assign me the masculine gender before I knew what this was. Now I
am old enough to think about it maybe I should try some other settings.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Intelligence: Placebos have been shown to improve test results. If you label
yourself as stupid, or bad at maths, changing the label could help.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Nationality: Maybe try picking one at random, or probably better, try to
have none at all.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Diet: Depending on your randomly assigned country and religion, your default
diet may be omnivore, vegetarian, or have some other restrictions. Have you
thought about the ethical and health implications of each option? What about
just trying something different? I was omnivorous by default and then
switched to a vegan diet, for example.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>There are other things you can change too, like lifestyle and living
arrangements, which are not so clearly “I am” relationships, but still often
considered a part of who you are. The difference between “traveller” and
“homeless” is not in where you sleep, I think it is about how you see
yourself, and if you are happy.</p>

<p>In summary, I would like to encourage you to experiment with what really makes
you happy, and not just accept the defaults you are given.</p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Free Food]]></title>
    <link href="https://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/08/12/Free-Food.html"/>
    <updated>2012-08-12T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/08/12/Free-Food</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This post is about getting food for free, that is without spending money, but
actually I mean more than that by free food. Food is the key thing which keeps
many people in slavery. You need it to live (although some people dispute
that) and the current system is set up such that you need to pay for it. This
requires money, which in turn requires you to participate in the economic
system which binds people to jobs they don’t want and generally makes people
so many people miserable. When you know how to get food for free, you become
more free.</p>

<p>I don’t claim that the methods I outline in this post will fix the system or
work if everyone were to do this, but for now they can at least help some of
us.</p>

<h2 id="skipping">Skipping</h2>

<p>In Europe this is called recycling, in America, dumpster diving. The best
places to go are supermarkets at closing time. Huge amounts of good food are
thrown away every day. This might be because an apple is bruised or a banana is
deemed too brown. Much of it will be food that has reached its best before
date. Apart from the fact that these dates are usually very conservative and
therefore the food will probably be good for some time, if you go at closing
time you get food which was on the shelves only minutes earlier, so it may not
even go out of date until the next day. You can live on entirely on what you
find in these bins.</p>

<p>There are some things you will very rarely find, like dried foods and things
with a long shelf life. It’s nice to be able to buy these things, but it’s a
luxury.</p>

<h2 id="growing">Growing</h2>

<p>If you are settled, you can of course grow food. Not much good if you are
travelling though.</p>

<h2 id="foraging">Foraging</h2>

<p>Depending on where you are, you may be able to find fruit, mushrooms, and
other foods growing wild.</p>

<h2 id="asking-in-restaurants-and-shops">Asking in Restaurants and Shops</h2>

<p>This is similar to skipping, but you get it before it is thrown in the
bin. Going to bakeries at closing time is often very worthwhile. Some
restaurants will also cook lots of food that if unsold gets thrown away.</p>

<h2 id="charity">Charity</h2>

<p>There are charities which give food to “the homeless” (whatever that
means). Some temples and churches do this. It is not something I really like
because, unlike skipping, the food has been paid for by someone. I’m not
really comfortable with the idea of other people buying food for me. If you
need it though, you should know these places are there.</p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Living and Travelling without Money]]></title>
    <link href="https://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/08/11/Living-for-Free.html"/>
    <updated>2012-08-11T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/08/11/Living-for-Free</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Many people assume that travel is expensive, but it doesn’t need to be. I
wintered in the Canary Islands for three months and spent almost nothing. It’s
just a matter of learning how to live without using money. You won’t be
staying in five star hotels all the time, but it is quite possible to be happy
and there are actually many advantages of a money free lifestyle.</p>

<p>Without money, I think you are likely to meet more people, see more of the
places you travel to, and learn more. If you stay in an hotel and go on guided
tours you see the inside of an hotel and meet tourists. Then you come home a
week later because you can’t afford any more and you think you’ve got to do
some job you would rather not be doing right then. If you sleep on a beach, in
a cave, or even on the street you will certainly have a more interesting
experience. You’ll probably meet other travellers or locals who can help you
with things and show you interesting places.</p>

<p>Money forces things. This is maybe ok if you know exactly what you want all
the time, but you probably don’t. The most obvious example is where to go. I
left Edinburgh with the idea of going to Patagonia. If I had bought a flight,
I would have gone straight there. I attempted to hitchhike, and because I was
not successful I had other adventures and learnt and did things which I might
not have otherwise. I think what should have happened did. Things tend to work
out for the best.</p>

<p>I think I’ll write separately about the practicalities of living without
money. The main expenses which need to be removed are accommodation, <a href="/blog/2012/08/12/Free-Food.html">food</a>, and transport. For now I’ll
cover more general ideas.</p>

<h2 id="the-bare-necessities-of-life-will-come-to-you">“The bare necessities of life will come to you.”</h2>

<p>I’ve worked some of this out for myself on my recent travels, but I’m hardly
unique in doing so. First, I’ll tell you a story. I met a guy in Las Palmas
called Toto. He helped me at a lower point with his story.</p>

<p>A few years ago he left home with 20 euros and his bike. Since then he has
travelled round the world. He sailed from Australia to Europe, then to the
Caribbean and back to Europe, and probably other places he didn’t talk
about. He did some busking and when I met him had 100 euros. He didn’t have
any special performing skill, he just did some silly dance. It’s not really
important where he went, the story is that this is possible.</p>

<p>“Even if I only ate bread one day it doesn’t matter, maybe I’ll find something
else the next day.”</p>

<p>I met another guy who makes a bit of money from playing music on the
street. You might call him homeless if you saw him, but since I’ve been back
in Edinburgh working on my geek bike project, he’s been flying all over
Europe. He’s probably happier than most people who work in an office.</p>

<p>It is important to be positive. You’ll be interacting with people for things
like hitchhiking, and people like happy people. “You won’t get a boat with a
sad face.” It’s also important for your own motivation.</p>

<h2 id="the-kindness-of-strangers">The kindness of Strangers</h2>

<p>When I was in the marina one day I went and said hello to some people. After I
short conversation I had to go and buy some food. They said no, you don’t need
to, we have food. I was reluctant to take it from people who may need to more
than me but they insisted and later I found it is not really in short supply.</p>

<p>On La Palma I wanted some sort of shelter to take walking with me in the
wetter Northern part of the island. I mentioned this to someone I had just met
and so within a few minutes of meeting he had lent me his tent and a better
sleeping bag. I nearly skipped over the fact that this happened in a house I
was staying in - where I had been invited to stay by someone else I had just
met. There are many more examples but you’ll need to read them in my other
blov entries when I get round to writing more.</p>

<h2 id="what-you-do-need-money-for">What you do need money for</h2>

<p>Basically, it comes down to convenience and speeding things up. There are a
few things you probably need it for though.</p>

<p>If you want food, you don’t need money. If you want something particular to
eat, you’ll probably need to buy it. If you want something now, you need to
buy it. If you can wait until you find it in a skip, you don’t. If you have
time to hitchhike, you’ll get there in the end. If you want to go now, you
have to pay for a bus. Of course, if you don’t know where you are going,
hitchhiking is better anyway.</p>

<p>Things you pretty much do need money for are transport, some foods, and
medicines. Sometimes you might need to pay for transport: a ferry, for
example. It’s very rare to find certain things in a bin, e.g. alcohol, coffee,
cooking oil, dried foods, and things with a long sell by date, but you can
live without these.</p>

<p>This post is rather unfocused because I have a lot to say on this subject and
I’m just trying to get some ideas out for now. Hopefully it is enough to show
you that this is possible. If you go out into the world with nothing but a
good attitude and an open mind you’ll probably do very well.</p>

<p>I’ll end with a particularly impressive story from a friend, and a link to
another blog post about this sort of thing, “<a href="http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=18463814">The
Universe Is Conspiring to Help Us”.</a></p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“The magic is FULL ON when u arrive in a city and we have no where to sleep
and a beautiful girl called Ling comes up to u and says: I heard u play music
its is beautiful! Do u have anywhere to sleep? U can have my apartment for the
weekend when i go visit my boyfriend! So she gave us the key. AMAZING
LIFE!!!”</p>
</blockquote>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Love and Light as a Service]]></title>
    <link href="https://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/08/05/Love-and-Light-as-a-Service.html"/>
    <updated>2012-08-05T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/08/05/Love-and-Light-as-a-Service</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I was walking with a girl in Maspalomas and discussing the squatting and
recycling lifestyle when a tourist turned round and gave her €20. We don’t
know why.</p>

<p>I asked her how she felt about taking money for nothing. I don’t really like
the idea. She argued that she did not just take from the conventional society,
but provided some value, by spreading love and light.</p>

<p>Initially I thought this sounded like ridiculous hippie nonsense but later I
came to think that it is true. I think most people, ultimately, just want to be
happy. One thing that I find makes me happy is being around happy people.</p>

<p>I believe there is a French saying that “there is only one smile”. When
someone sees the smile, zie then smiles, and so the smile is passed on. Thus a
pool of unfettered happy people should help to support global happiness.</p>

<p>I think the world would be a much better place if there were more people who
dedicated themselves to happiness. What else is life for?</p>

<p>So what about a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cloud_computing">Cloud
based</a> Love &amp; Light <a href="https://www.google.co.uk/search?q=as+a+service">service</a>? I suppose
that’s going to be called heaven.io and have plenty of node.js and rounded
corners.</p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Vegan Crunk Night]]></title>
    <link href="https://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/05/02/Vegan-Crunk-Night.html"/>
    <updated>2012-05-02T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/05/02/Vegan-Crunk-Night</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/58967572@N03/7135620371/" title="Vegan Crunk Night by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7076/7135620371_13a888b2f4_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="Vegan Crunk Night" /></a></p>

<p><q>I organise a vegan crunk night.</q></p>

<p>Now that I am eating vegan, I feel like I can somewhat legitimately organise a
vegan crunk night. I still don’t know what one is meant to be, but that didn’t
stop me and on Saturday we had one. There were tasty vegan noms, potluck
style. Apparently crunk is a kind of southern hip-hop, but none of us were
keen on that so we decided table top games would be a reasonable
substitute. :)</p>

<p>If you don’t know what I’m talking about you need to watch this excellent
video.</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/lVmmYMwFj1I" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Vegan]]></title>
    <link href="https://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/05/02/Vegan.html"/>
    <updated>2012-05-02T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/05/02/Vegan</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Nearly three weeks ago I adopted a vegan diet. Since the 12th of April I
have not eaten anything containing animal products, except for a few vitamin
pills until I got hold of some vegan ones.</p>

<p>I’m not sure why I am doing this. I just had a feeling it was the thing to
do. Usually I don’t pay too much attention to feelings and would make
decisions based on conscious reasoning but as an experiment I am trying to pay
more attention to feelings. So this diet could be called a meta-experiment.</p>

<p>If I had to rationalise this notion, I would note that I had a vegetarian diet
for much, perhaps even most, of the time when I was <a href="/blog/2011/11/15/Serendipitous-Blaggagio.html">travelling
recently</a>. This was simply because of what was available and
practical. Meat and milk do not survive well if you live outside in a hot
climate. I felt good when I was away and perhaps associated eating less meat
with this, even if there is no causal relation.</p>

<p>When I returned to this meat eating household I was very aware of when I ate
meat. In some cases, such as ready meals, it seemed slightly unappealing.</p>

<p>I had also become more aware of food in general, particularly if it was
expensive or rare, like fish for example. I did not object completely to
eating it, but thought that if one is going to eat something of which there is
a limited supply, and which is not necessary, then it ought to be
appreciated. If the reason to eat a certain fish is flavour and pleasure,
making oneself happy, then one should pay attention to the eating and enjoy
it, not watch TV while doing so, otherwise it is mindless destruction.</p>

<p>Whatever the reason, I decided to eat vegan, with the idea I would probably
try it for a month and see how I felt. I started because of a feeling so
I will also use that criterion to decide when to stop, if at all.</p>

<p>I am not calling myself a vegan. Partly this is because I am trying to be
careful not to over-use labels, but mostly it is because this one does not seem
to apply. The Vegan Society says, <q cite="http://www.vegansociety.com/become-a-vegan/why.aspx">A vegan is someone
who tries to live without exploiting animals, for the benefit of animals,
people and the planet.</q>. The definition requires a certain intention, not
just action. I don’t think I am motivated by the given reasons. It is probably
the simplest way to describe my diet though. I am not a vegan, I just eat like
one.</p>

<p>I had some problems in the first few days. On days two and three I woke up
unusually hungry. Someone later told me when he was vegan for a month he was
hungry all the time and ate lots of sugar to relieve it, but I found this
resolved itself by the fourth day and it has not recurred. For the first week
perhaps, I was also producing Type 6 on the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bristol_Stool_Scale">Bristol Stool
Scale</a> and needed to go to the toilet more often. Perhaps I was eating much
more fibre than I was used to, but that is probably a good thing. It seems to
have settled down now. Otherwise, I have found it quite easy so far and learnt
some things about food, cooking and veganism.</p>

<p>I don’t seem to crave meat or cheese. If tasty animal food was put in front of
me, such as good quality meat or some cheese for Mellis’s cheesemonger, I would
like to eat it, but I rarely think about it otherwise. I miss eggs and butter
on toast.</p>

<p>One thing that requires some effort though is cooking. This is probably not
because vegan cooking is inherently more difficult than cooking with any
ingredients, but because the things I know how to cook are not
vegan. Therefore I need to learn a lot, fast, to avoid becoming bored with a
few dishes. It’s also hard to learn because the way I learnt to cook many
things I know is by discovering them somewhere, like a restaurant, and then
cooking it myself. That way I knew what I liked and what it was meant to be
like. I do not have the experience of vegan food to know what is good and what
things should come out like when I try recipes.</p>

<p>The positive side is that I am being forced to learn. I have discovered new
ingredients I would never have tried before and have probably diversified my
diet. I have become a fan of chickpeas and lentils, and would eat these more
even if I also ate meat. I’ve tried various grains, beans, soya flour, soya
milk, oat milk, agave syrup, and tempeh. I’ve also started cooking Indian
food, which I had been meaning to do for some time.</p>

<p>I also eat less processed food. Ready meals and other prepared foods often
have animal products in them, or in many cases, unspecified “flavourings”. Not
eating these is probably a significant health benefit. Another side effect of
the diet is reading ingredients carefully. I have learnt what some E numbers
are, and in some cases they are things I would not want to eat whether vegan
or not.</p>

<p>It’s also a good excuse to <a href="/blog/2012/05/02/Vegan-Crunk-Night.html">organise a Vegan Crunk Night</a>!</p>

<p>I’ve got lots more to say on this subject but will leave it at that for now.</p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Nyan cat, Psytrance, Meditation, Programming]]></title>
    <link href="https://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/04/21/Nyancat-Psytrance-Meditation-Programming.html"/>
    <updated>2012-04-21T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/04/21/Nyancat-Psytrance-Meditation-Programming</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>My highest score at <a href="http://nyan.cat">nyan.cat</a> was achieved when
programming. I was at work and struggling to get much done. Then I put on
nyan cat and within a few hours I had resolved several issues. I guessed it
might be helping because it occupied the part of my brain that usually would be
free to distract me by generating unrelated thoughts.</p>

<p>I also like to listen to <a href="http://www.last.fm/tag/psytrance">psytrance</a> music when
programming. I thought it was good because it is simple and repetitive, so
unlikely to be distracting. It’s also fast and good for keeping me awake for
long hacking sessions.</p>

<p>Meditation also can help to clear the mind of unwanted thoughts and aid
concentration. I think this state of focus is what some programmers call flow.</p>

<p>I suspect now that trance music and meditation probably produce similar mental
states, which aid concentration and getting things done. I therefore recommend
that offices should play repetitive music such as nyan cat to boost
productivity and increase moral. :) I also recommend hacking at psytrance
parties.</p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Bulgarian]]></title>
    <link href="https://mm0hai.net/blog/2011/12/01/The-Bulgarian.html"/>
    <updated>2011-12-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>https://mm0hai.net/blog/2011/12/01/The-Bulgarian</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We walked in the sand, on wasteland at the top of the city. Around and below
us, I saw towerblocks, houses, the sea. Grass and brick in the sand. Above,
the night sky. It was warm, dark and timeless.</p>

<p>I was with The Bulgarian; I saw him, at least. He wore black, a black cloth on
his head. Round his neck, a white towel with coloured spots. He carried a
large teddy bear he had found somewhere.</p>

<p>The Bulgarian vomited.</p>

<p>“I thought you were a ghost. I thought you were my guide to see the aliens.”</p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Welcome to Serendipitous Blaggagio]]></title>
    <link href="https://mm0hai.net/blog/2011/11/15/Serendipitous-Blaggagio.html"/>
    <updated>2011-11-15T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>https://mm0hai.net/blog/2011/11/15/Serendipitous-Blaggagio</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I had a fairly normal life in Edinburgh. I worked as a software engineer from
Monday to Friday and lived in a <a href="/blog/2011/07/26/Living.html">house</a>. I felt stuck.</p>

<p>I had read Into the Wild a while before - in which Christopher McCandless
decides after university to burn all his money and travel as a tramp around
America. He liked wilderness and ended up in Alaska, where he starved to
death. This was one thing which gave me inspiration to go travelling.</p>

<p>I also seem to like remote places. Scotland is actually quite good for this
given its size: I had walked in the Fisherfield Forest and Knoydart, and
visited Sandwood Bay on the North West coast. When I was there I wanted to
stay and try to live there for a while, by fishing and maybe in time farming,
but I had a job in Edinburgh pulling me back. On my to-visit list are
Antarctica, Siberia (with Samoyeds), Mongolia (by bike I think) and now
Alaska. The middle of the Atlantic is also a pretty remote place.</p>

<p><img src="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/b/b6/Sandwood_Bay_North_View.jpg" alt="Sandwood Bay" title="Sandwood Bay. Yes, Scotland." /></p>

<p>I had also done some sailing recently, around Scottish islands and Wales. I
thought then about going further and crossing the Atlantic.</p>

<p>Another source of inspiration for another life was Steve Roberts, the <a href="http://microship.com/bike/index.html">Technomad</a>. I am a geek of
computing and radio and found his website when looking for designs for <a href="/blog/2011/03/25/HF-Bicycle-Mobile-Experiment-Part-3.html">bicycle
mounted HF antenna systems</a>. He travelled round the USA for years on a bike
fitted with computer and radio systems. I have done some bike touring in
Europe and I thought about building a bike like this myself to go further.</p>

<p>Finally, while at work in Edinburgh I was reading In Patagonia, by Bruce
Chatwin. I realised it was wrong to stay in Edinburgh and Scotland for so long
and I should stop thinking and go out and see these places. The ideas of
sailing the Atlantic and travelling in Patagonia came together.</p>

<p>I resigned and started planning my trip. I heard that many boats cross from Las
Palmas de Gran Canaria so I flew there to look for a boat.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/58967572@N03/6431731859/" title="Cloud computing, or stupid things to carry to 6000ft by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7023/6431731859_5862ee9677_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="Cloud computing, or stupid things to carry to 6000ft" /></a></p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Living in a Secret Volcano Base]]></title>
    <link href="https://mm0hai.net/blog/2011/08/14/Living-in-a-Secret-Volcano-Base.html"/>
    <updated>2011-08-14T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://mm0hai.net/blog/2011/08/14/Living-in-a-Secret-Volcano-Base</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/canete/2641080054/" title="Llaima 2 by i.canete, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.static.flickr.com/3022/2641080054_8db36ea327_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="Llaima 2" /></a></p>

<p>No one ever really thinks about the practicalities of living in a
volcano. Every evil genius aspires to build the ultimate
volcano lair but despite the romantic attraction there are certain
problems when it comes to actually living and working in one.</p>

<p>It would not do to have people locate my secret lair so I can’t give too
many details, but nevertheless I hope to share some lessons sufficient to
discourage others from burning themselves on such an arrangement.</p>

<p>Obviously, it’s not a real volcano unless it is active. The heat is
certainly useful to provide energy to run mad science but it can make
the living conditions uncomfortable. You need to consider
cooling. This is an important point in favour of the island
volcano.</p>

<p>There are certain precautions you must take though or you may not like it
atoll. Desert islands require more to be imported by sea - too much traffic
increases the risk of unwanted attention.</p>

<p>There are issues common to all volcano types. Lava can overrun your base. The
ground can melt and quake underneath it. Noxious gases can be a problem, depending on
your state of evil mutation.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/photoknipser/2094172110/" title="Gletscher im Mutnovsky-Krater by photoknipser, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.static.flickr.com/2171/2094172110_48058f47a5_z.jpg?zz=1" width="640" height="423" alt="Gletscher im Mutnovsky-Krater" /></a></p>

<p>Given these difficulties, why would you still want your base in a volcano?
Some good reasons include:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Necessary to forge unobtainium.</li>
  <li>Required to destroy certain gold-based artifacts.</li>
  <li>Good supply of sulphur compounds and other evil chemicals.</li>
  <li>People tend to avoid getting too close. Those who do are probably scientists so no one will miss them.</li>
  <li>Extremely convenient for disposing of bodies.</li>
  <li>Explosions and smoke will be masked by natural seismic activity and should not draw too much attention.</li>
</ul>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/21331626@N07/3932218443/" title="Untitled by Adrien Cretin, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.static.flickr.com/3501/3932218443_a501ef5cbe_z.jpg" width="640" height="425" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>Let me know if you decide on the volcano option. Do you have any hints?</p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ways of Living]]></title>
    <link href="https://mm0hai.net/blog/2011/07/26/Living.html"/>
    <updated>2011-07-26T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://mm0hai.net/blog/2011/07/26/Living</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There are ways to live other than in a conventional house.</p>

<p><img src="https://farm7.static.flickr.com/6012/5975477373_d3de359f7b_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="Bilston Glen site" /></p>

<p>On Sunday, I went to visit a community in Bilston Glen. Here is a forest with
tree houses and ground houses. They are made almost entirely of scrap - parts
from skips, wood, rope, glass, planks, carpet, sofas, mattresses, oil drums,
gas cylinders.</p>

<p>There is a small hydroelectric plant in the river - it can charge mobile
phones, which have signal here, and suchlike.</p>

<p>Food is also available from skips. People can live happily from what others
throw away. Perhaps better in many cases, if someone could only afford lower
quality food. The several large fridges were full when I visited.</p>

<p>Are people happy here? I don’t know in general, but one girl I spoke to seemed
fairly indifferent - it just seemed to be normal. Later, a friend of mine
moved here and liked it.</p>

<p>There are a mixture of people who live here. Some have resided for years,
others stay for months or days. Some are young and some are old. All will tend
to smell of campfire.</p>

<p>I could live in a boat. Move when I want. Work anywhere. Or a tent, hammock,
bivvy bag. I thought a hammock in scaffolding could be a good place to sleep
if one had to in a town, to be near an office for example.</p>

<p>Is homelessness really bad? It is hard to separate it from poverty and
addiction because that seems to be the cause of so much of it but it is not
necessarily bad. What is homelessness anyway? Are you homeless if you live in
an hotel?  What if you are an explorer with tent? What is a home? Can a bike
be a home? Is it somewhere comfortable? Is it a place or a feeling? Is it
necessary?</p>

<p>I left the woods and soon after IKEA offered me “my dream home”. It came with
a contract binding me to money, a bank account, an address, a job, and a place
to keep the bloody thing - a sofa.</p>

<p><img src="https://farm7.static.flickr.com/6148/5976040942_e35f5e01f4_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="IKEA, near treehouses" /></p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
</feed>
