<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Alistair MacLeod, MM0HAI: Posts tagged life]]></title>

  <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/tag/life/index.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mm0hai.net/"/>
  <updated>2012-07-03T01:57:21+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/tag/life</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alistair N. MacLeod]]></name>
  </author>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Vegan Crunk Night]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/05/02/Vegan-Crunk-Night.html"/>
    <updated>2012-05-02T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/05/02/Vegan-Crunk-Night</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/58967572@N03/7135620371/" title="Vegan
Crunk Night by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img
src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7076/7135620371_13a888b2f4_z.jpg"
width="640" height="480" alt="Vegan Crunk Night"></a></p>

<p><q>I organise a vegan crunk night.</q></p>

<p>Now that I am eating vegan, I feel like I can somewhat legitimately organise a
vegan crunk night. I still don't know what one is meant to be, but that didn't
stop me and on Saturday we had one. There were tasty vegan noms, potluck
style. Apparently crunk is a kind of southern hip-hop, but none of us were
keen on that so we decided table top games would be a reasonable
substitute. :)</p>

<p>If you don't know what I'm talking about you need to watch this excellent
video.</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315"
src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/lVmmYMwFj1I" frameborder="0"
allowfullscreen></iframe>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Vegan]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/05/02/Vegan.html"/>
    <updated>2012-05-02T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/05/02/Vegan</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Nearly three weeks ago I adopted a vegan diet. Since the 12th of April I
have not eaten anything containing animal products, except for a few vitamin
pills until I got hold of some vegan ones.</p>

<p>I'm not sure why I am doing this. I just had a feeling it was the thing to
do. Usually I don't pay too much attention to feelings and would make
decisions based on conscious reasoning but as an experiment I am trying to pay
more attention to feelings. So this diet could be called a meta-experiment.</p>

<p>If I had to rationalise this notion, I would note that I had a vegetarian diet
for much, perhaps even most, of the time when I was <a
href="/blog/2011/11/15/Serendipitous-Blaggagio.html">travelling
recently</a>. This was simply because of what was available and
practical. Meat and milk do not survive well if you live outside in a hot
climate. I felt good when I was away and perhaps associated eating less meat
with this, even if there is no causal relation.</p>

<p>When I returned to this meat eating household I was very aware of when I ate
meat. In some cases, such as ready meals, it seemed slightly unappealing.</p>

<p>I had also become more aware of food in general, particularly if it was
expensive or rare, like fish for example. I did not object completely to
eating it, but thought that if one is going to eat something of which there is
a limited supply, and which is not necessary, then it ought to be
appreciated. If the reason to eat a certain fish is flavour and pleasure,
making oneself happy, then one should pay attention to the eating and enjoy
it, not watch TV while doing so, otherwise it is mindless destruction.</p>

<p>Whatever the reason, I decided to eat vegan, with the idea I would probably
try it for a month and see how I felt. I started because of a feeling so
I will also use that criterion to decide when to stop, if at all.</p>

<p>I am not calling myself a vegan. Partly this is because I am trying to be
careful not to over-use labels, but mostly it is because this one does not seem
to apply. The Vegan Society says, <q
cite="http://www.vegansociety.com/become-a-vegan/why.aspx">A vegan is someone
who tries to live without exploiting animals, for the benefit of animals,
people and the planet.</q>. The definition requires a certain intention, not
just action. I don't think I am motivated by the given reasons. It is probably
the simplest way to describe my diet though. I am not a vegan, I just eat like
one.</p>

<p>I had some problems in the first few days. On days two and three I woke up
unusually hungry. Someone later told me when he was vegan for a month he was
hungry all the time and ate lots of sugar to relieve it, but I found this
resolved itself by the fourth day and it has not recurred. For the first week
perhaps, I was also producing Type 6 on the <a
href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bristol_Stool_Scale">Bristol Stool
Scale</a> and needed to go to the toilet more often. Perhaps I was eating much
more fibre than I was used to, but that is probably a good thing. It seems to
have settled down now. Otherwise, I have found it quite easy so far and learnt
some things about food, cooking and veganism.</p>

<p>I don't seem to crave meat or cheese. If tasty animal food was put in front of
me, such as good quality meat or some cheese for Mellis's cheesemonger, I would
like to eat it, but I rarely think about it otherwise. I miss eggs and butter
on toast.</p>

<p>One thing that requires some effort though is cooking. This is probably not
because vegan cooking is inherently more difficult than cooking with any
ingredients, but because the things I know how to cook are not
vegan. Therefore I need to learn a lot, fast, to avoid becoming bored with a
few dishes. It's also hard to learn because the way I learnt to cook many
things I know is by discovering them somewhere, like a restaurant, and then
cooking it myself. That way I knew what I liked and what it was meant to be
like. I do not have the experience of vegan food to know what is good and what
things should come out like when I try recipes.</p>

<p>The positive side is that I am being forced to learn. I have discovered new
ingredients I would never have tried before and have probably diversified my
diet. I have become a fan of chickpeas and lentils, and would eat these more
even if I also ate meat. I've tried various grains, beans, soya flour, soya
milk, oat milk, agave syrup, and tempeh. I've also started cooking Indian
food, which I had been meaning to do for some time.</p>

<p>I also eat less processed food. Ready meals and other prepared foods often
have animal products in them, or in many cases, unspecified "flavourings". Not
eating these is probably a significant health benefit. Another side effect of
the diet is reading ingredients carefully. I have learnt what some E numbers
are, and in some cases they are things I would not want to eat whether vegan
or not.</p>

<p>It's also a good excuse to <a
href="/blog/2012/05/02/Vegan-Crunk-Night.html">organise a Vegan Crunk Night</a>!</p>

<p>I've got lots more to say on this subject but will leave it at that for now.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Nyan cat, Psytrance, Meditation, Programming]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/04/21/Nyancat-Psytrance-Meditation-Programming.html"/>
    <updated>2012-04-21T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/04/21/Nyancat-Psytrance-Meditation-Programming</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>My highest score at <a href="http://nyan.cat">nyan.cat</a> was achieved when
programming. I was at work and struggling to get much done. Then I put on
nyan cat and within a few hours I had resolved several issues. I guessed it
might be helping because it occupied the part of my brain that usually would be
free to distract me by generating unrelated thoughts.</p>

<p>I also like to listen to <a
href="http://www.last.fm/tag/psytrance">psytrance</a> music when
programming. I thought it was good because it is simple and repetitive, so
unlikely to be distracting. It's also fast and good for keeping me awake for
long hacking sessions.</p>

<p>Meditation also can help to clear the mind of unwanted thoughts and aid
concentration. I think this state of focus is what some programmers call flow.</p>

<p>I suspect now that trance music and meditation probably produce similar mental
states, which aid concentration and getting things done. I therefore recommend
that offices should play repetitive music such as nyan cat to boost
productivity and increase moral. :) I also recommend hacking at psytrance
parties.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Welcome to Serendipitous Blaggagio]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2011/11/15/Serendipitous-Blaggagio.html"/>
    <updated>2011-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2011/11/15/Serendipitous-Blaggagio</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I had a fairly normal life in Edinburgh. I worked as a software engineer from
Monday to Friday and lived in a <a
href="/blog/2011/07/26/Living.html">house</a>. I felt stuck.</p>

<p>I had read Into the Wild a while before - in which Christopher McCandless
decides after university to burn all his money and travel as a tramp around
America. He liked wilderness and ended up in Alaska, where he starved to
death. This was one thing which gave me inspiration to go travelling.</p>

<p>I also seem to like remote places. Scotland is actually quite good for this
given its size: I had walked in the Fisherfield Forest and Knoydart, and
visited Sandwood Bay on the North West coast. When I was there I wanted to
stay and try to live there for a while, by fishing and maybe in time farming,
but I had a job in Edinburgh pulling me back. On my to-visit list are
Antarctica, Siberia (with Samoyeds), Mongolia (by bike I think) and now
Alaska. The middle of the Atlantic is also a pretty remote place.</p>

<p><img
src="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/b/b6/Sandwood_Bay_North_View.jpg"
alt="Sandwood Bay" title="Sandwood Bay. Yes, Scotland." /></p>

<p>I had also done some sailing recently, around Scottish islands and Wales. I
thought then about going further and crossing the Atlantic.</p>

<p>Another source of inspiration for another life was Steve Roberts, the <a
href="http://microship.com/bike/index.html">Technomad</a>. I am a geek of
computing and radio and found his website when looking for designs for <a
href="/blog/2011/03/25/HF-Bicycle-Mobile-Experiment-Part-3.html">bicycle
mounted HF antenna systems</a>. He travelled round the USA for years on a bike
fitted with computer and radio systems. I have done some bike touring in
Europe and I thought about building a bike like this myself to go further.</p>

<p>Finally, while at work in Edinburgh I was reading In Patagonia, by Bruce
Chatwin. I realised it was wrong to stay in Edinburgh and Scotland for so long
and I should stop thinking and go out and see these places. The ideas of
sailing the Atlantic and travelling in Patagonia came together.</p>

<p>I resigned and started planning my trip. I heard that many boats cross from Las
Palmas de Gran Canaria so I flew there to look for a boat.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/58967572@N03/6431731859/" title="Cloud computing, or stupid things to carry to 6000ft by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7023/6431731859_5862ee9677_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="Cloud computing, or stupid things to carry to 6000ft"></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Living in a Secret Volcano Base]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2011/08/14/Living-in-a-Secret-Volcano-Base.html"/>
    <updated>2011-08-14T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2011/08/14/Living-in-a-Secret-Volcano-Base</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/canete/2641080054/" title="Llaima 2 by
i.canete, on Flickr"><img
src="http://farm4.static.flickr.com/3022/2641080054_8db36ea327_z.jpg"
width="640" height="480" alt="Llaima 2"></a></p>

<p>No one ever really thinks about the practicalities of living in a
volcano. Every evil genius aspires to build the ultimate
volcano lair but despite the romantic attraction there are certain
problems when it comes to actually living and working in one.</p>

<p>It would not do to have people locate my secret lair so I can't give too
many details, but nevertheless I hope to share some lessons sufficient to
discourage others from burning themselves on such an arrangement.</p>

<p>Obviously, it's not a real volcano unless it is active. The heat is
certainly useful to provide energy to run mad science but it can make
the living conditions uncomfortable. You need to consider
cooling. This is an important point in favour of the island
volcano.</p>

<p>There are certain precautions you must take though or you may not like it
atoll. Desert islands require more to be imported by sea - too much traffic
increases the risk of unwanted attention.</p>

<p>There are issues common to all volcano types. Lava can overrun your base. The
ground can melt and quake underneath it. Noxious gases can be a problem, depending on
your state of evil mutation.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/photoknipser/2094172110/"
title="Gletscher im Mutnovsky-Krater by photoknipser, on Flickr"><img
src="http://farm3.static.flickr.com/2171/2094172110_48058f47a5_z.jpg?zz=1"
width="640" height="423" alt="Gletscher im Mutnovsky-Krater"></a></p>

<p>Given these difficulties, why would you still want your base in a volcano?
Some good reasons include:</p>

<ul>
<li>Necessary to forge unobtainium.</li>
<li>Required to destroy certain gold-based artifacts.</li>
<li>Good supply of sulphur compounds and other evil chemicals.</li>
<li>People tend to avoid getting too close. Those who do are probably scientists so no one will miss them.</li>
<li>Extremely convenient for disposing of bodies.</li>
<li>Explosions and smoke will be masked by natural seismic activity and should not draw too much attention.</li>
</ul>


<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/21331626@N07/3932218443/"
title="Untitled by Adrien Cretin, on Flickr"><img
src="http://farm4.static.flickr.com/3501/3932218443_a501ef5cbe_z.jpg"
width="640" height="425" alt=""></a></p>

<p>Let me know if you decide on the volcano option. Do you have any hints?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ways of Living]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2011/07/26/Living.html"/>
    <updated>2011-07-26T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2011/07/26/Living</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There are ways to live other than in a conventional house.</p>

<p><img src="http://farm7.static.flickr.com/6012/5975477373_d3de359f7b_z.jpg"
width="640" height="480" alt="Bilston Glen site"></p>

<p>On Sunday, I went to visit a community in Bilston Glen. Here is a forest with
tree houses and ground houses. They are made almost entirely of scrap - parts
from skips, wood, rope, glass, planks, carpet, sofas, mattresses, oil drums,
gas cylinders.</p>

<p>There is a small hydroelectric plant in the river - it can charge mobile
phones, which have signal here, and suchlike.</p>

<p>Food is also available from skips. People can live happily from what others
throw away. Perhaps better in many cases, if someone could only afford lower
quality food. The several large fridges were full when I visited.</p>

<p>Are people happy here? I don't know in general, but one girl I spoke to seemed
fairly indifferent - it just seemed to be normal. Later, a friend of mine
moved here and liked it.</p>

<p>There are a mixture of people who live here. Some have resided for years,
others stay for months or days. Some are young and some are old. All will tend
to smell of campfire.</p>

<p>I could live in a boat. Move when I want. Work anywhere. Or a tent, hammock,
bivvy bag. I thought a hammock in scaffolding could be a good place to sleep
if one had to in a town, to be near an office for example.</p>

<p>Is homelessness really bad? It is hard to separate it from poverty and
addiction because that seems to be the cause of so much of it but it is not
necessarily bad. What is homelessness anyway? Are you homeless if you live in
an hotel?  What if you are an explorer with tent? What is a home? Can a bike
be a home? Is it somewhere comfortable? Is it a place or a feeling? Is it
necessary?</p>

<p>I left the woods and soon after IKEA offered me "my dream home". It came with
a contract binding me to money, a bank account, an address, a job, and a place
to keep the bloody thing - a sofa.</p>

<p><img src="http://farm7.static.flickr.com/6148/5976040942_e35f5e01f4_z.jpg"
width="640" height="480" alt="IKEA, near treehouses"></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
