<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss">

  <title><![CDATA[Alistair MacLeod, MM0HAI: Posts tagged life]]></title>

  <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/tag/life/index.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mm0hai.net/"/>
  <updated>2013-04-30T18:50:03-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/tag/life</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alistair N. MacLeod]]></name>
  </author>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Some Recent Karma]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/03/29/Recent-Karma.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/03/29/Recent-Karma.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2013-03-29T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/03/29/Recent-Karma</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I very rarely lose things, but recently I lost a cooking pot, by proxy. I lent
it to someone. The last thing I remember losing before that was a lighter. The
lighter I was given by someone at a house I stayed in, and it was lost when I
lent it to someone in another house.</p>

<p>The lost pot I bought, but then I remembered when I was on La Palma, I had
acquired a pot after a party, because I needed one to go walking in the
mountains. People told me it would be ok to take one if I asked around and
checked it did not belong to anyone in particular. I think it came from the
communal equipment collection at the nearby cave community, where many of the
people were Rainbow. I think my pot was taken by someone when it was left
lying around at the Oaxaca Rainbow gathering.</p>

<p>I started to wonder if I was going to lose the spoon I got on La Palma too,
but then I remembered I had given a KFS to someone at the Palenque Rainbow, so
it is probably safe. :)</p>

<p>Property seems to flow more when travelling. Property and people.</p>

<p>When I set off on this cycling journey I left a girl in Edinburgh. This
morning a girl left me to travel south.</p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Oaxaca Healing Rainbow]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/03/16/Oaxaca-Healing-Rainbow-Gathering.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/03/16/Oaxaca-Healing-Rainbow-Gathering.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2013-03-16T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/03/16/Oaxaca-Healing-Rainbow-Gathering</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8542647331/" title="Rainbow
Welcome by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img
src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8087/8542647331_1bf5f02ec0_z.jpg"
width="640" height="481" alt="Rainbow Welcome"></a></p>

<p>Somewhere over the rainbow, I found a coconut palm beach. Tropical, on the
pacific coast, warm sea and freshwater lagoon, plentiful coconuts and mangoes,
and rainbows living there.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8546100414/" title="DSCF3667 by
mm0hai, on Flickr"><img
src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8105/8546100414_b26a1edde2_z.jpg"
width="640" height="480" alt="DSCF3667"></a></p>

<p>This was a Healing Rainbow Gathering. This meant that there was no smoking,
alcohol, sugar or caffeine. The food was not all raw, but that was an option,
and it was of course all vegan. The gathering felt happier, calmer and more
relaxed than Palenque. There were far fewer people, and they were not coming
and going all the time.</p>

<p>I stayed there for a week. Meditating, reading, drinking tea, eating coconut,
swimming, and I learnt something about energy healing.</p>

<p>Whenever I used to hear people talk of healing, I did not know what they
meant. People do all sorts of things for healing: energy healing, music
therapy, laughter therapy and diets such as raw food, for example. I didn't
understand this because I thought healing is something you do or need if you
are injured or ill. I did not think I needed to be healed.</p>

<p>However, I came to realise that there are things that can be improved, and
what is taken to be normal is a far worse state than it should be. Many people
are not happy. They argue and fight and do not feel good about life. There is
something wrong which can be fixed. I think it is this sort of thing that
people mean when they talk of healing. I asked someone what it meant, and he
said something about increasing your vibrational frequency. I'm not sure what
that means though.</p>

<p>Someone ran an energy healing workshop. I didn't know what this was, but I
thought I might as well go and try it. The technique was to try and reach a
state of mind without ego, and then allow energy, or qi, or the great spirit,
or whatever you want to call it, to guide your hands over the patient. I think
the idea was to guide energy to flow in some way such as to heal. He explained
that you were not really doing anything, and were more like a conduit.</p>

<p>I tried it. I could feel, or imagined I could feel - it is hard to tell -
something when I held my hands over someone. I didn't think too much about
what I was doing. Asking her, it seems that there was no effect on my patient,
but the experience certainly left me feeling different. I attained a very
relaxed, meditative state of presence which lasted for some time afterwards. I
didn't feel much when I was worked on.</p>

<p>A couple of people I have spoken to about things like this have spoken of
intention. The idea is that what you do does not really matter, what matters
is your intention, and what you give your attention to. He spoke of putting
his hand on an injury, and focusing on it with an intention to heal. I would
guess that things like this have a strong placebo effect in credulous patients
and could indeed make people feel better. Ultimately the purpose of medicine is
to make people feel better, so you could say that this is useful, even if it
does not physically do anything.</p>

<p>Another interesting thing about this gathering was that I did not get ill. I
was eating some raw food prepared by innumerable dirty hippies who were not
washing their hands with soap, and probably some where not washing hands at
all. I felt healthy the whole time. Since I have been back in civilisation I
have had soft stools and been farting a lot, and generally not feeling as
good. I have not been sleeping as well either. Artificial food and light
really do seem to be bad for me. Maybe it is the tap water here which I
consume in small quantities from things like washed vegetables and tooth
brushing. At the rainbow though I drank well water and accidentally swallowed
some from the laguna than many birds swam in, and I did not get ill.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8544851505/" title="DSCF3658 by
mm0hai, on Flickr"><img
src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8235/8544851505_f9b04fae13_z.jpg"
width="640" height="480" alt="DSCF3658"></a></p>

<p>I was also introduced to coconut cheese. Some people discovered that some old
coconuts taste like gorgonzola. The texture is similar to cheese as well. This
was considered a delicacy, but I was a bit suspicious of it. It could be
marketed as a vegan cheese replacement, and I am surprised it has not been
already, as it is very good.</p>

<p>I slept in my hammock most of the time. I slept well. It turns out thought that
it was not very comfortable for two, because there was no space to move.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8544856681/" title="DD Frontline
Hammock by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img
src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8086/8544856681_e83c8aa46c_z.jpg"
width="640" height="480" alt="DD Frontline Hammock"></a></p>

<p>Overall, I enjoyed this gathering. I was much happier than at the Palenque
one, and I learnt some things. It was good to be by the sea after so long in
the mountains.</p>

<p>There was some excitement at the end of the gathering too. I'll write about
that in a further blov post.</p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[<span title="My hobby: asking for Buddhist temples in German. If they don't understand then I try Chinese">gibt es einen buddhistischen Tempel in der Nähe?</span>]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/03/07/Buddhist.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/03/07/Buddhist.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2013-03-07T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/03/07/Buddhist</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8549721861/" title="San Cristobal NKT Buddhist Centre by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8391/8549721861_29da425226_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="San Cristobal NKT Buddhist Centre"></a></p>

<p>I noticed this Buddhist centre when I first came to San Cristobal. I am now
living very close to it so there was no excuse not to have a look. They have a
"guided meditation" each day at 10am. On Thursday I went to it.</p>

<p>The main room or hall of the centre had a shrine at the end, with cushions on
the floor at the front and some seats in rows behind them. The shrine had
golden Buddhas and Bodhisattvas, 3 sets of 7 water bowls, a chocolate bar at
the right side, and various other things. On the wall behind the central
Buddha was a portrait of Kelsang Gyatso. Another, lager, portrait of him sat
in front of the Buddha. The way it was displayed reminded me of pictures of
Saddam Hussein in Iraq.</p>

<p>The session was not what I was expecting. The type of meditation I have
encountered before is about presence, silently concentrating on the senses and
body. This was mostly chanting with a few shorter periods of silence to
contemplate what was said.</p>

<p>It was surprisingly like a christian church service. There was the equivalent
of a hymn book for the chants or songs, and it followed a set program from the
book. The main difference was there were some periods of silence to
contemplate. I'm afraid it also felt rather like church - something you go to
because you are required to for some reason but you don't actually feel
anything or get the point. The order of service if you can call it that was
from a book by the founder of this type of Buddhism. I read the book
afterwards in a couple of hours and then researched it more on the web.</p>

<p>I discovered that this place was of the New Kadampa Tradition (NKT), founded
by Geshe Kelsang Gyatso in England in 1991 and now based in the Lake
District. This form of Buddhism seems to be somewhat controversial, and has
some aspects I do not like and which are somewhat suggestive of a cult. It
seems people are taught only to read the books by Kelsang Gyatso, and I
noticed in the centre all the books were by him.</p>

<p>The only book that did not have his name on the cover was by the Western
Shugden Society, which seems to be mostly run by Kadampa Buddhists. The
worship of Shugden seems to be a controversial issue. The Dalai Lama banned
it, but Kelsang Gyatso supported it.</p>

<p>I also found a story about a monk being financially exploited, and there are
websites for "recoverers". I don't know if these indicate systematic problems,
but the fact that there is an official <a
href="http://www.newkadampatruth.org">site</a> which tries to defend against
various accusations does not look good.</p>

<h2>The Teachings</h2>

<p>In any case, it does not matter what the organisation is like unless the
teachings are good. Kelsang Gyatso seems to be distinguished by designing a
clearly organised 21 step meditation plan, or lamrim in Tibetan, which I read
in one of his books.</p>

<p>Many of the steps seem like a good idea, but there were a few I really didn't
like, which I will point out below. This post may seem rather negative because
of this, and admittedly I was looking for problems. I think this is important
though, because I do not want to spend a lot of time on something if there are
basic problems with it. I don't know how much of this is specific to NKT and
how much is common to other Buddhist traditions.</p>

<h3>Fear</h3>

<p>The first point is entitled "Our precious human life" but in reality it is
designed to instil fear!</p>

<blockquote><p>"This feeling of fear is the object of our meditation. We then hold this
without forgetting it; our mind should remain on this feeling of fear
single-pointedly for as long as possible."</p></blockquote>

<p>The fear he is talking about is that of a lower rebirth. I should explain
samsara - the idea that we are trapped in a continuous cycle of death and
rebirth. This is common to many religions. Birth can be in any of six realms -
God, demi-god, human, animal, hungry ghost, and hell. Buddhas have escaped
from this cycle, and the idea is that by following the lamrim, you can achieve
this.</p>

<p>Christian Heaven and Hell seems like a special case of samsara where the
number of births is exactly two, or possibly three if purgatory counts as
one. Churches use fear of hell as a method of controlling people. It seems
here that fear of lower rebirth is being used to convince people to follow this
path.</p>

<p>I don't like this idea of instilling fear because it is not something
inherently good and it can be abused to control people. Is it really necessary
to invent something for people to fear? Are there not enough problems readily
apparent that we can fix? I can certainly see things in my life which I could
improve with some Buddhist teachings without having to fear hell. Rather than
creating fear, then running to Buddha and your guru ("taking refuge"), don't
unnecessarily create fear to start with. You can still learn, reduce existing
fear, and love.</p>

<p>All of this assumes that samsara exists. I tried searching for evidence of
this, or even where this idea came from, but I didn't find anything convincing
enough to base my life on it. Perhaps this is the religious part of Buddhism -
something you are just required to believe without evidence.</p>

<p>I found this on <a href="http://typing-sound.livejournal.com/63084.html">someones livejournal</a></p>

<blockquote><p>"Getting back to the NKT, I would advise anyone reading this to stay well
  away from it. If you don't and they get you inside, you will find yourself
  locked in beliefs and fear. You will be overloaded with practices and
  commitments prematurely, and then you will be afraid not to do them for fear
  of hell. Once you're deeply submerged in the NKT, it is very difficult to
  get out again, because in a way you get brainwashed."</p></blockquote>

<h3>Death</h3>

<p>Gyatso would also have you meditate on death.</p>

<blockquote><p>"I shall definitely die. There is no way to prevent my body from finally
decaying."</p></blockquote>

<p>This seems negative and may cause fear. Some people argue it is not even true
that you must die. Maybe it won't if you don't believe it, or if you become
more than a normal human. Again there is a more positive alternative. Instead
of saying I must work hard because I will die soon, think, I will work hard to
improve my life now. This works whether you believe in rebirth or not.</p>

<h3>Gurus</h3>

<p>He claims that it is necessary to have a spiritual teacher - it is the only
way. I won't say that it is not helpful to have a teacher, but I object to the
idea that it is absolutely necessary. Where did these teachers get their
knowledge from? It must be discoverable. The Buddha did not have a Dharma
teacher. Yes, he probably had several teachers he learned from, but he moved
between them and thought for himself to develop his ideas. He did not swear
loyalty to one guru who told him never to read the books of someone else.</p>

<p>I read that some schools practice guru yoga or worship, basically treating a
guru as a god. This doesn't seem like a good idea to me at all.</p>

<p>They also seem a bit obsessed about the lineage of teachers - students
becoming teachers and continuing the line. I think they see this line leading
back to Buddha as something to establish their legitimacy.</p>

<p>From the same livejournal post quoted above:</p>

<blockquote><p>"I did learn a valuable lesson from it all, which was not to believe
  anything that didn't depend upon experience, otherwise you get trapped in
  fear. And I learned to be self-reliant, not reliant on some Guru without
  thinking for myself."</p></blockquote>

<h3>Absolute statements</h3>

<p>The book is filled with definite statements which are clearly not true. For
example, that following this lamrim is the only way to give your life
meaning. It is obvious that I can do many valuable things without practising
Buddhism. The requirement for a guru is another example.</p>

<blockquote><p>"We need to practise Buddha’s teachings because there is no other real method
to solve human problems." - Geshe Kelsang Gyatso, "Modern Buddhism".</p></blockquote>

<p>Obviously this is not true either.</p>

<h3>Positive Teachings</h3>

<p>On the positive side, the rest of the steps of this lamrim may be good ideas,
although I have not read about all of them in enough detail. They include
loving everyone equally, believing in the kindness and love of others,
avoiding attachment, compassion and cherishing others rather than
yourself.</p>

<h2>Money</h2>

<p>They seem to be partly a way to sell "Buddhist Holidays". The retreats they
are selling in Mexico are about 100 GBP a day. For comparison I pay about 75
GBP a month in rent for rooms here.</p>

<p>The lama said we were invited to a lesson. I went. Afterwards I was asked for
money, "only if I had it", but they asked several times. I didn't want to pay
for something I thought was free.</p>

<h2>Conclusions</h2>

<p>Unless there is good evidence for some pain after death it does not make sense
change your behaviour because of this. Focus on fixing real problems you have
now.</p>

<p>One needs to be very careful in choosing gurus.</p>

<p>Whatever the nature of the teachings or philosophy, there is a great risk of
corruption and exploitation when a large organisation is created around
it. Good people can be corrupted. The power a guru can have over his students
can also attract people who intend to abuse that power.</p>

<p>There are a great variety of practices and beliefs within Buddhism. You need
to research the specific teachings of different teachers rather than rely on a
simple label like Buddhist or Kadampa.</p>

<p>I should research other forms of Buddhism to see if there is one with less
religion, power and fear, and more useful lessons for living this life.</p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[San Cristobal de las Casas]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/01/11/San-Cristobal-de-las-Casas.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/01/11/San-Cristobal-de-las-Casas.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2013-01-11T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/01/11/San-Cristobal-de-las-Casas</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img
src="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/9/9a/Flag_of_the_EZLN.svg"
width="640" alt="EZLN Flag"/></p>

<p>The streets smell of roasting coffee, grown by the coöps in the surrounding
hills. I also smell chocolate and bread from the panaderias. There are punks
on bikes - real bikes, not rusting Mexican style ones. Restaurants advertise
vegetarian and vegan food. Colourful gnomes and greyed hippies sit in the
streets.</p>

<p>There are anarchist and squatting symbols painted on the walls. If you wear an
anarchist patch in Edinburgh it is ignored. Here, the town was actually
captured by rebels. I don't think it would be a good idea to cycle past the
army base they built down the road on my own with Zapatista colours. There are
armed police and soldiers around, which is a nice reminder of what is
possible. The government is wary.</p>

<p>There are at least two places here devoted to permaculture, with a vegan
community. Until recently there was a community bike workshop.</p>

<p>I wandered into the yard of some casa, following the sound of a woman singing
reggae. There was a guy contact juggling, and silks hanging from a frame. The
smoke was the pleasant smelling kind - not tobacco. A menu on the wall listed
hummus and verduras.</p>

<p>I wandered on aimlessly, and reached a cafe. Now I'm drinking tea that tastes
of the earth where it came from.</p>

<p>Mexico is sick and makes me feel sick. The world is sick. San Cristobal is a
hill station for the recovery of humanity.</p>
]]></content>
   <georss:point>16.7385777 -92.6332806</georss:point>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Gods]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/22/Gods.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/22/Gods.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2012-12-22T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/22/Gods</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I don't believe in any gods, and think religion is dangerous and very
harmful. The Rainbow Gathering had a good selection of them though. There were
temples for Hare Krishna, Shiva, and even a few Jesuses and Marys around. This
flippant attitude changed though, at the End of the World.</p>

<p>When everything is wet, it feels like it will never stop raining, you are
vomiting and the jungle is trying to eat you, Gods seem to come back. I like
sacred songs whatever I think of the content. In the dark I prayed to the rain
to stop, and apologised to Krishna for singing but not believing.</p>

<p>A Christian minister once told me, when questioned, that praying is something
people do because it is all they can do. Find a real way to control the
environment and prayer is useless.</p>

<p>Gods aren't disappearing directly because of science taking over as a method
of understanding the world, they are disappearing because there is less
suffering. Modern life gives more comfort and less disease. With control of
your environment, waterproof roofs, heating, and factory farming, there is no
desperation, and no need for gods of rain and corn.</p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Cycle Who]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/10/Cycle-Who.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/10/Cycle-Who.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2012-12-10T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/10/Cycle-Who</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I am cycling from Mexico to Patagonia, the southern most part of South
America. I have fitted the bike with a solar panel, and am adding more
electronic gadgets as I travel. I started my trip on 10th of December 2012 and
have no plans about when it will finish. This is an introduction to what I am
doing and why.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8384962554/" title="Leaving Edinburgh by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8214/8384962554_1461cea29d_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="Leaving Edinburgh"></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8272408443/" title="First test of solar charger by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8352/8272408443_0390543aa4_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="First test of solar charger"></a></p>

<h2>Exploring Lifestyles</h2>

<p>There is a standard life pattern that where I'm people are expected to
follow. School, university, job. Buy house and car. Work most of
life. Retire. Die. Is this the best way to be happy? I'm pretty sure it's not.</p>

<p>Some questions I would like to answer:</p>

<ul>
<li>Do you need a house?</li>
<li>Do you need to stay in one place?</li>
<li>What are good forms of transport for a nomadic life?</li>
<li>What makes me happy. What could make everyone happy?</li>
<li>What is needed to allow more or even most people to be nomadic? What could be
done to make travellers lives easier? For example, I think more community
workshops, for bikes, electronics and other things, would help.</li>
<li>How can people achieve freedom from:</li>
<li>Work</li>
<li>Location</li>
<li>Oil</li>
<li>Everything, as far as possible</li>
</ul>


<h2>Promoting</h2>

<ul>
<li>Independent, sustainable travel.</li>
<li>The bicycle as a practical means of transport - not just a toy.</li>
<li>Alternative energy sources.</li>
<li>Thought, and rational behaviour. I would like more people to think about how
they are living their lives - analyse them. Is what you are doing really what
is best for you, or are you doing what you have been told to do by society,
even though it's making you miserable? How many people do you see smiling in
the morning on their way to work? It doesn't need to be like that.</li>
</ul>


<h2>Where</h2>

<p>After failing to get a lift across the Atlantic in a yacht last year, I still
wanted to go to Patagonia. In December I wanted to escape the Scottish winter
to somewhere warm. I knew there was going to be a Rainbow Gathering in
Palenque, Mexico, near a Mayan ruin site, around the time of the end of the
cycle of the Mayan Calendar. This, the climate and a very cheap flight to
Cancun came together to give me the start point of Palenque, at the End of the
World. Now I am heading down to another end.</p>

<p>I don't suppose the exact location really matters though - it is probably most
important that it is just somewhere different from what I already know.</p>

<h2>Why</h2>

<p>I wanted to travel - actually I felt I had to. When I went travelling in the
Canary Islands I missed my bike too much - walking around can be very
tedious. So I decided to travel by bicycle.</p>

<p>I'm looking for happiness. I think that is ultimately what it is all
about. Therefore, I'm exploring different ways of living, and different
places, to see what could make me happy and the world a better place.</p>

<h2>What can you Contribute?</h2>

<p>I think I can inspire people and help them to be happier. I suspect most
people have ideas about how to have a better life but they just don't do
it. Hopefully I can show that something apparently difficult, like cycling a
long way, is actually easily achievable, so more people will do what they know
they want to anyway.</p>

<p>Maybe I can learn things about happiness that I can pass on. Rather than
providing some fixed solution though, which is not likely to work for anyone
but me, getting people to think and improve their situation rather than
accept what is given would be an excellent result.</p>

<p>Happiness and love are contagious.</p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Free Food]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/08/12/Free-Food.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/08/12/Free-Food.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2012-08-12T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/08/12/Free-Food</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This post is about getting food for free, that is without spending money, but
actually I mean more than that by free food. Food is the key thing which keeps
many people in slavery. You need it to live (although some people dispute
that) and the current system is set up such that you need to pay for it. This
requires money, which in turn requires you to participate in the economic
system which binds people to jobs they don't want and generally makes people
so many people miserable. When you know how to get food for free, you become
more free.</p>

<p>I don't claim that the methods I outline in this post will fix the system or
work if everyone were to do this, but for now they can at least help some of
us.</p>

<h2>Skipping</h2>

<p>In Europe this is called recycling, in America, dumpster diving. The best
places to go are supermarkets at closing time. Huge amounts of good food are
thrown away every day. This might be because an apple is bruised or a banana is
deemed too brown. Much of it will be food that has reached its best before
date. Apart from the fact that these dates are usually very conservative and
therefore the food will probably be good for some time, if you go at closing
time you get food which was on the shelves only minutes earlier, so it may not
even go out of date until the next day. You can live on entirely on what you
find in these bins.</p>

<p>There are some things you will very rarely find, like dried foods and things
with a long shelf life. It's nice to be able to buy these things, but it's a
luxury.</p>

<h2>Growing</h2>

<p>If you are settled, you can of course grow food. Not much good if you are
travelling though.</p>

<h2>Foraging</h2>

<p>Depending on where you are, you may be able to find fruit, mushrooms, and
other foods growing wild.</p>

<h2>Asking in Restaurants and Shops</h2>

<p>This is similar to skipping, but you get it before it is thrown in the
bin. Going to bakeries at closing time is often very worthwhile. Some
restaurants will also cook lots of food that if unsold gets thrown away.</p>

<h2>Charity</h2>

<p>There are charities which give food to "the homeless" (whatever that
means). Some temples and churches do this. It is not something I really like
because, unlike skipping, the food has been paid for by someone. I'm not
really comfortable with the idea of other people buying food for me. If you
need it though, you should know these places are there.</p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Living and Travelling without Money]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/08/11/Living-for-Free.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/08/11/Living-for-Free.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2012-08-11T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/08/11/Living-for-Free</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Many people assume that travel is expensive, but it doesn't need to be. I
wintered in the Canary Islands for three months and spent almost nothing. It's
just a matter of learning how to live without using money. You won't be
staying in five star hotels all the time, but it is quite possible to be happy
and there are actually many advantages of a money free lifestyle.</p>

<p>Without money, I think you are likely to meet more people, see more of the
places you travel to, and learn more. If you stay in an hotel and go on guided
tours you see the inside of an hotel and meet tourists. Then you come home a
week later because you can't afford any more and you think you've got to do
some job you would rather not be doing right then. If you sleep on a beach, in
a cave, or even on the street you will certainly have a more interesting
experience. You'll probably meet other travellers or locals who can help you
with things and show you interesting places.</p>

<p>Money forces things. This is maybe ok if you know exactly what you want all
the time, but you probably don't. The most obvious example is where to go. I
left Edinburgh with the idea of going to Patagonia. If I had bought a flight,
I would have gone straight there. I attempted to hitchhike, and because I was
not successful I had other adventures and learnt and did things which I might
not have otherwise. I think what should have happened did. Things tend to work
out for the best.</p>

<p>I think I'll write separately about the practicalities of living without
money. The main expenses which need to be removed are accommodation, <a
href="/blog/2012/08/12/Free-Food.html">food</a>, and transport. For now I'll
cover more general ideas.</p>

<h2>"The bare necessities of life will come to you."</h2>

<p>I've worked some of this out for myself on my recent travels, but I'm hardly
unique in doing so. First, I'll tell you a story. I met a guy in Las Palmas
called Toto. He helped me at a lower point with his story.</p>

<p>A few years ago he left home with 20 euros and his bike. Since then he has
travelled round the world. He sailed from Australia to Europe, then to the
Caribbean and back to Europe, and probably other places he didn't talk
about. He did some busking and when I met him had 100 euros. He didn't have
any special performing skill, he just did some silly dance. It's not really
important where he went, the story is that this is possible.</p>

<p>"Even if I only ate bread one day it doesn't matter, maybe I'll find something
else the next day."</p>

<p>I met another guy who makes a bit of money from playing music on the
street. You might call him homeless if you saw him, but since I've been back
in Edinburgh working on my geek bike project, he's been flying all over
Europe. He's probably happier than most people who work in an office.</p>

<p>It is important to be positive. You'll be interacting with people for things
like hitchhiking, and people like happy people. "You won't get a boat with a
sad face." It's also important for your own motivation.</p>

<h2>The kindness of Strangers</h2>

<p>When I was in the marina one day I went and said hello to some people. After I
short conversation I had to go and buy some food. They said no, you don't need
to, we have food. I was reluctant to take it from people who may need to more
than me but they insisted and later I found it is not really in short supply.</p>

<p>On La Palma I wanted some sort of shelter to take walking with me in the
wetter Northern part of the island. I mentioned this to someone I had just met
and so within a few minutes of meeting he had lent me his tent and a better
sleeping bag. I nearly skipped over the fact that this happened in a house I
was staying in - where I had been invited to stay by someone else I had just
met. There are many more examples but you'll need to read them in my other
blov entries when I get round to writing more.</p>

<h2>What you do need money for</h2>

<p>Basically, it comes down to convenience and speeding things up. There are a
few things you probably need it for though.</p>

<p>If you want food, you don't need money. If you want something particular to
eat, you'll probably need to buy it. If you want something now, you need to
buy it. If you can wait until you find it in a skip, you don't. If you have
time to hitchhike, you'll get there in the end. If you want to go now, you
have to pay for a bus. Of course, if you don't know where you are going,
hitchhiking is better anyway.</p>

<p>Things you pretty much do need money for are transport, some foods, and
medicines. Sometimes you might need to pay for transport: a ferry, for
example. It's very rare to find certain things in a bin, e.g. alcohol, coffee,
cooking oil, dried foods, and things with a long sell by date, but you can
live without these.</p>

<p>This post is rather unfocused because I have a lot to say on this subject and
I'm just trying to get some ideas out for now. Hopefully it is enough to show
you that this is possible. If you go out into the world with nothing but a
good attitude and an open mind you'll probably do very well.</p>

<p>I'll end with a particularly impressive story from a friend, and a link to
another blog post about this sort of thing, "<a
href="http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=18463814">The
Universe Is Conspiring to Help Us".</a></p>

<blockquote><p>"The magic is FULL ON when u arrive in a city and we have no where to sleep
and a beautiful girl called Ling comes up to u and says: I heard u play music
its is beautiful! Do u have anywhere to sleep? U can have my apartment for the
weekend when i go visit my boyfriend! So she gave us the key. AMAZING
LIFE!!!"</p></blockquote>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Love and Light as a Service]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/08/05/Love-and-Light-as-a-Service.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/08/05/Love-and-Light-as-a-Service.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2012-08-05T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/08/05/Love-and-Light-as-a-Service</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I was walking with a girl in Maspalomas and discussing the squatting and
recycling lifestyle when a tourist turned round and gave her €20. We don't
know why.</p>

<p>I asked her how she felt about taking money for nothing. I don't really like
the idea. She argued that she did not just take from the conventional society,
but provided some value, by spreading love and light.</p>

<p>Initially I thought this sounded like ridiculous hippie nonsense but later I
came to think that it is true. I think most people, ultimately, just want to be
happy. One thing that I find makes me happy is being around happy people.</p>

<p>I believe there is a French saying that "there is only one smile". When
someone sees the smile, zie then smiles, and so the smile is passed on. Thus a
pool of unfettered happy people should help to support global happiness.</p>

<p>I think the world would be a much better place if there were more people who
dedicated themselves to happiness. What else is life for?</p>

<p>So what about a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cloud_computing">Cloud
based</a> Love &amp; Light <a
href="https://www.google.co.uk/search?q=as+a+service">service</a>? I suppose
that's going to be called heaven.io and have plenty of node.js and rounded
corners.</p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Vegan Crunk Night]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/05/02/Vegan-Crunk-Night.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/05/02/Vegan-Crunk-Night.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2012-05-02T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/05/02/Vegan-Crunk-Night</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/58967572@N03/7135620371/" title="Vegan
Crunk Night by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img
src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7076/7135620371_13a888b2f4_z.jpg"
width="640" height="480" alt="Vegan Crunk Night"></a></p>

<p><q>I organise a vegan crunk night.</q></p>

<p>Now that I am eating vegan, I feel like I can somewhat legitimately organise a
vegan crunk night. I still don't know what one is meant to be, but that didn't
stop me and on Saturday we had one. There were tasty vegan noms, potluck
style. Apparently crunk is a kind of southern hip-hop, but none of us were
keen on that so we decided table top games would be a reasonable
substitute. :)</p>

<p>If you don't know what I'm talking about you need to watch this excellent
video.</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315"
src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/lVmmYMwFj1I" frameborder="0"
allowfullscreen></iframe>

]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Vegan]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/05/02/Vegan.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/05/02/Vegan.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2012-05-02T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/05/02/Vegan</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Nearly three weeks ago I adopted a vegan diet. Since the 12th of April I
have not eaten anything containing animal products, except for a few vitamin
pills until I got hold of some vegan ones.</p>

<p>I'm not sure why I am doing this. I just had a feeling it was the thing to
do. Usually I don't pay too much attention to feelings and would make
decisions based on conscious reasoning but as an experiment I am trying to pay
more attention to feelings. So this diet could be called a meta-experiment.</p>

<p>If I had to rationalise this notion, I would note that I had a vegetarian diet
for much, perhaps even most, of the time when I was <a
href="/blog/2011/11/15/Serendipitous-Blaggagio.html">travelling
recently</a>. This was simply because of what was available and
practical. Meat and milk do not survive well if you live outside in a hot
climate. I felt good when I was away and perhaps associated eating less meat
with this, even if there is no causal relation.</p>

<p>When I returned to this meat eating household I was very aware of when I ate
meat. In some cases, such as ready meals, it seemed slightly unappealing.</p>

<p>I had also become more aware of food in general, particularly if it was
expensive or rare, like fish for example. I did not object completely to
eating it, but thought that if one is going to eat something of which there is
a limited supply, and which is not necessary, then it ought to be
appreciated. If the reason to eat a certain fish is flavour and pleasure,
making oneself happy, then one should pay attention to the eating and enjoy
it, not watch TV while doing so, otherwise it is mindless destruction.</p>

<p>Whatever the reason, I decided to eat vegan, with the idea I would probably
try it for a month and see how I felt. I started because of a feeling so
I will also use that criterion to decide when to stop, if at all.</p>

<p>I am not calling myself a vegan. Partly this is because I am trying to be
careful not to over-use labels, but mostly it is because this one does not seem
to apply. The Vegan Society says, <q
cite="http://www.vegansociety.com/become-a-vegan/why.aspx">A vegan is someone
who tries to live without exploiting animals, for the benefit of animals,
people and the planet.</q>. The definition requires a certain intention, not
just action. I don't think I am motivated by the given reasons. It is probably
the simplest way to describe my diet though. I am not a vegan, I just eat like
one.</p>

<p>I had some problems in the first few days. On days two and three I woke up
unusually hungry. Someone later told me when he was vegan for a month he was
hungry all the time and ate lots of sugar to relieve it, but I found this
resolved itself by the fourth day and it has not recurred. For the first week
perhaps, I was also producing Type 6 on the <a
href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bristol_Stool_Scale">Bristol Stool
Scale</a> and needed to go to the toilet more often. Perhaps I was eating much
more fibre than I was used to, but that is probably a good thing. It seems to
have settled down now. Otherwise, I have found it quite easy so far and learnt
some things about food, cooking and veganism.</p>

<p>I don't seem to crave meat or cheese. If tasty animal food was put in front of
me, such as good quality meat or some cheese for Mellis's cheesemonger, I would
like to eat it, but I rarely think about it otherwise. I miss eggs and butter
on toast.</p>

<p>One thing that requires some effort though is cooking. This is probably not
because vegan cooking is inherently more difficult than cooking with any
ingredients, but because the things I know how to cook are not
vegan. Therefore I need to learn a lot, fast, to avoid becoming bored with a
few dishes. It's also hard to learn because the way I learnt to cook many
things I know is by discovering them somewhere, like a restaurant, and then
cooking it myself. That way I knew what I liked and what it was meant to be
like. I do not have the experience of vegan food to know what is good and what
things should come out like when I try recipes.</p>

<p>The positive side is that I am being forced to learn. I have discovered new
ingredients I would never have tried before and have probably diversified my
diet. I have become a fan of chickpeas and lentils, and would eat these more
even if I also ate meat. I've tried various grains, beans, soya flour, soya
milk, oat milk, agave syrup, and tempeh. I've also started cooking Indian
food, which I had been meaning to do for some time.</p>

<p>I also eat less processed food. Ready meals and other prepared foods often
have animal products in them, or in many cases, unspecified "flavourings". Not
eating these is probably a significant health benefit. Another side effect of
the diet is reading ingredients carefully. I have learnt what some E numbers
are, and in some cases they are things I would not want to eat whether vegan
or not.</p>

<p>It's also a good excuse to <a
href="/blog/2012/05/02/Vegan-Crunk-Night.html">organise a Vegan Crunk Night</a>!</p>

<p>I've got lots more to say on this subject but will leave it at that for now.</p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Nyan cat, Psytrance, Meditation, Programming]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/04/21/Nyancat-Psytrance-Meditation-Programming.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/04/21/Nyancat-Psytrance-Meditation-Programming.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2012-04-21T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/04/21/Nyancat-Psytrance-Meditation-Programming</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>My highest score at <a href="http://nyan.cat">nyan.cat</a> was achieved when
programming. I was at work and struggling to get much done. Then I put on
nyan cat and within a few hours I had resolved several issues. I guessed it
might be helping because it occupied the part of my brain that usually would be
free to distract me by generating unrelated thoughts.</p>

<p>I also like to listen to <a
href="http://www.last.fm/tag/psytrance">psytrance</a> music when
programming. I thought it was good because it is simple and repetitive, so
unlikely to be distracting. It's also fast and good for keeping me awake for
long hacking sessions.</p>

<p>Meditation also can help to clear the mind of unwanted thoughts and aid
concentration. I think this state of focus is what some programmers call flow.</p>

<p>I suspect now that trance music and meditation probably produce similar mental
states, which aid concentration and getting things done. I therefore recommend
that offices should play repetitive music such as nyan cat to boost
productivity and increase moral. :) I also recommend hacking at psytrance
parties.</p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Bulgarian]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2011/12/01/The-Bulgarian.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2011/12/01/The-Bulgarian.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2011-12-01T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2011/12/01/The-Bulgarian</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We walked in the sand, on wasteland at the top of the city. Around and below
us, I saw towerblocks, houses, the sea. Grass and brick in the sand. Above,
the night sky. It was warm, dark and timeless.</p>

<p>I was with The Bulgarian; I saw him, at least. He wore black, a black cloth on
his head. Round his neck, a white towel with coloured spots. He carried a
large teddy bear he had found somewhere.</p>

<p>The Bulgarian vomited.</p>

<p>"I thought you were a ghost. I thought you were my guide to see the aliens."</p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Welcome to Serendipitous Blaggagio]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2011/11/15/Serendipitous-Blaggagio.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2011/11/15/Serendipitous-Blaggagio.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2011-11-15T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2011/11/15/Serendipitous-Blaggagio</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I had a fairly normal life in Edinburgh. I worked as a software engineer from
Monday to Friday and lived in a <a
href="/blog/2011/07/26/Living.html">house</a>. I felt stuck.</p>

<p>I had read Into the Wild a while before - in which Christopher McCandless
decides after university to burn all his money and travel as a tramp around
America. He liked wilderness and ended up in Alaska, where he starved to
death. This was one thing which gave me inspiration to go travelling.</p>

<p>I also seem to like remote places. Scotland is actually quite good for this
given its size: I had walked in the Fisherfield Forest and Knoydart, and
visited Sandwood Bay on the North West coast. When I was there I wanted to
stay and try to live there for a while, by fishing and maybe in time farming,
but I had a job in Edinburgh pulling me back. On my to-visit list are
Antarctica, Siberia (with Samoyeds), Mongolia (by bike I think) and now
Alaska. The middle of the Atlantic is also a pretty remote place.</p>

<p><img
src="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/b/b6/Sandwood_Bay_North_View.jpg"
alt="Sandwood Bay" title="Sandwood Bay. Yes, Scotland." /></p>

<p>I had also done some sailing recently, around Scottish islands and Wales. I
thought then about going further and crossing the Atlantic.</p>

<p>Another source of inspiration for another life was Steve Roberts, the <a
href="http://microship.com/bike/index.html">Technomad</a>. I am a geek of
computing and radio and found his website when looking for designs for <a
href="/blog/2011/03/25/HF-Bicycle-Mobile-Experiment-Part-3.html">bicycle
mounted HF antenna systems</a>. He travelled round the USA for years on a bike
fitted with computer and radio systems. I have done some bike touring in
Europe and I thought about building a bike like this myself to go further.</p>

<p>Finally, while at work in Edinburgh I was reading In Patagonia, by Bruce
Chatwin. I realised it was wrong to stay in Edinburgh and Scotland for so long
and I should stop thinking and go out and see these places. The ideas of
sailing the Atlantic and travelling in Patagonia came together.</p>

<p>I resigned and started planning my trip. I heard that many boats cross from Las
Palmas de Gran Canaria so I flew there to look for a boat.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/58967572@N03/6431731859/" title="Cloud computing, or stupid things to carry to 6000ft by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7023/6431731859_5862ee9677_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="Cloud computing, or stupid things to carry to 6000ft"></a></p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Living in a Secret Volcano Base]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2011/08/14/Living-in-a-Secret-Volcano-Base.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2011/08/14/Living-in-a-Secret-Volcano-Base.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2011-08-14T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2011/08/14/Living-in-a-Secret-Volcano-Base</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/canete/2641080054/" title="Llaima 2 by
i.canete, on Flickr"><img
src="http://farm4.static.flickr.com/3022/2641080054_8db36ea327_z.jpg"
width="640" height="480" alt="Llaima 2"></a></p>

<p>No one ever really thinks about the practicalities of living in a
volcano. Every evil genius aspires to build the ultimate
volcano lair but despite the romantic attraction there are certain
problems when it comes to actually living and working in one.</p>

<p>It would not do to have people locate my secret lair so I can't give too
many details, but nevertheless I hope to share some lessons sufficient to
discourage others from burning themselves on such an arrangement.</p>

<p>Obviously, it's not a real volcano unless it is active. The heat is
certainly useful to provide energy to run mad science but it can make
the living conditions uncomfortable. You need to consider
cooling. This is an important point in favour of the island
volcano.</p>

<p>There are certain precautions you must take though or you may not like it
atoll. Desert islands require more to be imported by sea - too much traffic
increases the risk of unwanted attention.</p>

<p>There are issues common to all volcano types. Lava can overrun your base. The
ground can melt and quake underneath it. Noxious gases can be a problem, depending on
your state of evil mutation.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/photoknipser/2094172110/"
title="Gletscher im Mutnovsky-Krater by photoknipser, on Flickr"><img
src="http://farm3.static.flickr.com/2171/2094172110_48058f47a5_z.jpg?zz=1"
width="640" height="423" alt="Gletscher im Mutnovsky-Krater"></a></p>

<p>Given these difficulties, why would you still want your base in a volcano?
Some good reasons include:</p>

<ul>
<li>Necessary to forge unobtainium.</li>
<li>Required to destroy certain gold-based artifacts.</li>
<li>Good supply of sulphur compounds and other evil chemicals.</li>
<li>People tend to avoid getting too close. Those who do are probably scientists so no one will miss them.</li>
<li>Extremely convenient for disposing of bodies.</li>
<li>Explosions and smoke will be masked by natural seismic activity and should not draw too much attention.</li>
</ul>


<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/21331626@N07/3932218443/"
title="Untitled by Adrien Cretin, on Flickr"><img
src="http://farm4.static.flickr.com/3501/3932218443_a501ef5cbe_z.jpg"
width="640" height="425" alt=""></a></p>

<p>Let me know if you decide on the volcano option. Do you have any hints?</p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ways of Living]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2011/07/26/Living.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2011/07/26/Living.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2011-07-26T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2011/07/26/Living</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There are ways to live other than in a conventional house.</p>

<p><img src="http://farm7.static.flickr.com/6012/5975477373_d3de359f7b_z.jpg"
width="640" height="480" alt="Bilston Glen site"></p>

<p>On Sunday, I went to visit a community in Bilston Glen. Here is a forest with
tree houses and ground houses. They are made almost entirely of scrap - parts
from skips, wood, rope, glass, planks, carpet, sofas, mattresses, oil drums,
gas cylinders.</p>

<p>There is a small hydroelectric plant in the river - it can charge mobile
phones, which have signal here, and suchlike.</p>

<p>Food is also available from skips. People can live happily from what others
throw away. Perhaps better in many cases, if someone could only afford lower
quality food. The several large fridges were full when I visited.</p>

<p>Are people happy here? I don't know in general, but one girl I spoke to seemed
fairly indifferent - it just seemed to be normal. Later, a friend of mine
moved here and liked it.</p>

<p>There are a mixture of people who live here. Some have resided for years,
others stay for months or days. Some are young and some are old. All will tend
to smell of campfire.</p>

<p>I could live in a boat. Move when I want. Work anywhere. Or a tent, hammock,
bivvy bag. I thought a hammock in scaffolding could be a good place to sleep
if one had to in a town, to be near an office for example.</p>

<p>Is homelessness really bad? It is hard to separate it from poverty and
addiction because that seems to be the cause of so much of it but it is not
necessarily bad. What is homelessness anyway? Are you homeless if you live in
an hotel?  What if you are an explorer with tent? What is a home? Can a bike
be a home? Is it somewhere comfortable? Is it a place or a feeling? Is it
necessary?</p>

<p>I left the woods and soon after IKEA offered me "my dream home". It came with
a contract binding me to money, a bank account, an address, a job, and a place
to keep the bloody thing - a sofa.</p>

<p><img src="http://farm7.static.flickr.com/6148/5976040942_e35f5e01f4_z.jpg"
width="640" height="480" alt="IKEA, near treehouses"></p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
</feed>
