<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Alistair MacLeod, MM0HAI: Posts tagged electronics</title>
 <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/tag/electronics/index.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://mm0hai.net"/>
 <updated>2012-03-20T20:12:23+00:00</updated>
 <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/tag/electronics</id>
 <author>
   <name>Alistair N. MacLeod</name>
   <email>anm@mm0hai.net</email>
 </author>

 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 <entry>
   <title>SGC SG-211 Mini Smartuner Teardown</title>
   <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2011/06/02/SGC-211-autotuner.html"/>
   <updated>2011-06-02T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2011/06/02/SGC-211-autotuner</id>
   <content type="html">My&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; SGC autotuner had an accident when I stupidly put it down on a
bench. The boat heeled and it landed on the connector, bending it. Luckily the
connector was mounted on the case and wired up, rather than soldered directly
to the board, so there was no damage other than a bent box. I took it apart
so I could straighten it out and thought I might as well take some photos
while I was at it.

The item in question is an &lt;a
href=&quot;http://www.sgcworld.com/211ProductPage.html&quot;&gt;SG-211&lt;/a&gt;. I'm not going
to review it or say much other than it is pretty good and the case is soft
aluminium.

&lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow&quot; href=&quot;http://www.flickr.com/photos/58967572@N03/5788517160/&quot; title=&quot;Top of board&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://farm3.static.flickr.com/2327/5788517160_677a9ff43e_z.jpg&quot; width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;428&quot; alt=&quot;Top of board&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow&quot; href=&quot;http://www.flickr.com/photos/58967572@N03/5788523098/&quot; title=&quot;Bottom of board&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://farm4.static.flickr.com/3273/5788523098_208ab1258e_z.jpg&quot; width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;441&quot; alt=&quot;Bottom of board&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

The relays are interesting. I have been meaning to design an automatic ground
tuner for my &lt;a
href=&quot;/blog/2011/03/25/HF-Bicycle-Mobile-Experiment-Part-3.html&quot;&gt;bike&lt;/a&gt; but
one problem I have is the inability to find any latching relays. It seems SGC
either had their own made, or have had some branded to hide where they get
these mythical devices.

&lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow&quot; href=&quot;http://www.flickr.com/photos/58967572@N03/5787968241/&quot; title=&quot;Custom relays?&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://farm3.static.flickr.com/2440/5787968241_e4bbc34dee_z.jpg&quot; width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;236&quot; alt=&quot;Custom relays?&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow&quot; href=&quot;http://www.flickr.com/photos/58967572@N03/5787972187/&quot; title=&quot;Bottom half of case&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://farm6.static.flickr.com/5230/5787972187_20fb28eaa0_z.jpg&quot; width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;436&quot; alt=&quot;Bottom half of case&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

The white wire is connected to a front panel toggle switch which was added by
SGC. The new switch disables retuning to avoid a problem where it would retune
in the middle of an over. I'm not sure if the uninsulated wires above this are
part of the mod. I hope they are not fixing a bad board. The switch is useful
but I'm a bit concerned about what this will do for durability. The controller
is a PIC.

&lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow&quot; href=&quot;http://www.flickr.com/photos/58967572@N03/5788529612/&quot; title=&quot;PIC&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://farm6.static.flickr.com/5264/5788529612_7265d6aa5f_z.jpg&quot; width=&quot;415&quot; height=&quot;640&quot; alt=&quot;PIC&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

A reference / dummy load?

&lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow&quot; href=&quot;http://www.flickr.com/photos/58967572@N03/5787974261/&quot; title=&quot;Reference / load?&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://farm6.static.flickr.com/5229/5787974261_2a675e013d_m.jpg&quot; width=&quot;240&quot; height=&quot;149&quot; alt=&quot;Reference / load R?&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;


--

&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; Actually borrowed, but he'll never know my bending was that good. :-)</content>
 </entry>
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 <entry>
   <title>My introduction to the Arduino platform</title>
   <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2011/05/25/Arduino-Getting-started-with-Seeeduino.html"/>
   <updated>2011-05-25T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2011/05/25/Arduino-Getting-started-with-Seeeduino</id>
   <content type="html">I have been meaning to do several microcontroller based projects for some time
now. Ideally I wanted to do it without spending any money so I decided to make
myself a PIC programmer with some samples from Microchip. This would also make
the process more interesting.

The plan was to make a &lt;a href=&quot;http://usbpicprog.org/&quot;&gt;usbpicprog&lt;/a&gt; and
bootstrap it with a serial port based programmer using an old computer.  I
bought all the parts, including copper clad board and ferric chloride but
never quite got round to doing it. This was in part because I was not very
keen to have to work with ferric chloride and I didn't want to dissolve the
sink.

Meanwhile, I had been hearing about the Arduino more and more. Initially I
ignored it as something for artists and people who didn't know what they were
doing. I had spent some time at university learning about and using real
microcontrollers with none of this boot loader nonsense so I did not think I
needed such things. Then I realised that being leet enough not to require
simplification did not make quicker development a bad thing. :-) I decided I
had wasted enough time and just wanted to get something done, so I bought an
Arduino.

&lt;img src=&quot;http://farm6.static.flickr.com/5223/5773580603_eee48af87b.jpg&quot;
width=&quot;500&quot; height=&quot;375&quot; alt=&quot;Seeeduino and ethernet shield&quot;&gt;

I actually chose the seeedunio, an Arduino clone. The design is open so this
is allowed and in fact there are some improvements made in the
seeeduino. Primarily I chose it though because it was the cheapest. I still
don't like the idea of paying decapounds for a single basic microcontroller
and some soldering. I also ordered an ethernet shield, which is what an
expansion card is called in the Arduino world. These arrived yesterday.

It took me longer than I would have liked to get started, with the blinking LED
hello world of microcontrollers, because there were no instructions about the
correct settings. After some googling and trial and error I determined that I
had to set the reset switch on the board to auto and, in the Arduino IDE, set
the board type to &lt;type&gt;Deumilanove or Nano w/ ATmega328&lt;/type&gt;.  After that
I very quickly had it beaconing my callsign on the board mounted LED attached
to pin 13. So far quite reasonable.

Then I decided to plug in the ethernet board and run the example programs.  I
had to stick all the source files in the same directory and change the ip
address and then I was pinging the board. It took only a few minutes. This I
thought was pretty ridiculous. Then I used the web server program. It
worked. I couldn't really believe this - this did not seem like electronics at
all. I would expect this to have taken weeks of debugging, loose wires, errors
in PCB design, software bugs and frustration but here it was working in a few
minutes with no test gear in sight. I have certainly confirmed my get things
done faster conjecture.

It was not quite as good though when I wanted to connect stuff up to it. The
board did not come with a data sheet and I could not find much at all online.
In the end I went to Atmel's web site and downloaded the datasheet for the
ATmega328P on my board. Included below are some useful figures from it.

Reference
=========

Seeeduino - Summary of Initial Setup
-----------------------------------

I am using the Seeeduino V2.21 which is also marked ARD128D2P.

It uses the ATmega328P.

This is the error I got initially:

&lt;code&gt;avrdude: stk500_disable(): protocol error, expect=0x14, resp=0x00&lt;/code&gt;

The solution:

- Move reset switch to auto
- Set board type to &lt;code&gt;Deumilanove or Nano w/ ATmega328&lt;/code&gt;.

ATmega328P Data
===============

Absolute Maximums
-----------------

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Operating Temperature&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;-55°C to +125°C&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Voltage on any Pin except RESET with respect to Ground&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;-0.5V to VCC+0.5V&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Maximum Operating Voltage&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;6.0V&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;DC Current per I/O Pin&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;40.0mA&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;DC Current VCC and GND Pins&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;200.0mA&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

Programming
-----------

The Arduino environment uses C but with some magic, see
&lt;a href=&quot;http://arduino.cc/en/Hacking/BuildProcess&quot;&gt;Arduino Build Process&lt;/a&gt;.


Ethernet board
--------------

It's ENC28J60 based. This is not the same as the official one, which uses the
Wiznet W5100.

Bought from &lt;a
href=&quot;http://www.ekitszone.com/Products/4-enc28j60-ethernet-shield-for-arduino.aspx&quot;&gt;ekitszone&lt;/a&gt;.
Looks well made and works.
</content>
 </entry>
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
</feed>
