<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss">

  <title><![CDATA[River MacLeod, MM0HAI: Posts tagged usa]]></title>

  <link href="https://mm0hai.net/blog/tag/usa/index.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://mm0hai.net/"/>
  <updated>2016-12-15T20:36:09+00:00</updated>
  <id>https://mm0hai.net/blog/tag/usa</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[River MacLeod]]></name>
  </author>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[USA Calling]]></title>
    <link href="https://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/05/24/USA-Calling.html"/>
    <updated>2013-05-24T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>https://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/05/24/USA-Calling</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I have thought about giving up this cycling nonsense and moving to the USA. I
would buy a Harley-Davidson instead, and eat burgers and donuts until fat.</p>

<p>I’ve not been to the US yet, but I think I’ve got almost the same experience in
this part of Honduras. All along the road into San Pedro Sula, there are huge
signs for fast food places. I’m now in the City Mall of San Pedro Sula, which
has the same American junk food chains, many of which I have now tried for the
first time over the last couple of days. Wendy’s, Applebee’s, Dunkin’ Donuts,
Subway, Quiznos, PizzaHut, KFC, Burger King… Conspicuously missing are
Starbucks and Costa Coffee.</p>

<p>I get the impression that people in Honduras want to be American. There are
shops call things like “American Company”, the coffee places are called
“Espresso Americano”, there was a huge billboard with a topless man on it that
said “American” - maybe advertising that clothes shop, or selling American
men. It seem the girls here like gringos, too. A giggling car full were
shouting at me and taking photos when I was cycling into town.</p>

<p>Mostly it’s the food though, which is at American prices - way more than local
food can cost. I think the idea is “you are what you eat”. If you are rich
enough to afford Mcdonalds, you eat your way to America. I’ve tried several of
these places, but suspect I won’t qualify for citizenship until my BMI gets up
rather more.</p>

<p>Apart from the food, the USA has had a huge influence here, and is the reason
why it’s not safe to go out, and why the place I am staying has a high wall
topped with spikes, razor wire and an electric fence. This town, San Pedro
Sula, is run by drugs cartels. They only have money and power because of the
ridiculous policies of the US and its War on Drugs. If drugs were not illegal
in the US, there would probably not be 3 people getting shot dead per day in
just this town, and probably fewer people dying in the US too, if they can get
pure substances of known dose.</p>

<p>So I’m in the mall eating junk, because it’s a relatively safe place, and
giving money to companies who send it back to the US to pay for the violence
outside. It’s a prison where I’m paying to cause the problem that keeps me
here.</p>

<p>There is also a great US influence on Belize, although it seems much less
destructive. There are many products imported from the US. There are brands I
had heard of “in popular culture”, but some I had never seen. I drank the cool
aid, for example. I didn’t buy the Lucky Charms, but I did have some pop
tarts. The poptarts where in honour of nyancat though, so I couldn’t miss
those.</p>
]]></content>
   <georss:point>14.906967 -87.808228</georss:point>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
