<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss">

  <title><![CDATA[River MacLeod, MM0HAI: Posts tagged meditation]]></title>

  <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/tag/meditation/index.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mm0hai.net/"/>
  <updated>2014-04-20T21:09:55+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/tag/meditation</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[River MacLeod]]></name>
  </author>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Vipassana]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/08/05/Vipassana.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/08/05/Vipassana.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2013-08-05T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/08/05/Vipassana</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/9392460997/" title="Cushion-25 by
mm0hai, on Flickr"><img
src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5496/9392460997_3ab694ea18_z.jpg"
width="640" height="480" alt="Cushion-25"></a></p>

<p>I spent 10 full days sitting on a cushion meditating, on a course run by
S. N. Goenka (by audio recording) and his assistant teacher, Mirjam Berns, who
was present in Costa Rica. I had heard about these courses several times from
travellers over the past year and a half, and now I was near one I thought it
was time to try it.</p>

<p>I didn't really know what meditation was before this course and that is why I
went - curiosity.  There are many forms of meditation. I think what they have
in common, at least those I know of, is concentrating on something. It could
be an image in the mind, a sound like a mantra or drum, breathing, or in the
case of vipassana, the sensations on the body. They have different purposes,
the simplest being to develop discipline of the mind and an ability to
concentrate. I don't know much more about meditation in general though, so
will talk about what we were taught on this course.</p>

<p>The first thing we did was ānāpāna meditation. This meant focusing on the
breath, and specifically the sensations of it moving inside the nostril, and
on the upper lip. It is not about controlling the breath, only observing it as
it comes naturally. The purpose was to develop discipline, and improve our
ability to feel sensations on the body. We did this for most of four days. It
hurt, physically, especially in the knees because of sitting for so long. The
pain was worse because there was no distraction. It was also very boring. I
spent most of the time thinking rather than concentrating.</p>

<p>On the evening of the fourth day and for almost all of the rest of the course,
we were taught and practised vipassana. This involves observing sensations all
over the body. Sensation means any feeling such as hot, cold, itching, pain,
movement of air, etc. While doing this, we were to maintain equanimity and the
awareness of anicca, a Pali word which means change. Equanimity meant we were
not to judge sensation as good or bad, not to be averse to pain, or crave
pleasant sensations. We were also to observe that all sensations are temporary
- they will go away eventually. This was one way to avoid reacting too much to
the pain.</p>

<p>The theory is that, as Goenka says Gautama Buddha taught, suffering is caused
by desire. This could be craving for something not there, or aversion to
something that is. By learning to avoid these feelings, suffering can stop. I
wondered why just observe the sensations on the body? The idea is that all
thoughts or emotions will manifest in the body in some way. By learning not to
react to feelings in the body, all reactions should be covered.</p>

<p>The reactions of craving and aversion are called sankaras. They also said that
sankaras build up - there is a store of old ones. This causes continued
suffering, and rebirth. If you can get rid of them all, then you will be free
of suffering and not have to be reborn. They said that when you stop creating
new sankaras, the new ones come to the surface, and if you remain equanimous,
they disappear.</p>

<p>I found that they did surface. I had maybe five or so in total. When my mind
was clear, they would come suddenly as an image or word out of nowhere, not
connected to any previous thought. The first one I had, for example, was the
image of a dropped mobile phone. Obviously I felt some aversion or pain that I
may have broken an expensive thing.</p>

<p>The sensations on the body can be of two types. "Gross" and "subtle". The
gross sensations are things like pain. There is also a feeling that I got when
there was nothing else, a slight pleasant tingling. When this happens all over
the body, interesting things happen. At one point, briefly, on day eight I
think, I felt my whole body shaking, and oscillating around a vertical line
through the middle. It was rather like a feeling I have had occasionally when
falling asleep - the whole body spins.</p>

<p>The interpretation given by the teacher was that the subtle tingling is you
feeling subatomic particles, and that the shaking and vibrating is feeling the
underlying fabric of the universe. There is a common idea amongst some
spiritual people that the universe is fundamentally "vibrational", and
improving you life or increasing your consciousness means to operate at a
higher frequency. They never say what it is that is meant to be vibrating
though. Maybe it is something like string theory. Maybe that's where string
theory came from, I don't know. Anyway, I don't take this feeling as evidence
of the nature of the universe - it could also be explained by the brain
failing to function correctly after being subjected to this unusual practice.</p>

<p>If you practice more, it is possible for the effect to go much further. Rather
than just the surface, if you can feel only subtle sensation inside the body
as well, then it can feel like the whole body has dissolved. As far as I
understand it from asking people, you don't really feel a physical body
anymore.</p>

<p>As far as I practised the technique, I did have experiences consistent with
what the teachers said. I don't see any reason why they would lie about the
rest, so it seems that with further practice I could experience, or think I
was experiencing, the universe at a more fundamental level, and free myself of
suffering. Maybe I would even clear old sankaras from past lives, which when
it happens apparently allows you to remember those lives. I still don't know
that I agree with all the theory though. One thing the teacher said on one of
his talks though, was that if you don't like the theory just ignore it - the
practice will still work.</p>

<p>Will I keep practising? They say you should do two hours a day. I'm not
sure. I can see that there could be benefits, but on the other hand it
hurts. This is not relaxing, it is not easy. It is physically and mentally
painful and unpleasant. I had a rather unpleasant image at the end of the
course and decided to give my mind a rest for a while. Maybe I'll try it again
sometime, but I am not very keen. On the other hand, if the theory is all
correct, this technique is how I can free myself from suffering and escape the
cycle of rebirth and endless suffering, so if true it seems that it is the
most important, or only thing I should do. That would mean becoming a monk, or
at least devoting significant time to meditating.</p>

<p>I also want to describe the way the course was run. It was like living the
life of a monk for 10 days. Men and women were separated. Talking was not
allowed. Food was eaten at breakfast and lunchtime, but not after 12pm, except
a little fruit for new students (those on their first 10 day course). Reading,
writing, music and any other communications were not allowed. Really, there was
nothing to do but meditation, eat, and rest. The teaching was almost entirely
from S. N. Goenka, in the form of audio recordings. Sometimes he taught during
meditation sessions, but he spoke mostly in the evening discourse, which was
sometimes a lesson, and often rather like a sermon. On the last full day, the
tenth, we were allowed to talk again and genders were no longer separated in
some public spaces. Everyone seemed quite happy to talk, but I found the noise
rather overwhelming initially.</p>

<p>On the last full day I saw a sloth! It was climbing a tree right beside the
path in the centre. I have never seen one before but I like them. I like how
they are lazy and imagining that they just hang out in trees all day being
fluffy and cuddly.</p>

<p>I got the bus back to San Jose the next day, the eleventh, after tidying up
and things in the morning. I didn't want to think about meditation or do it
more. On the bus though, I found my mind was very quiet.  I tried meditating
for lack of anything else to do - I didn't want to read or write - but I
couldn't because of the movement of the bus. It covered the sensations in the
body I was looking for. Maybe it is acceptable to feel the bus shaking you
around. Anyway, I didn't want to think about it or write about it for some
time and did other things until now, just over a week later.</p>
]]></content>
   <georss:point>9.328286 -83.749638</georss:point>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
