<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss">

  <title><![CDATA[River MacLeod, MM0HAI: Posts tagged anarchism]]></title>

  <link href="https://mm0hai.net/blog/tag/anarchism/index.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://mm0hai.net/"/>
  <updated>2017-10-31T21:18:18+01:00</updated>
  <id>https://mm0hai.net/blog/tag/anarchism</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[River MacLeod]]></name>
  </author>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Mi cueva!]]></title>
    <link href="https://mm0hai.net/blog/2016/12/20/es-mi-cueva.html"/>
    <updated>2016-12-20T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>https://mm0hai.net/blog/2016/12/20/es-mi-cueva</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I’m starting to really feel Proudhon.</p>

<p>When I was last here, we shared a cave between around ten of us. If a stranger
had come, we would have undoubtedly invited them to join us round the fire. I
returned to the cave this night, and found that the lock on the bars that were
installed when the policia threw us out had been broken, and replaced. I stood
and contemplated my history here, until presently I heard the gate
open. “Buenas”, “Hola”, I said. “Vaya vaya, … mi cueva! …”. He wanted me
out the barranco. He even claimed the neighbouring caves, the view maybe…</p>

<p>Previously, on this Canarian trip, I visited La Tomatera. The shared meals
round the one table were gone. The kitchen was bare. One man ate a takeaway
sandwich. Instead of a welcome note, the fridge said “Kill all hippies”.  A
room had a lock. I suspect most of the soft furnishings, the comfort, had gone
behind it.</p>

<p>I feel like the island has lost its soul. The stage is still here but the
actors gone. Of course it was the people who made what we had here
before. It’s probably stupid to say the island has changed. It’s been here
forever compared to us. The cave I’m writing in now was occupied before the
Spanish came. The bars will break soon enough.</p>

<p>Property is theft.</p>

<p><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/6/5472/31737151766_201d797963_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="Cave Bear" /></p>
]]></content>
   <georss:point>28.06 -15.51</georss:point>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Caves, not concrete]]></title>
    <link href="https://mm0hai.net/blog/2016/12/18/caves-not-allowed.html"/>
    <updated>2016-12-18T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>https://mm0hai.net/blog/2016/12/18/caves-not-allowed</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://c8.staticflickr.com/1/580/31658253711_c1fd5cf681_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="Coto Privado de Caza Sign" /></p>

<p>Last time en Canarias, I discovered some caves and slept in them a while. I
was excited at the novelty, and to discover how good caves are for
living. They stay warm at night because the rock holds the heat of the
day. They surround you with warmth and look after you. It is like mother
nature saying “I love you, here is a home I made for you”.</p>

<p>The government says no. No entry. Private hunting estate. Only killing allowed
here, not living. Go and pay someone to make you a concrete box.</p>

<p>Now I’m angry.</p>
]]></content>
   <georss:point>27.85 -15.68</georss:point>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
