<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss">

  <title><![CDATA[River MacLeod, MM0HAI: Posts tagged 2012]]></title>

  <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/tag/2012/index.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mm0hai.net/"/>
  <updated>2015-07-25T12:26:37+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/tag/2012</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[River MacLeod]]></name>
  </author>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Great Flood and a Rainbow]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/21/End-of-the-World.html"/>
    <updated>2012-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/21/End-of-the-World</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One reason I left on <a href="/blog/tag/cyclewho/">this trip</a> before I was
ready was to get to Palenque in time for the end of the world. There is a
Mayan prophecy about the end of an era of Babylon, the broken world, and the
transformation to a new world where people live consciously. I made it to the
Rainbow Gathering near Palenque a few days before the 21st.</p>

<p>The 21st of December 2012 was to be the end of the world. In the morning there
was going to be a ceremony at the Palenque ruins. Before that, a global
meditation at 0411, I think it was. That is not a time when I would find it
easy to get up. Someone suggested going to sleep at the main circle so I might
wake up, so I went out there with my bivvy bag.</p>

<p>I lay down to sleep, and it started to rain. I was not concerned about this,
because I had previously tested this bivvy bag up a hill in Scotland when it
rained all night and I remained dry, so I tried to go to sleep.</p>

<p>The rain started to become very heavy. I could feel the lumps of water
whacking into me. I started to get wet. I don't think it was coming in the
opening - probably it was so hard it was forced through the material. I stayed
for a while anyway hoping it would stop, but after maybe half an hour it was
still raining heavily.</p>

<p>The drummers had left and the previously strong fire had been extinguished by
the rain. I was now on my own in the dark, getting cold in the heaviest rain I
had every seen, which showed no sign of stopping. I started to wonder if this
was the end. If you want to clean the world ready for a new one rain might be
a good way to do it. It would not be the first time there had been a Great
Flood for something like this.</p>

<p>I decided to get up before I became hypothermic. I made it back to my camp on
the paths which were now mud rivers. My tent was still there, but full of
water. I slept in my damp sleeping bag and missed the morning ceremonies.</p>

<p>The world seemed the same in the morning, but then I realised that actually
anything could have happened. Maybe the rest outside the Rainbow had gone. I
would have to check it out later.</p>
]]></content>
   <georss:point>17.483017 -91.925139</georss:point>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
