<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss">

  <title><![CDATA[River MacLeod, MM0HAI: Posts tagged captainslog]]></title>

  <link href="https://mm0hai.net/blog/tag/captainslog/index.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://mm0hai.net/"/>
  <updated>2018-01-14T19:05:55+01:00</updated>
  <id>https://mm0hai.net/blog/tag/captainslog</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[River MacLeod]]></name>
  </author>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[An unpleasant day]]></title>
    <link href="https://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/04/30/Hospital.html"/>
    <updated>2013-04-30T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/04/30/Hospital</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The day I woke up with a fever and ended up in hospital.</p>

<p>I woke up in my hammock at the Guatemalan migration post at about 5am with a
fever, but tried to ignore it for the moment. I started cycling later, and got
about 20km along the road before I stopped at a petrol station. I was feeling
pretty bad now. I could only just eat a biscuit thing (bran fruit, it was
called) and I drank a bottle of Gatorade. I didn’t think it was a good idea to
cycle further, and I would not have enjoyed cycling feeling like that, so I
waited for a bus.</p>

<p>I had read that if you get a fever after being in a malarious area the first
thing you need to do is get checked for Malaria. I thought I would go to the
nearest town for a doctor, but I wanted to go to Flores as I thought that
would be a nice place to recover, and also there would be a cash machine
there. I didn’t know the exchange rate so only risked very little in pesos to
the border based moneychangers.</p>

<p>The bus was something like a large minibus, with a roofrack where my bike
went. This was the worst bus ride of my life. The road was stony, long,
straight, and with nothing interesting at all to see. It is, I think, also the
worst road to cycle I have ever seen. The bus was hot, and as the journey went
on it got hotter. More people got on, and I started to feel worse.</p>

<p>At 1200, I got hold of my paracetamol and started pouring water on my head and
face to try and avoid my brain overheating.</p>

<p>When it was getting really quite bad, on got a preacher who started screaming
stuff about jesus at the top of his voice right beside me. I considered
trying to tell him to stop but realised that arguing with a mad man would just
encourage him. Interestingly the driver seemed to allow this. I was also
concerned that if I said anything the rest of the bus would lynch me for being
an evil atheist. I told myself that the kind of malaria you get around here is
not fatal, but I was concerned about it anyway. I considered asking the
preacher for the last rites - that would probably get him to shut up. In the
end I realised I had some earplugs to hand, so fitted them to some
improvement.</p>

<p>It would be a reasonable way to die anyway. A jungle in some exotic country
seems a respectable death for a British gentleman explorer.</p>

<p>We stopped at petrol station. Here some men threw buckets of water over the
bus and washed it, while some others stood around with guns. I was soon to
discover Guatemalans like standing around with guns. I wasn’t happy about the
lack of sense of urgency to reach our destination.</p>

<p>Finally we got to somewhere urban, near our destination. It was crazily busy,
with Tuk-Tuks, other vehicles and people. People getting on the bus to sell
refrescos and snacks. When we got going again it wasn’t too far to the hospital.</p>

<p>I had asked about a doctor initially but later asked them to drop me at the
hospital. I thought they would actually take me there, but they dumped me on
the other side of the road a few hundred meters away. I felt very weak and
probably couldn’t think properly, but out of necessity I managed to load up my
bike and push it across the road without being run over.</p>

<p>There was a kind man at the reception who took me to the emergency department,
with my bike. They wanted to register me with my passport, but otherwise no
paperwork, and treatment was free. I had to speak to several doctors before
they decided someone knew enough English to understand. I tried Spanish first
but apparently they were not happy with that.</p>

<p>They took blood and urine samples. I was severely dehydrated so I was given
two bags of saline i.v. and some drug I can’t remember to reduce fever and
pain. The tests for malaria and dengue were negative, but I might have had
some infection. I think the main problem was that I didn’t eat and drink
enough.</p>

<p>I watched a bit of Marc Beaumont’s Americas film before I left San Cris. It
said he has to eat six meals a day. I laughed at that because there is no way
I was eating that much. On the road through the forest mostly there was just
biscuits and sugar drinks. Usually shops also had some rice and tuna, and
occasionally some veg., but generally it was very difficult to eat
properly. Anyway, it turns out if you go cycling in 35C, midday sun and don’t
eat and drink properly, you end up in hospital.</p>

<p>I have now been recovering for a few days in an hotel and now a hostel in
Flores. I couldn’t eat for the first couple of days but I had some
smoothies. I’m pretty much recovered now and enjoying the food at Los Amigos
hostel, which includes tofu and vegetable curry - possibly the only place in
the country (except maybe Antigua) to have such things.</p>

<p>I think I’ll go and check out the warm showers place near here, clean the
bike, and head to Belize in a few days maybe.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8696706948/" title="DSCF4210 by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8396/8696706948_209dc5e844_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="DSCF4210" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8695285843/" title="DSCF4201 by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8535/8695285843_69d392516c_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="DSCF4201" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8696405860/" title="DSCF4199 by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8399/8696405860_486a234a45_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="DSCF4199" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8696705644/" title="DSCF4208 by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8114/8696705644_c7e56dac62_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="DSCF4208" /></a></p>
]]></content>
   <georss:point>16.913470 -89.912978</georss:point>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
