<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss">

  <title><![CDATA[River MacLeod, MM0HAI: Posts tagged hammocks]]></title>

  <link href="https://mm0hai.net/blog/tag/hammocks/index.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://mm0hai.net/"/>
  <updated>2018-01-13T14:46:11+01:00</updated>
  <id>https://mm0hai.net/blog/tag/hammocks</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[River MacLeod]]></name>
  </author>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hammocks for Cycle Touring]]></title>
    <link href="https://mm0hai.net/blog/2014/04/20/hammocks-for-cycle-touring.html"/>
    <updated>2014-04-20T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://mm0hai.net/blog/2014/04/20/hammocks-for-cycle-touring</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8695127663" title="Camping on road to Frontera Corozal by River, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8534/8695127663_dd289b5752_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="Camping on road to Frontera Corozal" /></a></p>

<p>Most cycle tourists use tents, but it is worth considering taking a hammock.</p>

<p>Hammocks are particularly good for use in tropical areas. If there is tropical
rain, you do not want to be on the ground. Tents are likely to fill up with
water or be washed down the river, as happened to many people I was with in
Mexico. They can also fill up with poisonous and biting insects. It is not
easy to find somewhere to put a tent in a jungle. Hammocks keep you off the
ground, avoiding these problems.</p>

<p>A tarp over a hammock keeps wet and dry gear totally separate. You can
organise everything, pack, and unpack in the rain underneath the tarp. It
gives you a lot of space to do things like cooking and eating, too. I kept my
bike under the same tarp of the hammock. In the photo below, I had my hammock
hung over the bike.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/9079582774" title="Everything under the tarp on a rainy morning by River, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2823/9079582774_8a4464f150_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="Everything under the tarp on a rainy morning" /></a></p>

<p>Hammocks can help to keep you cool. Air circulates all around you. If you
sleep on the ground, you probably need some sort of padding which will also
act as insulation and can feel smothering. If you have enough water, you can
even wet the hammock for cooling.</p>

<p>I found my hammock to be very comfortable too. I now prefer it to a bed.</p>

<p>Something people think could be a disadvantage of hammocks is that there might
not be anywhere to hang them. I did not have a problem with this on my trip in
Central America, and I think it is not likely to happen unless you are in a
desert, maybe. Conversely, you could have trouble finding somewhere to put a
tent. If you are cycling through a jungle, the only flat ground, if any, will
be right beside the road. Obviously this is pretty dangerous, because of the
risk of being hit by traffic, and you are an easy target for a robbery. With a
hammock you can get off the road and be very well hidden.</p>

<p>A real disadvantage of a hammock is that it is not good for doing anything
apart from sleeping. Trying to drink a cup of tea and use a laptop is likely
to end in disaster. (Unless you have a tea-proof Thinkpad.) They are also not
great for more than one person, at least my one was not. Maybe larger ones
designed for this would be ok.</p>

<p>A mosquito net is essential if in any affected area. Some hammocks have built
in nets, and it is also possible to buy a net bag that contains a hammock, or
to make a net and hang it over a sheet hammock. The bottom of the hammock has
to be bite proof too. It seems that having more than one layer of fabric
achieves this, even if they are quite thin.</p>

<p>After a bad experience with a tent in Mexico, I tried out some hammocks and
decided to buy a DD Frontline hammock.</p>

<p>I like this design a lot. It has a net with zips on both sides of the
hammock. The hammock itself is a rectangular sheet gathered at the ends. The
net is held above with elastic cords at each end. I found it very
comfortable. The net worked well and gave good ventilation and space. It has
two bottom layers, which protect against bites, and allows you to put a
sleeping mat between them if it is cold.</p>

<p>I was generally very pleased with the design of the DD hammock, but the build
quality is not very good. It came with loose threads, and there were some
unpleasant ripping noises at times. I’m not sure what it was but it sounded
like stitches ripping. There was also a problem with the net, which had larger
holes in one area where it had not been made properly. It was not a problem
for mosquitoes, but would have let midges in. It is good enough for light use,
but I would be a bit concerned about using it for a long time. I think DD
ought to offer a sturdier version.</p>

<p>I also tried a Hennessy hammock. This is an unusual design because everything
hangs from one horizontal line. The sleeping area hangs below this because of
the shape of the material - it is not just a rectangle of cloth. It comes with
a tarp that hangs on the same line as the hammock. The one I tried had an
entry at the bottom - you get in through a hole underneath. The net was not
removable.</p>

<p>I did not like this setup much because it gives very little ventilation and
you can’t see out, because the tarp is so close. It is also inflexible. If
there are no mosquitoes, it is better not to use the net because it increases
the temperature significantly. You can’t take it off with this hammock. With
the DD, you can tie it up out the way, or just turn the hammock upside down
and not deploy the net at all. It is also not good for sitting in. It may be
quicker to deploy though, because it uses the same points for the hammock and
two of the four corners of the tarp.</p>

<p>I was not sure whether I should buy a hammock in Mexico or before I went
there. The Yucatan is know as a hammock producing area. The hammocks made here
are net hammocks, so not mosquito proof, and they do not come with nets. I did
not see any nets for sale either, and suspect it may be impossible to find
one. The Mexican style hammocks can be comfortable, but it depends a lot on
the quality. The cheap ones are pretty bad, but ones made with stretchy
strings can be good.</p>

<p>I think the best option is to buy something like a DD or Hennessy hammock, or
to make one yourself. The Mexican type ones are probably good for relaxing on
a beach, but not for an expedition.</p>

<p>I have not used a hammock in a temperate climate, but a friend has used his DD
for cycle touring in Scotland, and recommends it over a tent here as well. He
likes it because he can hide in a wood where it is harder to find somewhere to
pitch a tent.</p>

<p>If you are going cycling in a tropical area I would recommend you take a
hammock. In a temperate area, it could be a good idea as well.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/10001922436" title="20130929_073504 by River, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3766/10001922436_eb4ca1ddf2_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="20130929_073504" /></a></p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
</feed>
