<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss">

  <title><![CDATA[River MacLeod, MM0HAI: Posts tagged boat]]></title>

  <link href="https://mm0hai.net/blog/tag/boat/index.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://mm0hai.net/"/>
  <updated>2016-11-28T02:35:12+01:00</updated>
  <id>https://mm0hai.net/blog/tag/boat</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[River MacLeod]]></name>
  </author>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[2 Cats 1 Boat]]></title>
    <link href="https://mm0hai.net/blog/2016/09/25/two-cats-one-boat.html"/>
    <updated>2016-09-25T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://mm0hai.net/blog/2016/09/25/two-cats-one-boat</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://c5.staticflickr.com/6/5836/30583122980_5ebe6a8ef3_z.jpg" width="640" height="360" alt="2 Cats 1 Boat - Scampi 30" /></p>

<p>After sailing on other people’s boats for a while, I finally got my own. I’m
planning to live aboard and travel. It seems like a good way to have more
comfort than most ways of travelling - you take your bed, kitchen, etc. with
you - but you are not stuck in one place as you are with a house. For the
moment the boat is on land in Stockholm, but in the Spring we should be ready
to go.</p>

<p>The boat is a Shipman Scampi, better known as Albin Scampi, as Albin also
built them. 30ft, made in Sweden around 40 years ago. Quite light displacement
and meant for racing, but hopefully will serve for cruising. She needs some
work, but overall not a bad deal.</p>

<p>I bought this boat after hitchhiking around Sweden, looking mostly at the Albin
Vega, until Autumn when prices on larger boats like this dropped. I heard
Sweden is a good place to buy a boat, and they certainly do seem cheaper here
than in the UK and probably most of Europe. Swedish boats do not, however,
seem to be well equipped to go to sea, as British ones more often are. I think
this is because they are usually just used around the islands here, so there
is more work to do, like adding anchors, tender, vhf radio!</p>
]]></content>
   <georss:point>59.324140 18.045904</georss:point>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
