<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss">

  <title><![CDATA[River MacLeod, MM0HAI: Posts tagged piratebox]]></title>

  <link href="https://mm0hai.net/blog/tag/piratebox/index.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://mm0hai.net/"/>
  <updated>2018-02-07T17:59:18+00:00</updated>
  <id>https://mm0hai.net/blog/tag/piratebox</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[River MacLeod]]></name>
  </author>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Reïmplementing PirateBox]]></title>
    <link href="https://mm0hai.net/blog/2017/11/01/Re%C3%AFmplementing-PirateBox.html"/>
    <updated>2017-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://mm0hai.net/blog/2017/11/01/Reïmplementing-PirateBox</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After using Piratebox for a while, I decided I could do the same thing in a
way I liked better.</p>

<p>The PirateBox install is rather complicated, and I still don’t understand how
it is all laid out, with various disk image files, scripts in different
places, services started from a piratebox init script, or their own
scripts… Fundamentally what it is doing is pretty simple, so I decided it
would be easier just to reïmplement it myself in a simpler way. Perhaps
unusally for such a project, I was right - it was easy to do and the end
result I like much more - simpler, easier to understand. I don’t want to say
anything bad about the developer of the project - he has other constraints
that may make the system he has make more sense. For example, he is supporting
several platforms including raspberry pi, and has to spend time supporting the
thing too.</p>

<p>To start with, I decided to upgrade to LEDE. LEDE seems to basically be the
latest version of OpenWRT. I don’t know all the details or politics, but my
impression is OpenWRT has stalled and basically you should move to LEDE. There
was a version of this compiled and ready to go for my router, but later I
compiled my own anyway, because I wanted to compile a custom nginx and it was
easy enough to do the whole thing.</p>

<p>So, I started with a plain install of the latest LEDE. I setup an overlay
filesystem on a disk image file on a USB drive, which would also host the
PirateBox files.</p>

<p>Then there is basic network config to do, setup access point, etc. Fairly
standard stuff for LEDE. I did some other stuff to make the system more usable
for me, switched ssh to OpenSSH, installed bash and some other packages I
like.</p>

<p>First design change I made from PirateBox was to use nginx instead of lighttpd
for the main web server. It’s much faster - I really noticed in the page load
time. Also, PirateBox copies header and footer files into every directory,
which is a nasty mess. Instead, I used nginx’s fancy_index module, which does
this in the reasonably expected fashion - specify the header and footers to
include in the config file. I had to compile this module for mips, but it was
not hard and worked fine.</p>

<p>Next thing was to redirect http to the PirateBox page. You can do this just by
intercepting traffic to port 80, or with making your DNS server always return
the IP of the PirateBox whatever is asked for. Just the http redirect works
fine, and avoids messing up DNS for other purposes, so I recommend sticking
with that.</p>

<p>Optionally (TODO for me): Implement RFC 7710 - advertise captive portal login
page with a DHCP option.</p>

<p>I wanted to move away from droopy - it just feels a bit dodgy, so looked into
getting nginx to do as much as possible. There are various ways to upload
files with nginx, but it looks like I would need to do at least a bit of
scripting myself which I couldn’t be bothered with at the moment, so I stuck
to Droopy for now.</p>

<p>I did not include the image board. This is really dodgy looking and I even
noted complaints in the PirateBox forum that it linked to porn. Not to my taste.</p>

<p>The original chat box never worked properly for me - it was very slow. I
decided to try and move to something based on XMPP (Jabber). Prosody was easy
to set up, and to use from normal XMPP clients. Getting a working chat box
though I’ve not sorted out. I tried to use converse.js, and got it working in
the end, but it was so slow as to be unusable, I decided, locking up a browser
on a laptop for long enough to be considered broken. I don’t have a solution
yet. Maybe if no web XMPP client works, something based on IRC could, but
that’s not so good for using on phones.</p>

<p>So, what I ended up with was not as feautureful as the original, but it was
faster, easier to understand and modify, and more “secure”, if such a thing
can be said of a system which allows arbitrary anonymous uploads. I’ve not
checked exactly what or where droopy is going to allow uploads…</p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Pirate Box]]></title>
    <link href="https://mm0hai.net/blog/2017/10/30/PirateBox.html"/>
    <updated>2017-10-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://mm0hai.net/blog/2017/10/30/PirateBox</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img width="50%" class="block-centre" src="/res/2017-10-30-PirateBox/PirateBox-logo.svg" alt="PirateBox logo" /></p>

<p>This year, I have been playing with a <a href="https://piratebox.cc/">Pirate
Box</a>, which I made from an old home router that I flashed with OpenWRT. I
came across this project a while ago, and eventually make one early this
year.</p>

<p>A Pirate Box is basically a file server with a captive portal style web
interface, and an open wifi access point. So, anyone can see the PirateBox
wifi network, connect, and when they try to browse the web they’ll be
redirected to a page where they can upload and download files. Some key points
which make this system notable are that anyone can upload, there is no
authentication, and no logging. ALso, it’s not connected to the internet.</p>

<p>It’s comparable to <a href="https://deaddrops.com/">USB dead drops</a>, but
with wifi. USB dead drops are USB flash drives which are stuck in public
places, like cemented into a wall for example. There is a map of them on the
web.</p>

<p>I was quite excited at the idea of having a PirateBox on my ship. I imagined
running it at anchor, so that other boats and sailors could share things like
charts, local info, pilots, other less useful but entertaining things. The
Pirate box also includes chat, and this could be extended with AIS like info
maybe, so you can see who you are talking to around you.</p>

<p>Anyway, it didn’t really work out. Noöne used it. I can’t be sure it was never
used - remember there is no logging - but I didn’t see any evidence of it. I
have a wifi activity LED on the box, which never did anything exciting. Noöne
uploaded anything either, or commented in the chat box. I have tried running
the box in various likely places - an alternative cafe, a hackerspace which
also has many offices and a pub within range, marinas, anchorages - but never
received any files.</p>

<p>What’s the problem? I think there are several. When the project was conceived
some years ago, people didn’t have mobile data connections. I guess people
generally are not looking for wifi as much as they used to, especially in
anchorages where they may just assume there is none, and not even try.</p>

<p>If they do see it, maybe some people are put off by the name. Of course, it
should attract others, so not convinced this is a big problem.</p>

<p>After connecting, there could be problems from various modern operating
systems interfering. Mobile phones at least, do this like marking a network as
having “No internet”, opening limited captive portal login pages, etc. There
is an assumption by these systems that the only useful network is the
internet, making it harder to run an independent network, however useful it
may be.</p>

<p>The proliferation of HTTPS also makes things harder. Captive portals generally
rely on intercepting an HTTP connection, but as almost all sites people go to
now are encrypted, they can’t make themselves known unless an HTTP site is
requested, so people will just see failed connections to google.com, etc.</p>

<p>There is RFC 7710, which proposes a method of advertising the captive portal
login page using a DHCP option, but I don’t know if anyone is actually using
this.</p>

<p>Maybe it would help to name the network something like “Go to piratebox.lan”.</p>

<p>In the end, I got bored of it, and turned it into a private file / media
server. Even this is handy on the boat, and actually it has been extended for
other functions too as a general boat router.</p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
</feed>
