<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss">

  <title><![CDATA[Alistair MacLeod, MM0HAI: Posts tagged trees]]></title>

  <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/tag/trees/index.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mm0hai.net/"/>
  <updated>2013-08-21T13:30:42-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/tag/trees</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alistair N. MacLeod]]></name>
  </author>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Forest of London]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/08/14/The-Forest-of-London.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/08/14/The-Forest-of-London.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2012-08-14T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/08/14/The-Forest-of-London</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The first time I visited London on my own I went for a walk around the
City. Apart from various novelties like seeing the most people evar wearing
suits in one place and paying 7 GPB for a sandwich I was interested in the
buildings.</p>

<p>London is an organic city. It was not planned, it doesn't have blocks. It has
evolved and grown. Like trees in a rainforest, the buildings have become
taller. Evolution requires old organisms to die, leaving space for new
generations. It is the same with buildings.</p>

<p>I especially like the <a
href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lingam">Gherkin</a>, <a
href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/30_St_Mary_Axe">30 St Mary Annexe</a>. This
was built on the site of a previous building which was destroyed by a
bomb. Without this <a
href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shiva">destruction</a>, there would be no
new building.</p>

<p>Some forests are like this too. Pyriscent seeds only germinate when
burnt. Seedlings need the space and light created by the fire.</p>

<blockquote>
<p>
"Many plant species in naturally fire-affected environments require fire to
germinate, to establish, or to reproduce, or all three. Fire suppression not
only eliminates these species, but also the animals that depend upon them."
</p>
<p>
-- <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fire_ecology">Wikipedia, Fire Ecology</a>
</p>
</blockquote>


<p>London is a forest.</p>

<!--
I am concerned that some interpretation of the <a
href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2006/11/part/1/crossheading/encouragement-etc-of-terrorism">Terrorism
Act 2006</a> might make writing this post punishable by 7 years in
prison. Therefore, I will add that I am not trying to encourage you to blow up
buildings or set forests on fire. It is probably not a good idea to set fire
to forests, but when it happens naturally or when old buildings fall apart,
there may be some benefits. Really, I'm not trying to comment on whether these
things are good or bad, I'm just noting how they are.
-->

]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ways of Living]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2011/07/26/Living.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2011/07/26/Living.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2011-07-26T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2011/07/26/Living</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There are ways to live other than in a conventional house.</p>

<p><img src="http://farm7.static.flickr.com/6012/5975477373_d3de359f7b_z.jpg"
width="640" height="480" alt="Bilston Glen site"></p>

<p>On Sunday, I went to visit a community in Bilston Glen. Here is a forest with
tree houses and ground houses. They are made almost entirely of scrap - parts
from skips, wood, rope, glass, planks, carpet, sofas, mattresses, oil drums,
gas cylinders.</p>

<p>There is a small hydroelectric plant in the river - it can charge mobile
phones, which have signal here, and suchlike.</p>

<p>Food is also available from skips. People can live happily from what others
throw away. Perhaps better in many cases, if someone could only afford lower
quality food. The several large fridges were full when I visited.</p>

<p>Are people happy here? I don't know in general, but one girl I spoke to seemed
fairly indifferent - it just seemed to be normal. Later, a friend of mine
moved here and liked it.</p>

<p>There are a mixture of people who live here. Some have resided for years,
others stay for months or days. Some are young and some are old. All will tend
to smell of campfire.</p>

<p>I could live in a boat. Move when I want. Work anywhere. Or a tent, hammock,
bivvy bag. I thought a hammock in scaffolding could be a good place to sleep
if one had to in a town, to be near an office for example.</p>

<p>Is homelessness really bad? It is hard to separate it from poverty and
addiction because that seems to be the cause of so much of it but it is not
necessarily bad. What is homelessness anyway? Are you homeless if you live in
an hotel?  What if you are an explorer with tent? What is a home? Can a bike
be a home? Is it somewhere comfortable? Is it a place or a feeling? Is it
necessary?</p>

<p>I left the woods and soon after IKEA offered me "my dream home". It came with
a contract binding me to money, a bank account, an address, a job, and a place
to keep the bloody thing - a sofa.</p>

<p><img src="http://farm7.static.flickr.com/6148/5976040942_e35f5e01f4_z.jpg"
width="640" height="480" alt="IKEA, near treehouses"></p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
</feed>
