<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss">

  <title><![CDATA[River MacLeod, MM0HAI: Posts tagged guatemala]]></title>

  <link href="https://mm0hai.net/blog/tag/guatemala/index.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://mm0hai.net/"/>
  <updated>2016-11-11T20:35:55+01:00</updated>
  <id>https://mm0hai.net/blog/tag/guatemala</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[River MacLeod]]></name>
  </author>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Guatemala]]></title>
    <link href="https://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/05/04/Guatemala.html"/>
    <updated>2013-05-04T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/05/04/Guatemala</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I don’t have a lot to say about this country, because I wasn’t there for very
long. I travelled through the North of Peten, and then a short distance in the
south east to the border with Honduras.</p>

<p>In general, it seemed to be very much like Mexico. There was no sudden change
after crossing the border. I enjoyed cycling from Flores to Belize, I think
partly because it was more colourful. Physically - houses and fences are
painted, the hammocks are maybe more colourful, and also there seemed to be a
bit more variety. In Mexico, everything was the same. The businesses, the
products available were usually exactly the same as each other. I don’t think
it was as bad here.</p>

<p>One noticable change is the guns. There are armed guards, usually with
shotguns, nearly everywhere. That includes ice cream shops. I was amused by
one gun shop called “Magnum” just beside an ice cream shop.</p>

<p>There are various places I would have liked to go but they were a bit too out
of the way for me just now. The hot waterfalls near Rio Dulce, and the river
and caves at Semuc Champey certainly sound worth visiting. I also skipped Lago
Atitlan and Antigua. I think Antigua is much like San Cristobal de las Casas,
though.</p>
]]></content>
   <georss:point>16.914282 -89.917603</georss:point>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
