<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss">

  <title><![CDATA[Alistair MacLeod, MM0HAI: Posts tagged mexico]]></title>

  <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/tag/mexico/index.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mm0hai.net/"/>
  <updated>2013-06-01T15:18:31-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/tag/mexico</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alistair N. MacLeod]]></name>
  </author>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Babylon by Bus]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/03/18/Babylon-by-Bus.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/03/18/Babylon-by-Bus.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2013-03-18T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/03/18/Babylon-by-Bus</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When it came time to leave the Oaxaca Rainbow Gathering, we were offered a
lift up the road. This turned out to be in an orange VW Bus called Gail, with
a figurehead of a ginger woman painted on the spare wheel.</p>

<p>We were given a joining briefing. She runs on gas, oil and love. Normally she
has a driver, driver's assistant, navigator, and band who sit in the back. She
was certainly well used, and I can see that she really must be held together
with love, as the string may not otherwise have been strong enough. I can see
how you can love a bus like this. My dreads kept getting caught in something
on the roof. Maybe she wanted a lock of my hair. :)</p>

<p>As we went up the sandy road through the coconut palms a man told a travel
horror story, over the considerable noise of the engine.</p>

<p>We made it to the main road, and after saying hello to some people on another
bus, returned to Babylon on a bus where we had to pay a fare.</p>

<p>We arrived at Salina Cruz, and I went a bit mad. At the Rainbow I was eating
healthily, vegan food, no sugar or caffeine. Now there were bright lights,
food and smells. I thought I smelt popcorn. It was esquites - corn. I bought a
cup. Then I wanted to try everything I saw - ice cream, burgers, tortas,
coffee. I ate churros next, which are similar to donuts but shaped like a star
prism. I also drank coffee and ate a cheese torta which was recommended by a
local. I felt very strange and didn't stop talking until asleep on the bus
home to San Cristobal.</p>

<p>I would like to travel by hippie bus one day.</p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Wind and Fire]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/03/17/Wind-and-Fire.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/03/17/Wind-and-Fire.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2013-03-17T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/03/17/Wind-and-Fire</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I could feel something today. Some energy in the air, like something was going
to happen. Everyone could feel it. The wind was building and shaking the
trees. It had been building for days.</p>

<p>The wind drove us to eat in a huddle in the camp, sensibly breaking the
protocol of eating in the exposed, sandblasted, main circle. It felt like a
tribe coming together in the face of adversity. It was. The wind blew all
night and bounced my hammock.</p>

<p>The next morning, I broke up with my girlfriend. We were sitting in camp. As I
was talking, something hit me in the back. A girl sat up in my hammock. My now
ex-gf left to make her own camp, and I talked to my friend.</p>

<p>She was sleeping there, she told me, on account of being very tired from the
previous night's activity. She had sex with a guy she liked, and the girl he
was with. She felt very free now. Free from jealousy, ego and social
limits. It sounds like it was a very liberating experience, and a cleansing
from the past. Past problems blown away with the wind.</p>

<p>Later, I was dwelling on the past. As I was thinking about what went wrong
with the gf, ruminating, a pan whacked me on the head. Stop it! Be present
now! The wind had blown it from the tree.</p>

<p>That night, there was an orange glow in the distance. With the wind coming
from there, it was not long before it brought the fire to the camp. Everyone
was driven out. Anything left behind was burnt. Many people lost things,
attachments maybe, and many moved on that morning.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8543751136/" title="DSCF3623 by
mm0hai, on Flickr"><img
src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8522/8543751136_b140416fd0_z.jpg"
width="640" height="480" alt="DSCF3623"></a></p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[San Cristobal de las Casas]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/01/11/San-Cristobal-de-las-Casas.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/01/11/San-Cristobal-de-las-Casas.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2013-01-11T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/01/11/San-Cristobal-de-las-Casas</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img
src="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/9/9a/Flag_of_the_EZLN.svg"
width="640" alt="EZLN Flag"/></p>

<p>The streets smell of roasting coffee, grown by the coöps in the surrounding
hills. I also smell chocolate and bread from the panaderias. There are punks
on bikes - real bikes, not rusting Mexican style ones. Restaurants advertise
vegetarian and vegan food. Colourful gnomes and greyed hippies sit in the
streets.</p>

<p>There are anarchist and squatting symbols painted on the walls. If you wear an
anarchist patch in Edinburgh it is ignored. Here, the town was actually
captured by rebels. I don't think it would be a good idea to cycle past the
army base they built down the road on my own with Zapatista colours. There are
armed police and soldiers around, which is a nice reminder of what is
possible. The government is wary.</p>

<p>There are at least two places here devoted to permaculture, with a vegan
community. Until recently there was a community bike workshop.</p>

<p>I wandered into the yard of some casa, following the sound of a woman singing
reggae. There was a guy contact juggling, and silks hanging from a frame. The
smoke was the pleasant smelling kind - not tobacco. A menu on the wall listed
hummus and verduras.</p>

<p>I wandered on aimlessly, and reached a cafe. Now I'm drinking tea that tastes
of the earth where it came from.</p>

<p>Mexico is sick and makes me feel sick. The world is sick. San Cristobal is a
hill station for the recovery of humanity.</p>
]]></content>
   <georss:point>16.7385777 -92.6332806</georss:point>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[PEMEX]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/01/07/PEMEX.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/01/07/PEMEX.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2013-01-07T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/01/07/PEMEX</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8387837666/" title="PEMEX"><img
src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8361/8387837666_ed618aa2b2_z.jpg"
width="640" height="480" alt="PEMEX Station"></a></p>

<p>Before I really started cycling here in Mexico, a couple of people told me
they camped and hammocked at PEMEX, the only brand of petrol station I have
seen so far in Mexico. I thought that sounded a bit crazy but that is because
I had only toured in Europe before.</p>

<p>In Europe, I found I could camp almost anywhere by the side of the road. There
might be a forest, or a field, a picnic spot, a public park or even a
campsite. Here the roads I have seen so far are lined by ditches and fences
unbroken for miles. The slopes to the ditches are often very steep, the
ditches quite wide and full of water and then there is a barbed wire fence on
the other side. Getting the bike across this would be very difficult. Getting
self over would be possible, but would involve getting wet, muddy, and
possibly injured. There are venomous snakes around here, ticks and maybe
leeches. It generally is not something I want to do.</p>

<p>Last night I found a small space between the road and the water. I stopped
there because I saw some flatter ground. I was not the first to notice it
though - there was an old camp fire, and lots of rubbish. I moved down from
the road a bit for cover from sight. I thought it would be better not to be
seen because that was my only defence against robbers. Down here though was
where people had been using as a toilet and rubbish dump.</p>

<p>In the morning I had to get the bike back up the slope, which was not
easy. Then I spent probably spent half an hour stopping and trying to work out
what was making a scraping noise as the wheels turned. Eventually I found a
piece of wire stuck in the back tyre was scraping on the inside of the
mudgaurd. This and the sticks that jammed in the gears are more reasons to
avoid these sites.</p>

<p>If you want a flat site with short grass (to avoid snakes) it seems like the
only option usually is to ask at someones house to camp in the garden. This
can be quite successful - I did this the night before and was also given a
meal. Some people at the Rainbow told me they had done this and it happened to
be the occasion of the Granny's 101st birthday. A pig was slaughtered for them
and they were basically forced to stay for two days eating and drinking.</p>

<p>The other option though is a petrol station. Now that I have seen one it makes
sense. I'm camping now on a large area of flat, short grass, about 20 meters
from the hardstanding. I can see my bike locked near the pumps, lit and under
cover from rain. There is a toilet, sink for washing, food and water right
outside. There is also a useful amount of light but not so much as to stop
sleep.</p>

<p>In Europe, I would avoid a petrol station as noisy and possibly dangerous and
camp somewhere quiet. I also think of them as expensive and of course
supporting an oil based system. But now I look out of the tent and the PEMEX
sign is like a marker of an oasis. This and the glowing traffic cone landing
lights, are beautiful.</p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Finally Moving]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/01/05/Finally-Moving.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/01/05/Finally-Moving.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2013-01-05T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/01/05/Finally-Moving</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I spent over two weeks at the Rainbow Gathering, then a couple of days in
Palenque getting my solar rack fixed. Before that I had been in hostels
working on computer related stuff, so apart from the road to the Rainbow I had
cycled very little. I was starting to get frustrated and feeling trapped by my
gear, admin and thoughts.</p>

<p>The bike was so far mostly a burden and extra expense on busses. It had already
needed repair work. I had almost forgotten what it was for, and felt I could
not move. I didn't know whether to go on to Merida, then across to Chichen
Itza and Tulum as planned, to head straight over to Chetumal and Belize, or to
go to San Cristobal de las Casas, which I had heard was a bike and vegan
friendly town. I was thinking and not moving.</p>

<p>Suddenly I realised I was right beside a freedom machine. I resolved I was
going to cycle today no matter what. Without a map, without doing a better job
of the solar rack or testing it, without any more gear, and without a well
considered decision about where to go. I just had to move.</p>

<p>I started cycling and it worked. I felt better as soon as I was rolling.</p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Intimate Shitting]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/23/Intimite-Shitting.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/23/Intimite-Shitting.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2012-12-23T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/23/Intimite-Shitting</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<!--- date approximate -->


<p>Someone told me one special Rainbow experience I had to have was sharing a
shit pit. She said if you haven't been elbow to elbow with someone on the next
trench then you don't know them, or something like that.</p>

<p>Ten minutes later I was using the shit pit and someone came along and asked if
he could join me, so I said yes. Of everyone this could have been, he was a
nurse, and apart, therefore, from being an expert on shit, he seemed to have a
particular interest.</p>

<p>Unprovoked, he explained his ideas. He thought illness could be a beautiful
thing because an inability to do things yourself such as wiping your bum means
you must become closer to other people. He thought illnesses were for a
reason, and must teach you something or have some benefit.</p>

<p>Another nurse I spoke to said she hated wiping bums. She quit to go
travelling.</p>

<p>I'm afraid I didn't take a photo for this post.</p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Cancun]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/13/Cancun.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/13/Cancun.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2012-12-13T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/13/Cancun</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Cancun is a tourist resort. It's made of hotels. It doesn't seem quite as bad
as Maspalomas - there are some areas where people live, but it's still not
somewhere I would like to spend much time. It was hard to find any food that
would not make me feel sick. Maybe there are good parts but I felt I had to
get out of there before I went mad.</p>

<p>I took the bus, as crazyguyonabike blogs told me the only routes out were big
boring roads. Cycling to the bus was quite exciting - mostly busses and
collectivos on the dual carriageway. Large roundabouts and weird junctions I
had not seen before. The general idea seems to be to drive on the right but
overtaking is done on whichever side is convenient.</p>

<p>Putting the bike on the bus was trivial. Did not even need to remove
panniers. Far superior service to busses in the UK.</p>

<p>My bike felt like a bus. Total weight of bike and gear was 55kg when I left
Manchester. The ADO bus, when I was on it, rolled along with a similar
feeling.</p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[First day in Mexico]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/11/Mexico-First-Day.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/11/Mexico-First-Day.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2012-12-11T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/11/Mexico-First-Day</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Police truck with armed man standing in back. I can't imagine how this is a
useful strategy from a military perspective - he is far too exposed and would
be shot before he could do anything. I guess it is primarily security theatre
- an attempt to intimidate the people into doing what they are told.</p>

<p>Tried to find vegan food, settled for vegetarian. Ordered peas, got meat -
pork I think. Ate it - think throwing away would be adding serious insult to
injury.</p>

<p>Still hot at night - not like Canaries where temp drops with the sun.  Very
humid - outside like a warm sauna. Later noted condensation on the <em>outside</em>
of bus windows.</p>

<p>Could not find fruit - wee shops pretty much just sell crisps and fizzy
drinks. Contraband fruit taken at airport. Probably a sign of a troublesome
free thinker.</p>

<p>In Germany drinking tea means are ill, here you must be a hippie.</p>

<p>The Simpsons speak Spanish in Mexico.  Almost all TV dubbed. Probably when
English limited here, cf. Netherlands.</p>

<p>Being forced to remember / learn Spanish already. Maybe should take a course.
Many menu words not in Spanish dictionary. Mexican only terms maybe? Should
have bought Mexican Spanish book saw at airport.</p>

<p>Not seen many Mexicans yet.</p>

<p>I am hearing accents I have only heard before on American T.V. shows. I really
like the (American) Indian accent from them, which a hotel receptionist
has. It is reassuring, as if his knowledge about the location of Walmart is
something passed through generations of tribes.</p>

<p>First shop I found was an electronics one. I mean one which actually had
multimeters and components, not washing machines. They had isopropanol and
thermal paste. I wanted to do that job on Thinkpad before I left. Ha. You can
always buy stuff later.</p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
</feed>
