<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss">

  <title><![CDATA[Alistair MacLeod, MM0HAI: Posts tagged elsalvador]]></title>

  <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/tag/elsalvador/index.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mm0hai.net/"/>
  <updated>2013-09-29T15:14:39-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/tag/elsalvador</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alistair N. MacLeod]]></name>
  </author>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[El Salvador]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/06/18/El-Salvador.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/06/18/El-Salvador.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2013-06-18T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/06/18/El-Salvador</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/9120315746/" title="El Salvador
Honduras Border, by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img
src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7407/9120315746_21ef809110_z.jpg"
width="640" height="480" alt="DSCF4937"></a></p>

<p>My route through Honduras did not leave very good options for visiting El
Salvador. To ride from one end of the country to the other, I would have to
go back north through Honduras. This route would be through the mountains -
hard work. It had also started raining now, and I didn't feel like
it. However, it was not far to the border, so I thought I might as well just
make a short side trip to tick the country.</p>

<p>I decided to head for La Union, a town on the cost, from which I could maybe
explore some islands or get a boat to Nicaragua.</p>

<p>As I was riding down the road, I realised that this must be the one Mark
Beaumont skipped because he thought it was too dangerous. He took a car from
El Salvador to Nicaragua. Then I remembered that he said something like, "this
isn't a place to hang around in", about what must have been La Union.</p>

<p>I got through the rather dodgy border without incident. All borders around
here are dodgy but at least this one had windows - you didn't need to go
inside, where they usually insist you leave your bike out of site. I was
trying to get to an hotel in La Union - I knew there was one from another
blog. I wasn't going to make it before dark though. I asked some police at a
checkpoint and they said to go to the police station at the junction on the
road down to La Union. I did so, and they said they would need to check with
the boss. In the mean time, they gave me a lift into town to get some
pupusas. They said it was not a safe place, and not a good idea to by cycling
around here even during the day. While I was waiting for my pupusas, they were
standing watch from across the road, one of them with his hand on his
holstered pistol. I spoke to a guy when I was waiting. He also said he would
not recommend cycling around here, or in Honduras, but further south was safer
in Nicaragua, and Costa Rica.</p>

<p>After we got back, someone put a mattress in the front office for me. I slept
adequately. Also, I had a wash the some way they did - by pouring buckets of
water over myself. I think it is probably more effective than a shower - much
greater water volume is achieved quickly.</p>

<p>I still hadn't decided where to go next. The options were try and get a boat
to Nicaragua, or Honduras, cycle up the coast and maybe find some nice
beaches, or go back the way I came. I was put off cycling around here by the
warnings, and one man said the beaches near here were not very nice anyway. To
get a boat I would need to go into town and search for it, which might not
actually exist, or be too expensive.</p>

<p>The next day I decided to go back the way I came. I hitched a lift part of the
way, to the junction where this time I took the road for Nicaragua.</p>

<p>I should add, to avoid giving a totally negative impression of the country,
that most cyclist come this way, and they seem to like the coast and
beaches. Apparently it is a great place for surfing.</p>
]]></content>
   <georss:point>13.357627 -87.914057</georss:point>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
