<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss">

  <title><![CDATA[River MacLeod, MM0HAI: Posts tagged canarias]]></title>

  <link href="https://mm0hai.net/blog/tag/canarias/index.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://mm0hai.net/"/>
  <updated>2017-10-31T21:18:18+01:00</updated>
  <id>https://mm0hai.net/blog/tag/canarias</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[River MacLeod]]></name>
  </author>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Mi cueva!]]></title>
    <link href="https://mm0hai.net/blog/2016/12/20/es-mi-cueva.html"/>
    <updated>2016-12-20T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>https://mm0hai.net/blog/2016/12/20/es-mi-cueva</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I’m starting to really feel Proudhon.</p>

<p>When I was last here, we shared a cave between around ten of us. If a stranger
had come, we would have undoubtedly invited them to join us round the fire. I
returned to the cave this night, and found that the lock on the bars that were
installed when the policia threw us out had been broken, and replaced. I stood
and contemplated my history here, until presently I heard the gate
open. “Buenas”, “Hola”, I said. “Vaya vaya, … mi cueva! …”. He wanted me
out the barranco. He even claimed the neighbouring caves, the view maybe…</p>

<p>Previously, on this Canarian trip, I visited La Tomatera. The shared meals
round the one table were gone. The kitchen was bare. One man ate a takeaway
sandwich. Instead of a welcome note, the fridge said “Kill all hippies”.  A
room had a lock. I suspect most of the soft furnishings, the comfort, had gone
behind it.</p>

<p>I feel like the island has lost its soul. The stage is still here but the
actors gone. Of course it was the people who made what we had here
before. It’s probably stupid to say the island has changed. It’s been here
forever compared to us. The cave I’m writing in now was occupied before the
Spanish came. The bars will break soon enough.</p>

<p>Property is theft.</p>

<p><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/6/5472/31737151766_201d797963_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="Cave Bear" /></p>
]]></content>
   <georss:point>28.06 -15.51</georss:point>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Caves, not concrete]]></title>
    <link href="https://mm0hai.net/blog/2016/12/18/caves-not-allowed.html"/>
    <updated>2016-12-18T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>https://mm0hai.net/blog/2016/12/18/caves-not-allowed</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://c8.staticflickr.com/1/580/31658253711_c1fd5cf681_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="Coto Privado de Caza Sign" /></p>

<p>Last time en Canarias, I discovered some caves and slept in them a while. I
was excited at the novelty, and to discover how good caves are for
living. They stay warm at night because the rock holds the heat of the
day. They surround you with warmth and look after you. It is like mother
nature saying “I love you, here is a home I made for you”.</p>

<p>The government says no. No entry. Private hunting estate. Only killing allowed
here, not living. Go and pay someone to make you a concrete box.</p>

<p>Now I’m angry.</p>
]]></content>
   <georss:point>27.85 -15.68</georss:point>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to use Las Palmas de Gran Canaria City Bikes "ByBike"]]></title>
    <link href="https://mm0hai.net/blog/2016/12/15/How-to-register-for-Las-Palmas-city-bikes-bybike.html"/>
    <updated>2016-12-15T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>https://mm0hai.net/blog/2016/12/15/How-to-register-for-Las-Palmas-city-bikes-bybike</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Las Palmas de Gran Canaria has a municipal bike system, but registering for it
is rather complicated and especially difficult if you don’t live here and
understand Spanish, so I decide to write a guide, as I have just done it. The
system is available to non-residents.</p>

<h2 id="what-you-get">What you get</h2>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>You can pick up a bike at any point and return it to any other.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>You can keep the bike out for up to one hour.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>After returning, you need to wait 15 minutes to use one again.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>You can borrow a bike up to five times per day.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>Rental is done with a smartcard or a phone app.</p>

<h2 id="what-it-costs">What it Costs</h2>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>1.50 EUR for the smart card, which also can be used for busses. Usage is
free.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Possibly various fees if you are late returning the bike or lose the bike,
don’t report them as damaged…</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<h2 id="how-to-register">How to Register</h2>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Fill in this
<a href="http://www.bybikelpa.com/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=83&amp;Itemid=85&amp;lang=en">form</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>You will receive two emails. Ignore the first.  In the second email, click
the link “HAGA CLICK AQUÍ”.  This takes you to a form which asks for your
Spanish tax number. You don’t need one. What you actually should enter here
is your passport or ID document number that you put in the last form. Follow
the process for verifying phone number. (You must receive a text message.)</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Wait for 24 to 48 hours, then go to one of the registration offices with
your passport or ID. A few offices are listed in the emails you are sent,
but I actually went to San Telmo bus station, which was not listed but
worked.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Buy a BONOGUAGUA smart card for 1.50 EUR. It is yellow. At San Telmo, you
can do this at the ticket office with the glass window, in a corner. I think
you can also do it at a machine.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Go to the ByBike / Bus office. At San Telmo, this is the larger office you
can walk into, to the right of the glass ticket office booth. Give them your
ID, yellow card, and say you want to register for ByBike. “Quiero
registrarme para ByBike”. They will look you up on the computer. If you
waited long enough since the last step, they will validate it and that
should be other. Otherwise it might still be “pendiente” - come back later.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>You should now be able to use the bikes!</p>

<h2 id="using-the-bikes">Using the Bikes</h2>

<p>You can use the card, or a mobile app. The app shows where stations are, and
how many bikes and spaces are at each place. You can also take a bike out
without the card at most stations.</p>

<p>For the app (optional):</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Download the app:
<a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.usualbike.bybikeLPA">Android</a>
or <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/es/app/bybike-lpa/id975121273?mt=8">iOS</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Login with username and password that you will receive in a third email,
after your ID is validated at the office.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Take a screenshot of the map while you still have internet, because the app
does not work at all offline.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<h2 id="hints">Hints</h2>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>The whole system is badly designed and maintained. Check the bike thoroughly
before you try to take it.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>The card readers almost don’t work at all. Try holding the card at 90
degrees to the way indicated.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Count the number of usages in a day, because if you try a sixth loan, it
will work, but then block you for a month! Days end at midnight.</p>
  </li>
</ul>
]]></content>
   <georss:point>28.127803 -15.436013</georss:point>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
