<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss">

  <title><![CDATA[Alistair MacLeod, MM0HAI: Posts tagged psychedelic]]></title>

  <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/tag/psychedelic/index.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mm0hai.net/"/>
  <updated>2013-08-21T13:32:24-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/tag/psychedelic</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alistair N. MacLeod]]></name>
  </author>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Mother Aya, Aunt Jurema]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/08/05/Mother-Aya.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/08/05/Mother-Aya.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2013-08-05T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/08/05/Mother-Aya</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/9497148473/" title="Magic Potions
from the Rainforest by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img
src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7439/9497148473_c779f76ed7_z.jpg"
width="640" height="480" alt="Magic Potions from the Rainforest"></a></p>

<p>Burning bush? Yes, you can talk with plants.</p>

<p>It tasted like black treacle, but sweeter, and with a hint of marmite.</p>

<p>I had read "DMT: The Spirit Molecule", and wondered if I would experience any
of the common patterns. Maybe I would meet alien entities, or find myself in a
nursery. Maybe I would learn the secrets of the universe. What is its true
nature? What is it all about?</p>

<p>I started to feel the effect of the Ayahuasca in my body after the first dose,
but did not notice any mental effect until shortly after the second, which was
double the size and washed down with a glass of the bitter, astringent,
Jurema. I am wary of mixing things, especially if I've not had them before,
but these plants both contain the same chemically active ingredient, DMT, and
spiritually I guess they are sisters so I thought they would be able to get
along.</p>

<p>At first all was black, but then colour noise appeared - red, green and blue
dots, always switching on and off. Then these formed into lines, which made up
constantly changing shapes. They were square and triangular and zig
zag. Seemed quite binary, angular, computer generated. The lines were in
rainbow colours, the rainbows moved and sparkled. It was very beautiful. With
open eyes, the picture seem quantised into simpler geometrical shapes. Leaves
and gaps between them angular, and they moved like an animation with
insufficient framerate. The images were very beautiful, and if I would have
noticed pain, my face would probably have been hurting from smiling.</p>

<p>I enjoyed this a lot, but I didn't just want pretty pictures. I wanted to
learn something. I said this and asked, "what can you show me?". I didn't get
a direct answer - no voice or character speaking to me - but the answer became
obvious. You are a baby. You know nothing about how the world works. You're
not ready for that sort of thing. Here - play with the pretty sparklies. I
realised I knew nothing, and I might as well enjoy it. When I accepted it, I
realised that being a baby is wonderful. You don't need to do anything or
worry about anything. You are looked after. Like any mother, Mother Aya just
wants her babies to healthy and happy.</p>

<p>I thought I was just happy because of the beauty, but then I realised it was
not just beauty, it was love. I thought I was loving the pictures, but then I
realised that was ridiculous - I am just a tiny spec - almost nothing - how
could I produce so much love? It was clear that this was all there - an
immense field of love - is this what everything is made of? I could only bathe
in it.</p>

<p>Ayahuasca is what is politely called purgative, or cleansing. I was sick
once. When I crawled out of the circle to vomit I felt like a snake. It was
worse for the boy next to me though, who had diarrhoea which at one point
splatted on my face. At first I tried to work out some way in which that had
not actually just happened, but my attempt to deny reality was clearly not
going to work.</p>

<p>There was a lesson though. I had been thinking earlier about how a baby has an
easy life, but it does things like shitting and pissing everywhere. Now I
experienced that this is not always enjoyable for everyone else who has to be
around it. While it is good and right to be a baby when you have to, when you
can you should grow up. I saw birds hatching and flying and making new nests.</p>

<p>I think it is clear that humans as a race are babies. How can we be told the
secrets of the universe when we can't even look after ourselves? We are
shitting all over this planet and can't even feed ourselves without making
such a mess that it will kill us all and everything else that lives
here. Maybe in a few million years, if we survive that long, we will will be
ready to understand.</p>

<p>I asked someone to heat water for me so I could wash my hair and face. Someone
else fed me chocolate. I could enjoy being looked after a little more, but
tomorrow I must grow up.</p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Utila]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/06/07/Utila.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/06/07/Utila.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2013-06-07T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/06/07/Utila</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>DMT</strong>: Dimethyltriptamine, a psychedelic.</p>

<blockquote><p>"subjective effects can range from short-lived milder psychedelic states to
powerful immersive experiences; these are often described as a total loss of
connection to conventional reality with the encounter of ineffable
spiritual/alien realms." -- wikipedia</p></blockquote>

<p><strong>DMT</strong>: Divemaster in Training.</p>

<blockquote><p>People who accompany you in an immersive experience of encounters with
strange creatures in an alien realm. -- me</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8908111363/" title="DSCF4793 by
mm0hai, on Flickr"><img
src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3682/8908111363_a979f91e41_z.jpg"
width="640" height="480" alt="DSCF4793"></a></p>

<p>Underwater, perception changes. Everything is 33% bigger, sound is different
and faster, gravity can be countered allowing you to fly, and everything
tastes of salt. The trees are pink, and the birds are very strange.</p>

<p>I'm on the boat at the end of my holiday trip to Utila. I feel a bit sad, but
I don't think I'll miss the place. I didn't think I could stand the dorm room
for more than a couple of days, but then I realised I stayed for twelve.</p>

<p>I learned to scuba dive here. It's not something I had ever thought about
before, but since the Yucatan, people were talking about it. You can dive in
the Cenotes there - gateways to the Mayan underworld, and there is also the
Mesoamerican reef that runs all down the cost from Mexico to Honduras. I
learnt that Utila is the cheapest place in the world to take diving courses,
so I thought I might as well try it.</p>

<p>I did some snorkelling first, off Caye Caulker, Belize. This was a good
introduction, because once you get used to a mask and breathing through a
tube, it doesn't really make much difference to how it feels on your face
whether the tube is connected to the atmosphere or a tank. The reef was more
alive with fish and animals here than in Utila, too.</p>

<p>I took the PADI Open Water course, the entry level qualification that lets you
dive with a buddy. (Solo diving is highly discouraged by most people, and
should only be done with redundant equipment and extra training.) I decided to
do the Advanced course too, after some thought, because I wanted to do some
diving after the training, and the course didn't cost too much more than just
paying for some dives. It allows diving in more places too, and deeper.</p>

<p>I particularly liked a wall dive we did. It is a unique feeling to be able to
dive off a cliff and not fall. Swimming along the top of the coral, then
turning 90 degrees down, still swimming. The world rotates and you are free of
up and down.</p>

<p>We also visited a wreck, and did a night dive. The scene of everyone
descending into a circle on the bottom with beams of light from torches
resembled something from a sci fi film; maybe a space ship landing, or a team
going to recover a crashed ship.</p>

<p>I also found that there are some good people in Honduras, who don't just try
to steal from you, like the taxi drivers and the person who tried to take my
camera out its bag in La Ceiba. There are still the people coming into what
was my home for a while to try and sell me weed or failing that crack, and
people stealing from the kitchen, but there is the occasional pretty
engineering nerd and nyancat fan around too.</p>

<p>Actually I think diving is a bit of a geeky hobby. I met a couple of
engineers, a physics teacher, a biologist / bird watcher, and a web
designer. It's not really a sport, being much like a casual stroll would be on
land. It probably appeals to geeks because of the equipment and the required
knowledge of physics, chemistry and biology. Looking at fish is the underwater
equivalent of bird watching, too.</p>

<p>I'm on my way back to the mainland now anyway. I think I'll make a brief
foray into the jungle, then rejoin my bike and return to the cycling life. I
forgot about cycling after a day or two here - it was a distant memory of a
past life, but it is resurfacing now. I'm not sure I want to be working away
in the sun and dust again, rather than floating weightless in the sea, but it
seems to be what I'm doing.</p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
</feed>
