<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss">

  <title><![CDATA[River MacLeod, MM0HAI: Posts tagged indieweb]]></title>

  <link href="https://mm0hai.net/blog/tag/indieweb/index.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://mm0hai.net/"/>
  <updated>2018-01-14T19:05:55+01:00</updated>
  <id>https://mm0hai.net/blog/tag/indieweb</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[River MacLeod]]></name>
  </author>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[IndieWebCamp Edinburgh]]></title>
    <link href="https://mm0hai.net/blog/2015/07/26/Indie-Web-Camp-Edinburgh.html"/>
    <updated>2015-07-26T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://mm0hai.net/blog/2015/07/26/Indie-Web-Camp-Edinburgh</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img width="640" src="https://indieweb.org/images/8/84/2015-07-25_Edinburgh.jpg" alt="IndieWebCamp Edinburgh group photo" /></p>

<p>At the weekend, I attended an <a href="https://indieweb.org/2015/Edinburgh">IndieWebCamp in Edinburgh</a>.</p>

<p>IndieWeb basically seems to be the idea that people should have their own
websites - what we used to call homepages - instead of using things like
Facebook, Twitter, etc. It is some ideas of how to do things, and some minimal
standards to allow for sites to interoperate.</p>

<p>One of the most important ideas is that your url and site are you
identity. You should own your url and content. There is a system to allow you
to authenticate to other sites as your domain name. Other standards allow, for
example, comments to be posted on other sites, syndication of posts (read
sites with a feed reader like RSS), and many others.</p>

<p>One thing not yet developed on the IndieWeb is a way to have friends-only or
other private type posts. We had some discussions about how to do this. We
also had some talk about static sites. I think most IndieWeb sites are
dynamically generated, but mine and certainly some others are static.</p>

<p>My site is generated with Jekyll, and then served as static pages. This has
some limitations, but not as many as you might think, and it has many
advantages regarding security and efficiency of hosting.</p>

<p>I also made some basic improvements to the indiewebyness of my site this
weekend, fixing <a href="http://microformats.org/">microformats</a>, and other
general work on the site.</p>

<p>I would certainly recommend going to one of these camps to anyone interested
in building or running a website themselves, which they can have control over.</p>
]]></content>
   <georss:point>55.935481 -3.180439</georss:point>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
