<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Alistair MacLeod, MM0HAI: Posts tagged cyclewho]]></title>

  <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/tag/cyclewho/index.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mm0hai.net/"/>
  <updated>2013-03-11T22:45:29-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/tag/cyclewho</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alistair N. MacLeod]]></name>
  </author>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[<span title="My hobby: asking for Buddhist temples in German. If they don't understand then I try Chinese">gibt es einen buddhistischen Tempel in der Nähe?</span>]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/03/07/Buddhist.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/03/07/Buddhist.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2013-03-07T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/03/07/Buddhist</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8549721861/" title="San Cristobal NKT Buddhist Centre by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8391/8549721861_29da425226_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="San Cristobal NKT Buddhist Centre"></a></p>

<p>I noticed this Buddhist centre when I first came to San Cristobal. I am now
living very close to it so there was no excuse not to have a look. They have a
"guided meditation" each day at 10am. On Thursday I went to it.</p>

<p>The main room or hall of the centre had a shrine at the end, with cushions on
the floor at the front and some seats in rows behind them. The shrine had
golden Buddhas and Bodhisattvas, 3 sets of 7 water bowls, a chocolate bar at
the right side, and various other things. On the wall behind the central
Buddha was a portrait of Kelsang Gyatso. Another, lager, portrait of him sat
in front of the Buddha. The way it was displayed reminded me of pictures of
Saddam Hussein in Iraq.</p>

<p>The session was not what I was expecting. The type of meditation I have
encountered before is about presence, silently concentrating on the senses and
body. This was mostly chanting with a few shorter periods of silence to
contemplate what was said.</p>

<p>It was surprisingly like a christian church service. There was the equivalent
of a hymn book for the chants or songs, and it followed a set program from the
book. The main difference was there were some periods of silence to
contemplate. I'm afraid it also felt rather like church - something you go to
because you are required to for some reason but you don't actually feel
anything or get the point. The order of service if you can call it that was
from a book by the founder of this type of Buddhism. I read the book
afterwards in a couple of hours and then researched it more on the web.</p>

<p>I discovered that this place was of the New Kadampa Tradition (NKT), founded
by Geshe Kelsang Gyatso in England in 1991 and now based in the Lake
District. This form of Buddhism seems to be somewhat controversial, and has
some aspects I do not like and which are somewhat suggestive of a cult. It
seems people are taught only to read the books by Kelsang Gyatso, and I
noticed in the centre all the books were by him.</p>

<p>The only book that did not have his name on the cover was by the Western
Shugden Society, which seems to be mostly run by Kadampa Buddhists. The
worship of Shugden seems to be a controversial issue. The Dalai Lama banned
it, but Kelsang Gyatso supported it.</p>

<p>I also found a story about a monk being financially exploited, and there are
websites for "recoverers". I don't know if these indicate systematic problems,
but the fact that there is an official <a
href="http://www.newkadampatruth.org">site</a> which tries to defend against
various accusations does not look good.</p>

<h2>The Teachings</h2>

<p>In any case, it does not matter what the organisation is like unless the
teachings are good. Kelsang Gyatso seems to be distinguished by designing a
clearly organised 21 step meditation plan, or lamrim in Tibetan, which I read
in one of his books.</p>

<p>Many of the steps seem like a good idea, but there were a few I really didn't
like, which I will point out below. This post may seem rather negative because
of this, and admittedly I was looking for problems. I think this is important
though, because I do not want to spend a lot of time on something if there are
basic problems with it. I don't know how much of this is specific to NKT and
how much is common to other Buddhist traditions.</p>

<h3>Fear</h3>

<p>The first point is entitled "Our precious human life" but in reality it is
designed to instil fear!</p>

<blockquote><p>"This feeling of fear is the object of our meditation. We then hold this
without forgetting it; our mind should remain on this feeling of fear
single-pointedly for as long as possible."</p></blockquote>

<p>The fear he is talking about is that of a lower rebirth. I should explain
samsara - the idea that we are trapped in a continuous cycle of death and
rebirth. This is common to many religions. Birth can be in any of six realms -
God, demi-god, human, animal, hungry ghost, and hell. Buddhas have escaped
from this cycle, and the idea is that by following the lamrim, you can achieve
this.</p>

<p>Christian Heaven and Hell seems like a special case of samsara where the
number of births is exactly two, or possibly three if purgatory counts as
one. Churches use fear of hell as a method of controlling people. It seems
here that fear of lower rebirth is being used to convince people to follow this
path.</p>

<p>I don't like this idea of instilling fear because it is not something
inherently good and it can be abused to control people. Is it really necessary
to invent something for people to fear? Are there not enough problems readily
apparent that we can fix? I can certainly see things in my life which I could
improve with some Buddhist teachings without having to fear hell. Rather than
creating fear, then running to Buddha and your guru ("taking refuge"), don't
unnecessarily create fear to start with. You can still learn, reduce existing
fear, and love.</p>

<p>All of this assumes that samsara exists. I tried searching for evidence of
this, or even where this idea came from, but I didn't find anything convincing
enough to base my life on it. Perhaps this is the religious part of Buddhism -
something you are just required to believe without evidence.</p>

<p>I found this on <a href="http://typing-sound.livejournal.com/63084.html">someones livejournal</a></p>

<blockquote><p>"Getting back to the NKT, I would advise anyone reading this to stay well
  away from it. If you don't and they get you inside, you will find yourself
  locked in beliefs and fear. You will be overloaded with practices and
  commitments prematurely, and then you will be afraid not to do them for fear
  of hell. Once you're deeply submerged in the NKT, it is very difficult to
  get out again, because in a way you get brainwashed."</p></blockquote>

<h3>Death</h3>

<p>Gyatso would also have you meditate on death.</p>

<blockquote><p>"I shall definitely die. There is no way to prevent my body from finally
decaying."</p></blockquote>

<p>This seems negative and may cause fear. Some people argue it is not even true
that you must die. Maybe it won't if you don't believe it, or if you become
more than a normal human. Again there is a more positive alternative. Instead
of saying I must work hard because I will die soon, think, I will work hard to
improve my life now. This works whether you believe in rebirth or not.</p>

<h3>Gurus</h3>

<p>He claims that it is necessary to have a spiritual teacher - it is the only
way. I won't say that it is not helpful to have a teacher, but I object to the
idea that it is absolutely necessary. Where did these teachers get their
knowledge from? It must be discoverable. The Buddha did not have a Dharma
teacher. Yes, he probably had several teachers he learned from, but he moved
between them and thought for himself to develop his ideas. He did not swear
loyalty to one guru who told him never to read the books of someone else.</p>

<p>I read that some schools practice guru yoga or worship, basically treating a
guru as a god. This doesn't seem like a good idea to me at all.</p>

<p>They also seem a bit obsessed about the lineage of teachers - students
becoming teachers and continuing the line. I think they see this line leading
back to Buddha as something to establish their legitimacy.</p>

<p>From the same livejournal post quoted above:</p>

<blockquote><p>"I did learn a valuable lesson from it all, which was not to believe
  anything that didn't depend upon experience, otherwise you get trapped in
  fear. And I learned to be self-reliant, not reliant on some Guru without
  thinking for myself."</p></blockquote>

<h3>Absolute statements</h3>

<p>The book is filled with definite statements which are clearly not true. For
example, that following this lamrim is the only way to give your life
meaning. It is obvious that I can do many valuable things without practising
Buddhism. The requirement for a guru is another example.</p>

<blockquote><p>"We need to practise Buddha’s teachings because there is no other real method
to solve human problems." - Geshe Kelsang Gyatso, "Modern Buddhism".</p></blockquote>

<p>Obviously this is not true either.</p>

<h3>Positive Teachings</h3>

<p>On the positive side, the rest of the steps of this lamrim may be good ideas,
although I have not read about all of them in enough detail. They include
loving everyone equally, believing in the kindness and love of others,
avoiding attachment, compassion and cherishing others rather than
yourself.</p>

<h2>Money</h2>

<p>They seem to be partly a way to sell "Buddhist Holidays". The retreats they
are selling in Mexico are about 100 GBP a day. For comparison I pay about 75
GBP a month in rent for rooms here.</p>

<p>The lama said we were invited to a lesson. I went. Afterwards I was asked for
money, "only if I had it", but they asked several times. I didn't want to pay
for something I thought was free.</p>

<h2>Conclusions</h2>

<p>Unless there is good evidence for some pain after death it does not make sense
change your behaviour because of this. Focus on fixing real problems you have
now.</p>

<p>One needs to be very careful in choosing gurus.</p>

<p>Whatever the nature of the teachings or philosophy, there is a great risk of
corruption and exploitation when a large organisation is created around
it. Good people can be corrupted. The power a guru can have over his students
can also attract people who intend to abuse that power.</p>

<p>There are a great variety of practices and beliefs within Buddhism. You need
to research the specific teachings of different teachers rather than rely on a
simple label like Buddhist or Kadampa.</p>

<p>I should research other forms of Buddhism to see if there is one with less
religion, power and fear, and more useful lessons for living this life.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[San Cristobal de las Casas]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/01/11/San-Cristobal-de-las-Casas.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/01/11/San-Cristobal-de-las-Casas.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2013-01-11T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/01/11/San-Cristobal-de-las-Casas</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img
src="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/9/9a/Flag_of_the_EZLN.svg"
width="640" alt="EZLN Flag"/></p>

<p>The streets smell of roasting coffee, grown by the coöps in the surrounding
hills. I also smell chocolate and bread from the panaderias. There are punks
on bikes - real bikes, not rusting Mexican style ones. Restaurants advertise
vegetarian and vegan food. Colourful gnomes and greyed hippies sit in the
streets.</p>

<p>There are anarchist and squatting symbols painted on the walls. If you wear an
anarchist patch in Edinburgh it is ignored. Here, the town was actually
captured by rebels. I don't think it would be a good idea to cycle past the
army base they built down the road on my own with Zapatista colours. There are
armed police and soldiers around, which is a nice reminder of what is
possible. The government is wary.</p>

<p>There are at least two places here devoted to permaculture, with a vegan
community. Until recently there was a community bike workshop.</p>

<p>I wandered into the yard of some casa, following the sound of a woman singing
reggae. There was a guy contact juggling, and silks hanging from a frame. The
smoke was the pleasant smelling kind - not tobacco. A menu on the wall listed
hummus and verduras.</p>

<p>I wandered on aimlessly, and reached a cafe. Now I'm drinking tea that tastes
of the earth where it came from.</p>

<p>Mexico is sick and makes me feel sick. The world is sick. San Cristobal is a
hill station for the recovery of humanity.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Getting into the Bathtub]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/01/09/Getting-into-the-Bathtub.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/01/09/Getting-into-the-Bathtub.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2013-01-09T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/01/09/Getting-into-the-Bathtub</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>My touring bike and gear had either very little or in some cases no testing at
all before leaving. I had replaced most of the bike, including rebuilding the
wheels with new rims, cones and ball bearings. The panniers were all brand
new. The ærobars and bar ends were new. The solar panel mounting was tested
only lightly around Edinburgh. Now I was on tour.</p>

<p>In engineering, there is something called a <a
href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bathtub_curve">bathtub curve</a>. This
shows the general shape of the probability of failures of many systems over
time. A new system might fail from manufacturing defects and an old one from
wearing out. In between, the chance of failure is lower. This curve looks like
a bathtub.</p>

<p><img
src="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/7/78/Bathtub_curve.svg"
width="640" alt="Bathtub curve" ></p>

<p>There was so much new on the bike that I knew I was not in the bath yet, and
was almost expecting things to fail. They did.</p>

<p>First my solar panel rack broke. I was worried it might on the Rainbow Road -
an awful, bumpy, rough track. 30km or so did it. The front tube broke where it
touched the carrier rack. The point at the rear where the tube was over bent,
that I was concerned about before I left, also broke. I needed to get this
fixed before I could cycle further. It did keep the panel on the bike like
this, but without fixing it would probably totally fail soon. Getting it
repaired is a story for another post.</p>

<p>The other problem I had was the front wheel started to make a nasty noise. I
found that something in the hub was catching when it rotated. When I left, the
balls were new and the cones were recycled but only had one very minor pit in
the track. The cups are built into the hub and had some wear but did not look
too bad. I found someone at the Rainbow Gathering who had cone spanners and we
had a look inside. The cones still looked good and the grease was clean. We
didn't take the balls out though or would inevitably have lost them in the
forest. He did not know what was wrong either, but took out one ball from each
side, so the hub now had 9 per side. I am sure it had 10 before I rebuilt it,
but the problem has now stopped, so I'm leaving it like that.</p>

<p>I found my headset was loose. I didn't use a headset press when I fitted it -
only a hammer - so maybe the bumpy road pushed the races in further. This was
easily tightened by borrowing a large adjustable spanner from a local bike
shop. I don't think they had a proper headset spanner so I couldn't hold the
bearing for exact adjustment as I tightened the locknut. It's probably
slightly overtight now but I decided to leave it as good enough for a change
rather than spending all day tweaking. It was a cheap headset anyway so I'll
probably have to replace it soon.</p>

<p>I've also been moving my saddle. I've mostly been using the ærobars and so I
have a different riding position. The saddle is a Brooks I've had for some
time, but it has not been used on a tour before. It's breaking in much faster
than at home, probably because of the heat and humidity.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[PEMEX]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/01/07/PEMEX.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/01/07/PEMEX.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2013-01-07T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/01/07/PEMEX</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8387837666/" title="PEMEX"><img
src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8361/8387837666_ed618aa2b2_z.jpg"
width="640" height="480" alt="PEMEX Station"></a></p>

<p>Before I really started cycling here in Mexico, a couple of people told me
they camped and hammocked at PEMEX, the only brand of petrol station I have
seen so far in Mexico. I thought that sounded a bit crazy but that is because
I had only toured in Europe before.</p>

<p>In Europe, I found I could camp almost anywhere by the side of the road. There
might be a forest, or a field, a picnic spot, a public park or even a
campsite. Here the roads I have seen so far are lined by ditches and fences
unbroken for miles. The slopes to the ditches are often very steep, the
ditches quite wide and full of water and then there is a barbed wire fence on
the other side. Getting the bike across this would be very difficult. Getting
self over would be possible, but would involve getting wet, muddy, and
possibly injured. There are venomous snakes around here, ticks and maybe
leeches. It generally is not something I want to do.</p>

<p>Last night I found a small space between the road and the water. I stopped
there because I saw some flatter ground. I was not the first to notice it
though - there was an old camp fire, and lots of rubbish. I moved down from
the road a bit for cover from sight. I thought it would be better not to be
seen because that was my only defence against robbers. Down here though was
where people had been using as a toilet and rubbish dump.</p>

<p>In the morning I had to get the bike back up the slope, which was not
easy. Then I spent probably spent half an hour stopping and trying to work out
what was making a scraping noise as the wheels turned. Eventually I found a
piece of wire stuck in the back tyre was scraping on the inside of the
mudgaurd. This and the sticks that jammed in the gears are more reasons to
avoid these sites.</p>

<p>If you want a flat site with short grass (to avoid snakes) it seems like the
only option usually is to ask at someones house to camp in the garden. This
can be quite successful - I did this the night before and was also given a
meal. Some people at the Rainbow told me they had done this and it happened to
be the occasion of the Granny's 101st birthday. A pig was slaughtered for them
and they were basically forced to stay for two days eating and drinking.</p>

<p>The other option though is a petrol station. Now that I have seen one it makes
sense. I'm camping now on a large area of flat, short grass, about 20 meters
from the hardstanding. I can see my bike locked near the pumps, lit and under
cover from rain. There is a toilet, sink for washing, food and water right
outside. There is also a useful amount of light but not so much as to stop
sleep.</p>

<p>In Europe, I would avoid a petrol station as noisy and possibly dangerous and
camp somewhere quiet. I also think of them as expensive and of course
supporting an oil based system. But now I look out of the tent and the PEMEX
sign is like a marker of an oasis. This and the glowing traffic cone landing
lights, are beautiful.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Bike is Important]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/01/05/The-Bike-is-Important.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/01/05/The-Bike-is-Important.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2013-01-05T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/01/05/The-Bike-is-Important</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I don't think you understand how important this is. This is not a toy or for
going to the shops. This is for tens of thousands of miles of dirt roads,
jungles, deserts and mountains. This is my home for years. For the majority
of people I meet for the next few years, this is all they will remember of
me. You did this like you had no time for better, then spent the rest of the
day standing around doing nothing.</p>

<p>This morning I started to cry. I put on Runrig, "Road and the River", which
triggered it, although I almost felt like crying when I saw your work
yesterday. I should have insisted you do it better. I didn't negotiate the
price down because I wanted you to be interested enough in it to do a good
job. Apparently that didn't work. The only reason I let you continue and paid
you is because I couldn't move without it. Something that might last a few
hundred miles would at least let me escape this place now. The one thing that
was good about this work was that it was done by 3pm the day it started.</p>

<p>Now I am sitting right next to a freedom machine but still feel trapped. I
don't know if I can cycle because of illness. If I do I'll probably get wet
when my tent leaks again. If I want better gear I will need to wait for it to
be delivered here - I think there is no chance of buying something that is not
rubbish here. That means waiting somewhere - again I am trapped. All the time
I can't even eat anything that is not poison, so it's not surprising I have
been ill for nearly two weeks. The current cold that is, not diarrhoea and
vomiting immediately preceding. And it will probably take days to choose things
and order them on the internet, and most of the days will be wasted trying to
find working wifi.</p>

<p>I am thinking too much. I can get out of an hotel room in the morning without
thinking - I have done this before. I am going to cycle, kit be dammed. I am
going to ride my bike today whether I have a map and a waterproof tent or not.</p>

<p>Now I feel better. I'm going to have breakfast.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Finally Moving]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/01/05/Finally-Moving.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/01/05/Finally-Moving.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2013-01-05T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/01/05/Finally-Moving</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I spent over two weeks at the Rainbow Gathering, then a couple of days in
Palenque getting my solar rack fixed. Before that I had been in hostels
working on computer related stuff, so apart from the road to the Rainbow I had
cycled very little. I was starting to get frustrated and feeling trapped by my
gear, admin and thoughts.</p>

<p>The bike was so far mostly a burden and extra expense on busses. It had already
needed repair work. I had almost forgotten what it was for, and felt I could
not move. I didn't know whether to go on to Merida, then across to Chichen
Itza and Tulum as planned, to head straight over to Chetumal and Belize, or to
go to San Cristobal de las Casas, which I had heard was a bike and vegan
friendly town. I was thinking and not moving.</p>

<p>Suddenly I realised I was right beside a freedom machine. I resolved I was
going to cycle today no matter what. Without a map, without doing a better job
of the solar rack or testing it, without any more gear, and without a well
considered decision about where to go. I just had to move.</p>

<p>I started cycling and it worked. I felt better as soon as I was rolling.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Intimate Shitting]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/23/Intimite-Shitting.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/23/Intimite-Shitting.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2012-12-23T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/23/Intimite-Shitting</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<!--- date approximate -->


<p>Someone told me one special Rainbow experience I had to have was sharing a
shit pit. She said if you haven't been elbow to elbow with someone on the next
trench then you don't know them, or something like that.</p>

<p>Ten minutes later I was using the shit pit and someone came along and asked if
he could join me, so I said yes. Of everyone this could have been, he was a
nurse, and apart, therefore, from being an expert on shit, he seemed to have a
particular interest.</p>

<p>Unprovoked, he explained his ideas. He thought illness could be a beautiful
thing because an inability to do things yourself such as wiping your bum means
you must become closer to other people. He thought illnesses were for a
reason, and must teach you something or have some benefit.</p>

<p>Another nurse I spoke to said she hated wiping bums. She quit to go
travelling.</p>

<p>I'm afraid I didn't take a photo for this post.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Gods]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/22/Gods.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/22/Gods.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2012-12-22T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/22/Gods</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I don't believe in any gods, and think religion is dangerous and very
harmful. The Rainbow Gathering had a good selection of them though. There were
temples for Hare Krishna, Shiva, and even a few Jesuses and Marys around. This
flippant attitude changed though, at the End of the World.</p>

<p>When everything is wet, it feels like it will never stop raining, you are
vomiting and the jungle is trying to eat you, Gods seem to come back. I like
sacred songs whatever I think of the content. In the dark I prayed to the rain
to stop, and apologised to Krishna for singing but not believing.</p>

<p>A Christian minister once told me, when questioned, that praying is something
people do because it is all they can do. Find a real way to control the
environment and prayer is useless.</p>

<p>Gods aren't disappearing directly because of science taking over as a method
of understanding the world, they are disappearing because there is less
suffering. Modern life gives more comfort and less disease. With control of
your environment, waterproof roofs, heating, and factory farming, there is no
desperation, and no need for gods of rain and corn.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[First Test of Solar Charger]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/14/First-Test-of-Solar-Charger.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/14/First-Test-of-Solar-Charger.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2012-12-14T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/14/First-Test-of-Solar-Charger</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I designed and built a charger for Thinkpad batteries before I left, but there
was not enough sun in Scotland to test it properly. Today in Tulum I tried it
for real for the first time.</p>

<p>Tropical mid-day sun was sufficient. It charged the battery for a while. When
I tried a battery that was at a higher voltage, it did not charge it as
designed. The voltage cutoff was lower than I had set at home, but basically
it seems to work. I did not leave it long enough to see it cutoff when full
though. I also would like to measure the power supplied so I know how long
charging will let the computer run.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8272408443/" title="First test of
solar charger by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img
src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8352/8272408443_0390543aa4_z.jpg"
width="640" height="480" alt="First test of solar charger"></a></p>

<p>The charger is not mounted on the bike yet, so it's just sitting on top while
I measure voltages.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Cancun]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/13/Cancun.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/13/Cancun.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2012-12-13T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/13/Cancun</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Cancun is a tourist resort. It's made of hotels. It doesn't seem quite as bad
as Maspalomas - there are some areas where people live, but it's still not
somewhere I would like to spend much time. It was hard to find any food that
would not make me feel sick. Maybe there are good parts but I felt I had to
get out of there before I went mad.</p>

<p>I took the bus, as crazyguyonabike blogs told me the only routes out were big
boring roads. Cycling to the bus was quite exciting - mostly busses and
collectivos on the dual carriageway. Large roundabouts and weird junctions I
had not seen before. The general idea seems to be to drive on the right but
overtaking is done on whichever side is convenient.</p>

<p>Putting the bike on the bus was trivial. Did not even need to remove
panniers. Far superior service to busses in the UK.</p>

<p>My bike felt like a bus. Total weight of bike and gear was 55kg when I left
Manchester. The ADO bus, when I was on it, rolled along with a similar
feeling.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Fruit is not Allowed]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/12/Fruit-is-not-allowed.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/12/Fruit-is-not-allowed.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2012-12-12T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/12/Fruit-is-not-allowed</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>"Fruit is not allowed", the customs officer said dissaprovingly. This seems
true not only of imports, but generally in Cancun. There are plenty of small
shops but they pretty much just sell crisps and sugary drinks. I ate mostly
sugar and felt sick.</p>

<p>I quickly gave up on finding vegan food and tried for vegetarian. I ordered
some quesadillas after carefull study of the menu and dictionary, but still
got meat. I ate it anyway. I think not to would be adding insult to injury. I
wouldn't be very impressed if someone killed me for food and then decided to
throw me in the bin instead. I felt sick.</p>

<p>Tortilla vegetariano for breakfast, served with refried beans. Interesting,
but eggs and cheese. Felt a bit sick.</p>

<p>Then I found Walmart. Here fruit is allowed - it is quite overwhelming. It's
stacked high - it would crush you if it fell over - and is all perfect. Every
apple is shiny and without blemish, and lit by green light. They must be
genetically engineered, irradiated, and coated with insectiside. Nevertheless,
I imagine the scale of the place and quantity of food could make a hungy
person cry.</p>

<p>The last time I tried to use a McDonalds drive through (in Penrith (England))
they wouldn't let me. Here they did. McDonalds was a theme on my last cycle tour
I wanted to avoid this time, but it seem to have happened already. I wanted
food without having to leave my bike. I didn't want to try the street vendors
because I have plenty of things to do for the moment without being sick. I
tried to order a vegeburger but they didn't understand. It was not the
langugae, I tried Spanish and English, they did not understand the concept of
not eating meat. I ordered chicken and felt nothing. It tasted of nothing, was
probably mostly breadcrumbs. I need to get out of here.</p>

<p>My water bottle holder does not work well for coffee cups. There is another
gadget to rig up.</p>

<p>In Nigeria if there is no meat in a meal people will be unimpressed and think
you are poor. I suspect poor countries go through a phase of everyone wanting
meat as a sign of affluence. Maybe they will grow out of it.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[First day in Mexico]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/11/Mexico-First-Day.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/11/Mexico-First-Day.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2012-12-11T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/11/Mexico-First-Day</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Police truck with armed man standing in back. I can't imagine how this is a
useful strategy from a military perspective - he is far too exposed and would
be shot before he could do anything. I guess it is primarily security theatre
- an attempt to intimidate the people into doing what they are told.</p>

<p>Tried to find vegan food, settled for vegetarian. Ordered peas, got meat -
pork I think. Ate it - think throwing away would be adding serious insult to
injury.</p>

<p>Still hot at night - not like Canaries where temp drops with the sun.  Very
humid - outside like a warm sauna. Later noted condensation on the <em>outside</em>
of bus windows.</p>

<p>Could not find fruit - wee shops pretty much just sell crisps and fizzy
drinks. Contraband fruit taken at airport. Probably a sign of a troublesome
free thinker.</p>

<p>In Germany drinking tea means are ill, here you must be a hippie.</p>

<p>The Simpsons speak Spanish in Mexico.  Almost all TV dubbed. Probably when
English limited here, cf. Netherlands.</p>

<p>Being forced to remember / learn Spanish already. Maybe should take a course.
Many menu words not in Spanish dictionary. Mexican only terms maybe? Should
have bought Mexican Spanish book saw at airport.</p>

<p>Not seen many Mexicans yet.</p>

<p>I am hearing accents I have only heard before on American T.V. shows. I really
like the (American) Indian accent from them, which a hotel receptionist
has. It is reassuring, as if his knowledge about the location of Walmart is
something passed through generations of tribes.</p>

<p>First shop I found was an electronics one. I mean one which actually had
multimeters and components, not washing machines. They had isopropanol and
thermal paste. I wanted to do that job on Thinkpad before I left. Ha. You can
always buy stuff later.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Leaving Edinburgh]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/10/Leaving-Edinburgh-for-Mexico.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/10/Leaving-Edinburgh-for-Mexico.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2012-12-10T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/10/Leaving-Edinburgh-for-Mexico</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After far too long in Edinburgh I am finally moving. I decided that even if I
was not really ready yet I had to leave because the weather was getting quite
unpleasant in Scotland and if I did not just decide to leave would I ever
really be ready anyway? I had booked a flight to Cancun, Mexico about two
weeks ago but was still not ready. The photos below I took myself just before
cycling to the train station. I hadn't finished packing when it came time to
leave to catch the train so I had to throw things in without time to decide
what I really needed. It was the first time I had ridden the bike loaded with
the new panniers and all gear.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8340847482/" title="Leaving by
mm0hai, on Flickr"><img
src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8072/8340847482_4f02f7752a_z.jpg"
width="480" height="640" alt="Leaving"></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8340848528/" title="Leaving by
mm0hai, on Flickr"><img
src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8498/8340848528_82c8c559b5_z.jpg"
width="640" height="480" alt="Leaving"></a></p>

<p>The handling with front panniers is very different. It felt like I had a flat
tyre, I think because of the weight compressing the tyre and giving more
friction on the ground. I cycled slowly and hoped nothing was going to break.</p>

<p>I got to the platform just as the train was about to leave. Someone told me I
would not make it but I ran to the far end where bikes go. The box for my
solar panel fell off as I ran but I did not have time to pick it up. Someone
picked it up for me though and threw it on the train - it turned out to be
Jannette who had come to see me off. :)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Cycle Who]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/10/Cycle-Who.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/10/Cycle-Who.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2012-12-10T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/10/Cycle-Who</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I am cycling from Mexico to Patagonia, the southern most part of South
America. I have fitted the bike with a solar panel, and am adding more
electronic gadgets as I travel. I started my trip on 10th of December 2012 and
have no plans about when it will finish. This is an introduction to what I am
doing and why.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8384962554/" title="Leaving Edinburgh by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8214/8384962554_1461cea29d_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="Leaving Edinburgh"></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8272408443/" title="First test of solar charger by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8352/8272408443_0390543aa4_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="First test of solar charger"></a></p>

<h2>Exploring Lifestyles</h2>

<p>There is a standard life pattern that where I'm people are expected to
follow. School, university, job. Buy house and car. Work most of
life. Retire. Die. Is this the best way to be happy? I'm pretty sure it's not.</p>

<p>Some questions I would like to answer:</p>

<ul>
<li>Do you need a house?</li>
<li>Do you need to stay in one place?</li>
<li>What are good forms of transport for a nomadic life?</li>
<li>What makes me happy. What could make everyone happy?</li>
<li>What is needed to allow more or even most people to be nomadic? What could be
done to make travellers lives easier? For example, I think more community
workshops, for bikes, electronics and other things, would help.</li>
<li>How can people achieve freedom from:</li>
<li>Work</li>
<li>Location</li>
<li>Oil</li>
<li>Everything, as far as possible</li>
</ul>


<h2>Promoting</h2>

<ul>
<li>Independent, sustainable travel.</li>
<li>The bicycle as a practical means of transport - not just a toy.</li>
<li>Alternative energy sources.</li>
<li>Thought, and rational behaviour. I would like more people to think about how
they are living their lives - analyse them. Is what you are doing really what
is best for you, or are you doing what you have been told to do by society,
even though it's making you miserable? How many people do you see smiling in
the morning on their way to work? It doesn't need to be like that.</li>
</ul>


<h2>Where</h2>

<p>After failing to get a lift across the Atlantic in a yacht last year, I still
wanted to go to Patagonia. In December I wanted to escape the Scottish winter
to somewhere warm. I knew there was going to be a Rainbow Gathering in
Palenque, Mexico, near a Mayan ruin site, around the time of the end of the
cycle of the Mayan Calendar. This, the climate and a very cheap flight to
Cancun came together to give me the start point of Palenque, at the End of the
World. Now I am heading down to another end.</p>

<p>I don't suppose the exact location really matters though - it is probably most
important that it is just somewhere different from what I already know.</p>

<h2>Why</h2>

<p>I wanted to travel - actually I felt I had to. When I went travelling in the
Canary Islands I missed my bike too much - walking around can be very
tedious. So I decided to travel by bicycle.</p>

<p>I'm looking for happiness. I think that is ultimately what it is all
about. Therefore, I'm exploring different ways of living, and different
places, to see what could make me happy and the world a better place.</p>

<h2>What can you Contribute?</h2>

<p>I think I can inspire people and help them to be happier. I suspect most
people have ideas about how to have a better life but they just don't do
it. Hopefully I can show that something apparently difficult, like cycling a
long way, is actually easily achievable, so more people will do what they know
they want to anyway.</p>

<p>Maybe I can learn things about happiness that I can pass on. Rather than
providing some fixed solution though, which is not likely to work for anyone
but me, getting people to think and improve their situation rather than
accept what is given would be an excellent result.</p>

<p>Happiness and love are contagious.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Making a Solar Panel Mount for a Bike]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/10/09/Building-the-Solar-Mounting.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/10/09/Building-the-Solar-Mounting.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2012-10-09T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/10/09/Building-the-Solar-Mounting</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I had chosen to use a 15W, monocrystaline panel mounted under glass in a metal
frame. It was made by ET Solar and bought on ebay for 33 GBP. This seems like
a good panel, but it weighs 2kg and measures 450 x 299 x 35 mm. I had to find
a way to attach it to my bike.</p>

<p>I considered putting it at the front, but the back seemed to be the easiest
and best place. In placing it I wanted to avoid shading from me or any radio
antennas as much as possible, and it was very important to try and design to
my principle of minimising faff.</p>

<p>I decided I needed to mount it above the rear rack somehow. Getting it higher
also has the advantage of getting more sun if I am in the way at the time.</p>

<h1>Ideas</h1>

<h2>Bungees</h2>

<p>The simplest way to mount it was to bungee it on top of the other gear on the
rear rack - my tent and roll mat. This was very easy to do, kept the weight
low - so reducing forces from putting at at the end of a lever higher up, and
it was well cushioned from shock by the gear. However, the problem with this
setup is that it makes it harder to get at my tent and to fix and remove and
other gear. One think I remember really hating when touring before is the time
spent mucking around trying packing and unpacking things. I wanted to get the
panel out the way.</p>

<h2>Custom Metal frame</h2>

<p>A rack could be built in metal, as an addition to the existing luggage racks,
or a custom rack for panniers and solar panel could be built.</p>

<h2>Seat Post Rack</h2>

<p>I looked at rear racks that attach to the seat post - this would give an
additional rack to the conventional one I had fitted. This would add even more
weight though, and they did not go very high, so there would not be much space
between the racks. I also wanted to save money on buying things, but given the
time spent it turned out this was not a valid reason.</p>

<h2>Fibreglass / Composite Luggage storage</h2>

<p>The idea is to build a custom structure that would serve as luggage storage
and solar mount. This would remove the need for panniers. It could also
incorporate spaces for electronics and batteries - for example giving an easily
accessible slot for changing batteries.</p>

<p>One way I've seen to do this that looks very good is a cardboard core glass
reinforced plastic structure. This can be easily built and hacked to any
shape. This was the technique used by Steve Roberts for a similar project.</p>

<p><a href="http://microship.com/resources/cardboard-core-composites.html">Cardboard Core Composites</a></p>

<p><a
href="http://www.solarpoweredbike.com/2008/04/solar-bike-faq-what-is-solar-panel-for.html">Another
fibreglass method</a> was used for a solar bike project:</p>

<p>I think the idea for this was:</p>

<ol>
<li>Build with cardboard.</li>
<li>Fill with expanding foam.</li>
<li>Remove cardboard.</li>
<li>Fibreglass over.</li>
</ol>


<p>So it doesn't end up as a composite with the cardboard core as with the other
method.</p>

<h1>Build / Test</h1>

<p>I decided to make a metal frame myself. This would put the panel where I
wanted it, and it should be possible to make it much lighter than a seat post
rack. Fibreglass looked like it could give a very nice structure, but it would
also be messy to work with and I didn't have anywhere I could do that work. It
would also be expensive and I suspect very time consuming.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/sets/72157632529416559/"><img
src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8515/8384167611_3eb618f479_z.jpg"
width="640" height="480" alt="101_0663"></a></p>

<p>The final design. More detailed photos are on <a
href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/sets/72157632529416559/">flickr</a>.</p>

<p>I had never made anything like this before and didn't know anything about
working metal. I didn't even know where to buy it. One day though I found what
I think might have been a bike rack for a car dumped beside a bin. I recovered
the smaller tubes and started working out what I could do with them.</p>

<p>The design I ended up with was mostly determined by the material I had
available. I used aluminium tube, which seemed like a good choice because it
was light and probably strong enough.</p>

<p>The most difficult part was bending the tubes. Bending a tube by hand can
cause it to collapse. I researched online and read that filling tubes with
sand first would work. I did this, but one of the bends still flattened out to
the point I was concerned it might break. It survived a little testing round
Edinburgh though so I kept it.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8385254986/" title="I was concerned about these bends, particularly on the left."><img
src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8351/8385254986_5cb5afc812_m.jpg"
width="240" height="180" alt="101_0665"></a></p>

<p>The tubes I attached to the bike at the front by screwing onto the rack
mounting points, and at the back with Jubilee clips (hose clamps) padded with
inner tube. The panel is attached to the rack with p-clips, which are horrible
to work with because they are so difficult to bend into the right shape. It
worked though.</p>

<p>It worked until an awful road in Mexico. Update to follow...</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
