<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss">

  <title><![CDATA[River MacLeod, MM0HAI: Posts tagged cyclewho]]></title>

  <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/tag/cyclewho/index.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mm0hai.net/"/>
  <updated>2014-04-11T01:48:02+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/tag/cyclewho</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[River MacLeod]]></name>
  </author>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Cycles Closing in Colombia]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/10/12/Cycles-Closing-Colombia.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/10/12/Cycles-Closing-Colombia.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2013-10-12T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/10/12/Cycles-Closing-Colombia</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I keep finding myself talking about things which happened in the Canary
Islands. It's at least partly because many things started there, and now they
are coming to some completion.</p>

<p>I went to the Canaries to try and hitch a lift on a boat to South America. I
didn't manage that, but nearly two years later, I arrived in Colombia on a
sailing catamaran.</p>

<p>When I was in La Tomatera, Las Palmas de Gran Canaria, I learned to make
macramé, and started to decorate my computer power cable. On the boat to
Colombia, I finished it. About half an hour after completion, the cable
failed. It held out just long enough to allow me to complete it.</p>

<p>I also made a bracelet, which I have worn permanently since then. Today, I
gave it away to a stranger I met on the metro in Medellín, Colombia. I really
don't know why. I didn't know her name, and do not expect to see her again. I
said she could have it if she could get it off. The knot untied.</p>

<p>Now I think where that bracelet had been - so many places. Beaches, mountains,
cities, forests. Up to about 35,000 feet, and down to 30 meters under the
sea. Boats, trains, cars, planes, and of course the bike. Three continents,
and two oceans, and too many islands to remember. Many beds and hammocks, of
which most mine. But this is all past. I shouldn't be dwelling on it. I am
here now.</p>

<p>In Las Palmas, I learned to make dreadlocks and had one made for me. In Costa
Rica, I made one for someone.</p>

<p>In Costa Rica also, I ate fruit given to us, the rainbow caravan, by market
sellers. Today, in Colombia, I bought some bananas and gave them to a beggar
who told me she was hungry, and whom I saw foraging unsuccessfully near the
river, where there are some banana plants.</p>

<p>I have been cycling my bike. Maybe that will end soon too. I don't know, that
is for the future.</p>
]]></content>
   <georss:point>8.857256 -75.635376</georss:point>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Vipassana]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/08/05/Vipassana.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/08/05/Vipassana.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2013-08-05T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/08/05/Vipassana</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/9392460997/" title="Cushion-25 by
mm0hai, on Flickr"><img
src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5496/9392460997_3ab694ea18_z.jpg"
width="640" height="480" alt="Cushion-25"></a></p>

<p>I spent 10 full days sitting on a cushion meditating, on a course run by
S. N. Goenka (by audio recording) and his assistant teacher, Mirjam Berns, who
was present in Costa Rica. I had heard about these courses several times from
travellers over the past year and a half, and now I was near one I thought it
was time to try it.</p>

<p>I didn't really know what meditation was before this course and that is why I
went - curiosity.  There are many forms of meditation. I think what they have
in common, at least those I know of, is concentrating on something. It could
be an image in the mind, a sound like a mantra or drum, breathing, or in the
case of vipassana, the sensations on the body. They have different purposes,
the simplest being to develop discipline of the mind and an ability to
concentrate. I don't know much more about meditation in general though, so
will talk about what we were taught on this course.</p>

<p>The first thing we did was ānāpāna meditation. This meant focusing on the
breath, and specifically the sensations of it moving inside the nostril, and
on the upper lip. It is not about controlling the breath, only observing it as
it comes naturally. The purpose was to develop discipline, and improve our
ability to feel sensations on the body. We did this for most of four days. It
hurt, physically, especially in the knees because of sitting for so long. The
pain was worse because there was no distraction. It was also very boring. I
spent most of the time thinking rather than concentrating.</p>

<p>On the evening of the fourth day and for almost all of the rest of the course,
we were taught and practised vipassana. This involves observing sensations all
over the body. Sensation means any feeling such as hot, cold, itching, pain,
movement of air, etc. While doing this, we were to maintain equanimity and the
awareness of anicca, a Pali word which means change. Equanimity meant we were
not to judge sensation as good or bad, not to be averse to pain, or crave
pleasant sensations. We were also to observe that all sensations are temporary
- they will go away eventually. This was one way to avoid reacting too much to
the pain.</p>

<p>The theory is that, as Goenka says Gautama Buddha taught, suffering is caused
by desire. This could be craving for something not there, or aversion to
something that is. By learning to avoid these feelings, suffering can stop. I
wondered why just observe the sensations on the body? The idea is that all
thoughts or emotions will manifest in the body in some way. By learning not to
react to feelings in the body, all reactions should be covered.</p>

<p>The reactions of craving and aversion are called sankaras. They also said that
sankaras build up - there is a store of old ones. This causes continued
suffering, and rebirth. If you can get rid of them all, then you will be free
of suffering and not have to be reborn. They said that when you stop creating
new sankaras, the new ones come to the surface, and if you remain equanimous,
they disappear.</p>

<p>I found that they did surface. I had maybe five or so in total. When my mind
was clear, they would come suddenly as an image or word out of nowhere, not
connected to any previous thought. The first one I had, for example, was the
image of a dropped mobile phone. Obviously I felt some aversion or pain that I
may have broken an expensive thing.</p>

<p>The sensations on the body can be of two types. "Gross" and "subtle". The
gross sensations are things like pain. There is also a feeling that I got when
there was nothing else, a slight pleasant tingling. When this happens all over
the body, interesting things happen. At one point, briefly, on day eight I
think, I felt my whole body shaking, and oscillating around a vertical line
through the middle. It was rather like a feeling I have had occasionally when
falling asleep - the whole body spins.</p>

<p>The interpretation given by the teacher was that the subtle tingling is you
feeling subatomic particles, and that the shaking and vibrating is feeling the
underlying fabric of the universe. There is a common idea amongst some
spiritual people that the universe is fundamentally "vibrational", and
improving you life or increasing your consciousness means to operate at a
higher frequency. They never say what it is that is meant to be vibrating
though. Maybe it is something like string theory. Maybe that's where string
theory came from, I don't know. Anyway, I don't take this feeling as evidence
of the nature of the universe - it could also be explained by the brain
failing to function correctly after being subjected to this unusual practice.</p>

<p>If you practice more, it is possible for the effect to go much further. Rather
than just the surface, if you can feel only subtle sensation inside the body
as well, then it can feel like the whole body has dissolved. As far as I
understand it from asking people, you don't really feel a physical body
anymore.</p>

<p>As far as I practised the technique, I did have experiences consistent with
what the teachers said. I don't see any reason why they would lie about the
rest, so it seems that with further practice I could experience, or think I
was experiencing, the universe at a more fundamental level, and free myself of
suffering. Maybe I would even clear old sankaras from past lives, which when
it happens apparently allows you to remember those lives. I still don't know
that I agree with all the theory though. One thing the teacher said on one of
his talks though, was that if you don't like the theory just ignore it - the
practice will still work.</p>

<p>Will I keep practising? They say you should do two hours a day. I'm not
sure. I can see that there could be benefits, but on the other hand it
hurts. This is not relaxing, it is not easy. It is physically and mentally
painful and unpleasant. I had a rather unpleasant image at the end of the
course and decided to give my mind a rest for a while. Maybe I'll try it again
sometime, but I am not very keen. On the other hand, if the theory is all
correct, this technique is how I can free myself from suffering and escape the
cycle of rebirth and endless suffering, so if true it seems that it is the
most important, or only thing I should do. That would mean becoming a monk, or
at least devoting significant time to meditating.</p>

<p>I also want to describe the way the course was run. It was like living the
life of a monk for 10 days. Men and women were separated. Talking was not
allowed. Food was eaten at breakfast and lunchtime, but not after 12pm, except
a little fruit for new students (those on their first 10 day course). Reading,
writing, music and any other communications were not allowed. Really, there was
nothing to do but meditation, eat, and rest. The teaching was almost entirely
from S. N. Goenka, in the form of audio recordings. Sometimes he taught during
meditation sessions, but he spoke mostly in the evening discourse, which was
sometimes a lesson, and often rather like a sermon. On the last full day, the
tenth, we were allowed to talk again and genders were no longer separated in
some public spaces. Everyone seemed quite happy to talk, but I found the noise
rather overwhelming initially.</p>

<p>On the last full day I saw a sloth! It was climbing a tree right beside the
path in the centre. I have never seen one before but I like them. I like how
they are lazy and imagining that they just hang out in trees all day being
fluffy and cuddly.</p>

<p>I got the bus back to San Jose the next day, the eleventh, after tidying up
and things in the morning. I didn't want to think about meditation or do it
more. On the bus though, I found my mind was very quiet.  I tried meditating
for lack of anything else to do - I didn't want to read or write - but I
couldn't because of the movement of the bus. It covered the sensations in the
body I was looking for. Maybe it is acceptable to feel the bus shaking you
around. Anyway, I didn't want to think about it or write about it for some
time and did other things until now, just over a week later.</p>
]]></content>
   <georss:point>9.328286 -83.749638</georss:point>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Mother Aya, Aunt Jurema]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/08/05/Mother-Aya.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/08/05/Mother-Aya.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2013-08-05T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/08/05/Mother-Aya</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/9497148473/" title="Magic Potions
from the Rainforest by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img
src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7439/9497148473_c779f76ed7_z.jpg"
width="640" height="480" alt="Magic Potions from the Rainforest"></a></p>

<p>Burning bush? Yes, you can talk with plants.</p>

<p>It tasted like black treacle, but sweeter, and with a hint of marmite.</p>

<p>I had read "DMT: The Spirit Molecule", and wondered if I would experience any
of the common patterns. Maybe I would meet alien entities, or find myself in a
nursery. Maybe I would learn the secrets of the universe. What is its true
nature? What is it all about?</p>

<p>I started to feel the effect of the Ayahuasca in my body after the first dose,
but did not notice any mental effect until shortly after the second, which was
double the size and washed down with a glass of the bitter, astringent,
Jurema. I am wary of mixing things, especially if I've not had them before,
but these plants both contain the same chemically active ingredient, DMT, and
spiritually I guess they are sisters so I thought they would be able to get
along.</p>

<p>At first all was black, but then colour noise appeared - red, green and blue
dots, always switching on and off. Then these formed into lines, which made up
constantly changing shapes. They were square and triangular and zig
zag. Seemed quite binary, angular, computer generated. The lines were in
rainbow colours, the rainbows moved and sparkled. It was very beautiful. With
open eyes, the picture seem quantised into simpler geometrical shapes. Leaves
and gaps between them angular, and they moved like an animation with
insufficient framerate. The images were very beautiful, and if I would have
noticed pain, my face would probably have been hurting from smiling.</p>

<p>I enjoyed this a lot, but I didn't just want pretty pictures. I wanted to
learn something. I said this and asked, "what can you show me?". I didn't get
a direct answer - no voice or character speaking to me - but the answer became
obvious. You are a baby. You know nothing about how the world works. You're
not ready for that sort of thing. Here - play with the pretty sparklies. I
realised I knew nothing, and I might as well enjoy it. When I accepted it, I
realised that being a baby is wonderful. You don't need to do anything or
worry about anything. You are looked after. Like any mother, Mother Aya just
wants her babies to healthy and happy.</p>

<p>I thought I was just happy because of the beauty, but then I realised it was
not just beauty, it was love. I thought I was loving the pictures, but then I
realised that was ridiculous - I am just a tiny spec - almost nothing - how
could I produce so much love? It was clear that this was all there - an
immense field of love - is this what everything is made of? I could only bathe
in it.</p>

<p>Ayahuasca is what is politely called purgative, or cleansing. I was sick
once. When I crawled out of the circle to vomit I felt like a snake. It was
worse for the boy next to me though, who had diarrhoea which at one point
splatted on my face. At first I tried to work out some way in which that had
not actually just happened, but my attempt to deny reality was clearly not
going to work.</p>

<p>There was a lesson though. I had been thinking earlier about how a baby has an
easy life, but it does things like shitting and pissing everywhere. Now I
experienced that this is not always enjoyable for everyone else who has to be
around it. While it is good and right to be a baby when you have to, when you
can you should grow up. I saw birds hatching and flying and making new nests.</p>

<p>I think it is clear that humans as a race are babies. How can we be told the
secrets of the universe when we can't even look after ourselves? We are
shitting all over this planet and can't even feed ourselves without making
such a mess that it will kill us all and everything else that lives
here. Maybe in a few million years, if we survive that long, we will will be
ready to understand.</p>

<p>I asked someone to heat water for me so I could wash my hair and face. Someone
else fed me chocolate. I could enjoy being looked after a little more, but
tomorrow I must grow up.</p>
]]></content>
   <georss:point>8.764126 -83.014069</georss:point>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Honduras]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/06/19/Honduras.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/06/19/Honduras.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2013-06-19T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/06/19/Honduras</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Honduras is a funny country. I couldn't find its identity. Most countries have
some stereotypical things about them that you can think of, like clothes, or
food, or music, or some quality of the people. I had no idea about Honduras
before I got there, and I still didn't when I left. It seems to be some sort
of generic Central America, with a great <a
href="/blog/2013/05/24/USA-Calling.html">influence from the USA</a>, and not
much of its own. It was however the home to some of the most exciting and
dangerous riding I did.</p>

<p>San Pedro Sula has at least some years been rated the most violent city in the
world. It is controlled by drug cartels. Someone I met later who had to go to
hospital there told of how he was asked to sit on a trolley which was covered
in blood. Apparently the staff thought this was pretty much normal, because it
was full of people who had been shot. The Daily Mail says there are 3.3
murders per day, and will show you pictures of this if you care to
search. Riding through the city is not really something to be recommended, but
there isn't much choice but to cross it somehow.</p>

<p>I wanted to make sure I got there before dark, so I left early and didn't muck
about. Approaching the city I started to see the cars with blacked out windows
and no number plates. Some are often fitted with bulletproof glass, which I saw
advertised. The driving standard was not good. I got the impression from the
way I was passed that everyone just drove as if I was not even there. Several
times I would have been hit if I had not ducked out the way at the last
minute. I heard that to take out a hit on someone here costs about $25, so the
value of my life was less than what it might cost someone to fix some
scratched paint on their car.</p>

<p>On the outskirts of town I stopped in an Honduran fast food type place for a
second breakfast / mid-morning meal and was amused to see a gringo who looked
pretty much exactly like a CIA agent from a Bond film. I doubt a group of
three middle aged men, each arriving here in their own vehicle to meet in an
unnoticeable place on the edge of town were on holiday, anyway.</p>

<p>In town, a car full of girls were shouting and taking photos of me. Apparently
the girls like gringos here, or possibly people crazy enough to cycle.</p>

<p>I found my prebooked hostel fairly easily. It was surrounded by a high wall
topped with spikes, razor wire and an electric fence. They told me this is an
affluent residential area. Leaving the hostel meant taking a taxi to the mall,
which was a relatively safe place where only rich people could go. There were
armed guards of course. The banks had lockers outside for you to put your
pistol in before you entered, and a few larger ones if you had a shotgun.</p>

<p>I read a spoof story about the opening of the city mall, in which the people
stormed it and cut up the benches for fire wood. I can almost imagine that
happening - just up the road I had seen people carrying bundles of wood on the
back of their bikes.</p>

<p>One day I decided I wanted to see this city, not just the American fast food
chains that lined the circunvalacion I rode down. I cycled into centre of
town. On the way I saw a naked man kneeling with his hands in the gutter. At
first thought it was some sort of extreme begging, but he was facing the
traffic, and was ignored. Maybe a yogi? But why practice yoga in the gutter?</p>

<p>I had some idea about wanting to sit in a cafe in the main square but there
was only a McDonald's there too. Money changers and aggressive "Professional
Photographers" stalked in the zocalo.</p>

<p>The next city was Tegucigalpa, the capital. Here it was ok to walk outside, in
some areas, but not at night, so more taxis to Pizza Hut, which has a salad
bar which will feed a touring cyclist for $5. The approach to the city though,
was the most exciting and dangerous cycling I have ever done.</p>

<p>From San Pedro Sula, I had to cross mountain passes, maybe 1500m of climbing at
a glace at the profile. This gave a long fast descent, which continued down
from the mountains into the city. Here there was extreme high speed traffic
dodging including overtaking at least two motorbikes, and avoiding the wheel
sized manholes which had their covers stolen for scrap metal. When it levelled
out, I was then navigating back streets in one of the most dangerous cities in
the world, all under time pressure to make sure I had somewhere secure to
sleep before it got dark.</p>

<p>In La Ceiba, I came the closest to being robbed (that I know of). Someone
tried to get my camera out of its bag while I carried it, but he was very ham
fisted and I felt the tugging. Here was also where I found myself surrounded
by three armed guards.</p>

<p>I went to a mall to buy some new sandals because my last ones had fallen
apart. I was sitting on a bench researching it on my phone, when one of them
objected that I wasn't allowed to be there without shoes on. At first I
decided I didn't understand him. Then he went and got two of his mates. So now
there I was, barefoot sitting on a bench, and surrounded by three armed men. I
considered seeing what would happen if I just sat there - a protest against
the ridiculousness of it - but as I happened to be there to buy sandals anyway
I decided to go and do that now. So I remembered how to speak Spanish, and
they agreed to let me buy some, but not on my own. I was escorted by one of
the guards to the shoe shop, and he waited outside until I came out with them
on. Of course noone would actually tell me why.</p>

<p>On <a href="/blog/2013/06/07/Utila.html">Utila</a>, one of the Bay Islands of
Honduras, I learned to scuba dive. I wouldn't really consider this Honduras
though. It was British until quite recently, and is only really officially
Honduran. A Honduran I spoke to in La Ceiba said if he wanted to get the ferry
there, he would be questioned first, under the assumption that his purpose was
to rob the gringos.</p>

<p>This was the same guy who tried to befriend me and walked around town with me
for about an hour before asking for money. He kept asking what I wanted -
weed, drugs, women, ... He seemed frustrated that I didn't really want
anything - I suppose this is what the consumer society is all about too - make
people want things so you can control them - or in his case make some
profit. At least he did help me by telling me not to go for a walk down the
beach, which was going into a particularly bad area controlled by the crack
dealers and pimps.</p>

<p>I did a a river rafting trip one day, which turned out to be rather more
serious that I expected of a typical organised tourist activity. Maybe because
I was on my own the guide didn't hold back. It involved a a non-trivial partly
overhanging rock climb out of the river, to a ledge he told me was 11 meters
above the water, and then jumping into the rapids. My heart really was
pounding before I did this, but really I had no choice - I certainly couldn't
climb down - I only just made it up, and there was no other way down. This was
not an old lady tour as it appeared in the brochure.</p>

<p>Honduras was also a country of buckets of water. Buckets for showering by
pouring it over your head, and buckets for flushing the toilet. The showering
is actually really good - better than a conventional one because you get so
much more water in one go, but I didn't much like the toilet flushing this
way. Before I had worked out this was what was done, I did a jobby in a
restaurant and couldn't flush it. They had given me some food for free "a
present", so I thought I would be leaving them a present in return, but later
realised there was a barrel of water outside.</p>

<p>Honduras is the country where I first encountered bedbugs, lack of basic
plumbing, US fast food beside starving beggars, and some fear at what I think was
an actually real threat of violence, but it also has islands also look like this,</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8908097643/" title="Water Cay
from Boat by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img
src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3747/8908097643_279a18f871_z.jpg"
width="640" height="480" alt="Water Cay from Boat"></a></p>

<p>and rivers like this for swimming,</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/9001628671/" title="DSCF4872 by
mm0hai, on Flickr"><img
src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5446/9001628671_4b2c3d737a_z.jpg"
width="480" height="640" alt="DSCF4872"></a></p>

<p>in which the locals also bathe and wash their clothes, presumably because they
have no other choice.</p>
]]></content>
   <georss:point>14.779530 -87.182007</georss:point>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[El Salvador]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/06/18/El-Salvador.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/06/18/El-Salvador.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2013-06-18T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/06/18/El-Salvador</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/9120315746/" title="El Salvador
Honduras Border, by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img
src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7407/9120315746_21ef809110_z.jpg"
width="640" height="480" alt="DSCF4937"></a></p>

<p>My route through Honduras did not leave very good options for visiting El
Salvador. To ride from one end of the country to the other, I would have to
go back north through Honduras. This route would be through the mountains -
hard work. It had also started raining now, and I didn't feel like
it. However, it was not far to the border, so I thought I might as well just
make a short side trip to tick the country.</p>

<p>I decided to head for La Union, a town on the cost, from which I could maybe
explore some islands or get a boat to Nicaragua.</p>

<p>As I was riding down the road, I realised that this must be the one Mark
Beaumont skipped because he thought it was too dangerous. He took a car from
El Salvador to Nicaragua. Then I remembered that he said something like, "this
isn't a place to hang around in", about what must have been La Union.</p>

<p>I got through the rather dodgy border without incident. All borders around
here are dodgy but at least this one had windows - you didn't need to go
inside, where they usually insist you leave your bike out of site. I was
trying to get to an hotel in La Union - I knew there was one from another
blog. I wasn't going to make it before dark though. I asked some police at a
checkpoint and they said to go to the police station at the junction on the
road down to La Union. I did so, and they said they would need to check with
the boss. In the mean time, they gave me a lift into town to get some
pupusas. They said it was not a safe place, and not a good idea to by cycling
around here even during the day. While I was waiting for my pupusas, they were
standing watch from across the road, one of them with his hand on his
holstered pistol. I spoke to a guy when I was waiting. He also said he would
not recommend cycling around here, or in Honduras, but further south was safer
in Nicaragua, and Costa Rica.</p>

<p>After we got back, someone put a mattress in the front office for me. I slept
adequately. Also, I had a wash the some way they did - by pouring buckets of
water over myself. I think it is probably more effective than a shower - much
greater water volume is achieved quickly.</p>

<p>I still hadn't decided where to go next. The options were try and get a boat
to Nicaragua, or Honduras, cycle up the coast and maybe find some nice
beaches, or go back the way I came. I was put off cycling around here by the
warnings, and one man said the beaches near here were not very nice anyway. To
get a boat I would need to go into town and search for it, which might not
actually exist, or be too expensive.</p>

<p>The next day I decided to go back the way I came. I hitched a lift part of the
way, to the junction where this time I took the road for Nicaragua.</p>

<p>I should add, to avoid giving a totally negative impression of the country,
that most cyclist come this way, and they seem to like the coast and
beaches. Apparently it is a great place for surfing.</p>
]]></content>
   <georss:point>13.357627 -87.914057</georss:point>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Utila]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/06/07/Utila.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/06/07/Utila.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2013-06-07T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/06/07/Utila</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>DMT</strong>: Dimethyltriptamine, a psychedelic.</p>

<blockquote><p>"subjective effects can range from short-lived milder psychedelic states to
powerful immersive experiences; these are often described as a total loss of
connection to conventional reality with the encounter of ineffable
spiritual/alien realms." -- wikipedia</p></blockquote>

<p><strong>DMT</strong>: Divemaster in Training.</p>

<blockquote><p>People who accompany you in an immersive experience of encounters with
strange creatures in an alien realm. -- me</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8908111363/" title="DSCF4793 by
mm0hai, on Flickr"><img
src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3682/8908111363_a979f91e41_z.jpg"
width="640" height="480" alt="DSCF4793"></a></p>

<p>Underwater, perception changes. Everything is 33% bigger, sound is different
and faster, gravity can be countered allowing you to fly, and everything
tastes of salt. The trees are pink, and the birds are very strange.</p>

<p>I'm on the boat at the end of my holiday trip to Utila. I feel a bit sad, but
I don't think I'll miss the place. I didn't think I could stand the dorm room
for more than a couple of days, but then I realised I stayed for twelve.</p>

<p>I learned to scuba dive here. It's not something I had ever thought about
before, but since the Yucatan, people were talking about it. You can dive in
the Cenotes there - gateways to the Mayan underworld, and there is also the
Mesoamerican reef that runs all down the cost from Mexico to Honduras. I
learnt that Utila is the cheapest place in the world to take diving courses,
so I thought I might as well try it.</p>

<p>I did some snorkelling first, off Caye Caulker, Belize. This was a good
introduction, because once you get used to a mask and breathing through a
tube, it doesn't really make much difference to how it feels on your face
whether the tube is connected to the atmosphere or a tank. The reef was more
alive with fish and animals here than in Utila, too.</p>

<p>I took the PADI Open Water course, the entry level qualification that lets you
dive with a buddy. (Solo diving is highly discouraged by most people, and
should only be done with redundant equipment and extra training.) I decided to
do the Advanced course too, after some thought, because I wanted to do some
diving after the training, and the course didn't cost too much more than just
paying for some dives. It allows diving in more places too, and deeper.</p>

<p>I particularly liked a wall dive we did. It is a unique feeling to be able to
dive off a cliff and not fall. Swimming along the top of the coral, then
turning 90 degrees down, still swimming. The world rotates and you are free of
up and down.</p>

<p>We also visited a wreck, and did a night dive. The scene of everyone
descending into a circle on the bottom with beams of light from torches
resembled something from a sci fi film; maybe a space ship landing, or a team
going to recover a crashed ship.</p>

<p>I also found that there are some good people in Honduras, who don't just try
to steal from you, like the taxi drivers and the person who tried to take my
camera out its bag in La Ceiba. There are still the people coming into what
was my home for a while to try and sell me weed or failing that crack, and
people stealing from the kitchen, but there is the occasional pretty
engineering nerd and nyancat fan around too.</p>

<p>Actually I think diving is a bit of a geeky hobby. I met a couple of
engineers, a physics teacher, a biologist / bird watcher, and a web
designer. It's not really a sport, being much like a casual stroll would be on
land. It probably appeals to geeks because of the equipment and the required
knowledge of physics, chemistry and biology. Looking at fish is the underwater
equivalent of bird watching, too.</p>

<p>I'm on my way back to the mainland now anyway. I think I'll make a brief
foray into the jungle, then rejoin my bike and return to the cycling life. I
forgot about cycling after a day or two here - it was a distant memory of a
past life, but it is resurfacing now. I'm not sure I want to be working away
in the sun and dust again, rather than floating weightless in the sea, but it
seems to be what I'm doing.</p>
]]></content>
   <georss:point>16.097582 -86.896357</georss:point>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Minimising Water Usage when Travelling]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/06/01/Saving-Water.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/06/01/Saving-Water.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2013-06-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/06/01/Saving-Water</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Here are some tips on using less water when travelling, by bike or with
backpack. I learnt them from other travellers, and myself through necessity.</p>

<h2>Ration Sweat</h2>

<p>Ration sweat, so you don't need to drink as much. In hot places, don't cycle
in midday sun. Instead, sleep, read, or write, under shelter from the
sun. Start cycling as soon as it gets light, and also in the evening, and you
should have enough time to get in the distance you want. In Central America, I
think I need to drink about 1 litre an hour, except around midday, maybe 1130
to 1500, when 2 litres an hour is about right if cycling.</p>

<h2>Washing Up</h2>

<p>Avoid frying - this makes washing up tractable. To cook vegetables, add them
to the boiling rice or pasta you are making. This also saves time cooking.</p>

<p>To wash a pan with only a few millilitres of water, first scrape it out with
your spoon as well as you can. Then add very little water. Rub with fingers,
or a scrubber if you have one. Remove debris with fingers. Repeat maybe once
or twice. At his stage the pan will be mostly clean, but there will probably
still be some bits of food stuck on from cooking. Now make a cup of tea in the
pan. The boiling water will remove what's stuck, and sterilise the pan. The
tea will cover any slight taste from the food. You had to drinking something
anyway, so this uses the drinking water for cleaning too. Use a lid if
available to minimise water loss as steam.</p>

<h2>Water Bottles</h2>

<p>When you need some water for washing hands, or small quantities for washing
other things, there is a technique for dispensing it.</p>

<p>Using a normal bottle of water with a screwtop, do not remove the lid. Unscrew
it just enough to allow drips of water out when you squeeze the bottle. If you
then hold the bottle between your legs, you have a tap with controllable flow
under which you can wash your hands. Better, especially if you have a large
bottle, is to put it sideways on some raised platform. Turn the lid as a tap
and wash hands under it.</p>

<h2>Paper</h2>

<p>Paper is much lighter than water. Many things you would use water for at home
can be done with tissue paper instead. For example, cleaning some things to a
good enough standard. When brushing teeth, it can be used to remove toothpaste
foam from the face.</p>

<h2>Showers</h2>

<p>This one is actually about using lots of water, but it's fun. :-) If you are
living on a beach and feel the need for the luxury of a fresh water shower:</p>

<ol>
<li>Carry large bottle of water to the beach.</li>
<li>Get naked.</li>
<li>Get someone to pour it over you.</li>
</ol>


<p>I leaned this one when I was arriving at a hippie beach in Tenerife, and the
first person I saw was a girl doing this in the moonlight. She didn't mind,
and invited me for dinner with them.</p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[USA Calling]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/05/24/USA-Calling.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/05/24/USA-Calling.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2013-05-24T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/05/24/USA-Calling</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I have thought about giving up this cycling nonsense and moving to the USA. I
would buy a Harley-Davidson instead, and eat burgers and donuts until fat.</p>

<p>I've not been to the US yet, but I think I've got almost the same experience in
this part of Honduras. All along the road into San Pedro Sula, there are huge
signs for fast food places. I'm now in the City Mall of San Pedro Sula, which
has the same American junk food chains, many of which I have now tried for the
first time over the last couple of days. Wendy's, Applebee's, Dunkin' Donuts,
Subway, Quiznos, PizzaHut, KFC, Burger King... Conspicuously missing are
Starbucks and Costa Coffee.</p>

<p>I get the impression that people in Honduras want to be American. There are
shops call things like "American Company", the coffee places are called
"Espresso Americano", there was a huge billboard with a topless man on it that
said "American" - maybe advertising that clothes shop, or selling American
men. It seem the girls here like gringos, too. A giggling car full were
shouting at me and taking photos when I was cycling into town.</p>

<p>Mostly it's the food though, which is at American prices - way more than local
food can cost. I think the idea is "you are what you eat". If you are rich
enough to afford Mcdonalds, you eat your way to America. I've tried several of
these places, but suspect I won't qualify for citizenship until my BMI gets up
rather more.</p>

<p>Apart from the food, the USA has had a huge influence here, and is the reason
why it's not safe to go out, and why the place I am staying has a high wall
topped with spikes, razor wire and an electric fence. This town, San Pedro
Sula, is run by drugs cartels. They only have money and power because of the
ridiculous policies of the US and its War on Drugs. If drugs were not illegal
in the US, there would probably not be 3 people getting shot dead per day in
just this town, and probably fewer people dying in the US too, if they can get
pure substances of known dose.</p>

<p>So I'm in the mall eating junk, because it's a relatively safe place, and
giving money to companies who send it back to the US to pay for the violence
outside. It's a prison where I'm paying to cause the problem that keeps me
here.</p>

<p>There is also a great US influence on Belize, although it seems much less
destructive. There are many products imported from the US. There are brands I
had heard of "in popular culture", but some I had never seen. I drank the cool
aid, for example. I didn't buy the Lucky Charms, but I did have some pop
tarts. The poptarts where in honour of nyancat though, so I couldn't miss
those.</p>
]]></content>
   <georss:point>14.906967 -87.808228</georss:point>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Belize]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/05/21/Belize.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/05/21/Belize.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2013-05-21T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/05/21/Belize</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Belize is mental, and I love it. This was one of my first thoughts on
arriving, and it basically stayed the same.</p>

<p>By mental, I mean the mixture of cultures, which can be quite
disorientating. When I first arrived, I knew that people were meant to speak
English, but I didn't quite believe it. I had been in Spanish speaking
countries for months, and had to remember to use English. When I first tried
it I was surprised that it worked.</p>

<p>In this country, I have cycled through a Menonite community with fancy modern
farming equipment and horse drawn buggies, where I ate a burger from "Fat
Boys" American fast food van. I was in the Mid-west, and an oil field. I
passed Santorini, a Greek island, then the Shanghai service station to a
Chinese hotel. Soon I reached the Caribbean where everyone called me Rasta
instead of Gringo, and I drank rum and went sailing from an island. Later I
cycled through Garifuna towns - black people from St Vincent, and later an
East Indian town. I saw no other white people in Dangringa - a Garifuna
town. In Belize, it would be helpful to know Chinese, and Kriol, and Garifuna.</p>

<p>Belize used to be British Honduras, and it still has the Queen on the
money. It is closer to the USA though, and is probably popular with Americans
because of the language. It's now a place where you can buy Cabdury's or
Hershey's, and choose between Oreos or Ginger Nuts and Bourbon biscuits. US
dollars are accepted everywhere, and are worth two Belize Dollars.</p>

<p>Belize is mostly jungle, which is filled with Mayan ruins, rivers and cave
systems. One day, I took a tour to the <a
href="/blog/2013/05/07/ATM-Cave.html">ATM Cave</a>.</p>

<p>I also stopped at the zoo briefly, initially for ice cream, but then I had a
look around too. It is an unusual zoo. All the animals are rescued, for example
from private captors who should not have had them or didn't want them
anymore. Also, they are in the area where they would normally live - they are
all native animals. I actually had a good feeling about the place.</p>

<p>Belize city, I was told to avoid because it is dangerous. I went through only
to get a ferry to Caye Calker, where I did some snorkelling.</p>

<p>I took a tour by sailing boat to the reef and saw various interesting animals,
like a sea turtle, sharks, rays, and a manatee. It took me a while to get used
to the gear but then I enjoyed seeing things I had never before. I recommend
this trip. Otherwise, I didn't like Caye Calker very much. It was far too
crowded, touristic, and expensive.</p>

<p>I think I would like to go back to Belize, either to explore the jungle, or by
sea around the cayes.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8805598786/" title="DSCF4600 by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8274/8805598786_fb68f00bda_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="DSCF4600"></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8737210820/" title="Arriving Caribbean Island, with bike by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7285/8737210820_0575be9bd9_z.jpg" width="480" height="640" alt="Arriving Caribbean Island, with bike"></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8736198721/" title="DSCF4534 by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7287/8736198721_cd501ac959_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="DSCF4534"></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8800093221/" title="DSCF4690 by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2883/8800093221_5ebc9725a0_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="DSCF4690"></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8800062227/" title="DSCF4672 by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3734/8800062227_d263fb0e4a_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="DSCF4672"></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8810633594/" title="DSCF4669 by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5332/8810633594_f7114b047e_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="DSCF4669"></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8799626577/" title="DSCF4624 by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3669/8799626577_9760dacabe_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="DSCF4624"></a></p>
]]></content>
   <georss:point>17.050877 -88.478394</georss:point>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[An emotional day]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/05/15/An-Emotional-Day.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/05/15/An-Emotional-Day.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2013-05-15T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/05/15/An-Emotional-Day</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I thought this day might be interesting as an example of some thoughts and
feelings experienced during a day of cycle touring.</p>

<p>This morning I left a hostel where I had been staying for several days. I
didn't miss it, but when leaving somewhere I usually do think about what I
might not have done there that I might have liked to do. Also, I am usually
slightly anxious about leaving something. I check several times that I haven't
left anything.</p>

<p>I went to the post office to send a letter and post card. The pretty stamps
made me happy, as did completing a task. Then I had breakfast at "Amor y
Cafe". They lived up to their name with some heart shaped ice cubes made of
coffee. I liked that, but was not totally relaxed because I didn't want to
miss the boat back to the mainland.</p>

<p>The sea is beautiful around there - mostly green, not blue - and I enjoyed the
ride back. I had a lunch sandwich and spoke a little to the guy at my table in
the ferry terminal. I had decided earlier that I would try and hitchhike to
Belmopan. I had already cycled this road, and where I was could be considered
a side trip, so this would not compromise a claim of having cycled all the way
south, and I didn't want to cycle this road again. It was not too bad, but I
had seen it before and it was not very interesting. I thought hitching a lift
would be easy because people in Belize are generally friendly, and I think
interested in the cyclist they see. More than one person I have met has said
they saw me cycling at some point. It is a small country with few roads.</p>

<p>Anyway, my expectation of it being easy was exceeded - the man asked me if I
wanted to stay at his place in Belmopan before I asked anything. I mentioned
hitchhiking and he offered a lift, which I accepted. So I didn't even mount the
bike before I got a lift, and it was to nearly exactly where I wanted to go.</p>

<p>When we got going I was really happy. I enjoyed moving so fast,
effortlessly. I felt the universe was looking after me today, in providing
exactly what I asked for. I laughed to myself at the drivers singing to the
radio.</p>

<p>I had offered him some money when he filled up petrol in Belize City. Around
here, at least in most other Central American countries, I believe pure
hitchhiking is not common. People generally expect to be paid what it would
cost in a bus. Busses here are really cheap, so I was thinking of offering a
couple of dollars. He said when we arrived I could give him something
depending on my means.</p>

<p>We arrived and he asked for money. I offered Quetzales, which I didn't need,
and thought he would because he travelled to Guatemala often. He said he
didn't want them, and wanted trustworthy currencies. He must have seen my
emergency 100 EUR not in my wallet, because he then asked for Euros. I offered
three dollars, and he said he wanted 20. 20 would pay for a bus journey to
Guatemala, about four times the distance we just did. This didn't seem like
the deal I was expecting. In the end I gave him ten, which I think is about
double what the bus would have cost. He then walked away without saying
anything.</p>

<p>I cycled off, but had a bad feeling now. I couldn't quite work out why to
start with. Initially I kept checking and rechecking I hadn't lost anything -
things that might have fallen off in his car, or been taken my his friend when
we were at the shop near the house we stopped at. I finally convinced myself I
had everything, but still had a bad feeling. After further thinking, I worked
out that the source of this feeling was seeing that man again. I knew if I did
it would be a bad thing. Either me returning because I had lost something,
which I had now ruled out, or him coming down the road to rob me. I remembered
that the first thing he asked in the cafe was how much did my bike cost. That
is always an unpleasant question. Then he had seen I had a lot of money, and
was demanding it. He know where I was going. Maybe he would get back in the
car later, maybe at dusk with his mate, and come for my bike and money.</p>

<p>Then I started to have other thoughts, like what if I had been drugged. I
didn't think he really had a good opportunity to do this - it is a pretty
unlikely thing. I was being a bit paranoid now, but that is the point of this
story, to show how some emotions can occur and probably be rather too
strong. I was thinking about this because I had heard stories about the use of
a drug on travellers that makes them like zombies. They will then do what they
are told by the attacker, such as taking all the money out their bank account
and giving it to them. Someone I met in Oaxaca said this happened to him, and
the internet claims it is true also. I was feeling a bit funny too. Maybe I
was drugged - by myself with an unaccustomed amount of caffeine this morning.</p>

<p>At one point I remembered an idea a fellow traveller was talking about -
teleportation. If you had a teleporter, would you use it when travelling? I
felt that if I had it, I would right now jump to Edinburgh and not come back
till the morning, or maybe 24hours later to preserve a sort of continuity of
my journey.</p>

<p>Later, once I had examined and realised the source of the emotion - seeing the
man again, I could work out a logical solution to the problem. I was concerned
about being attacked on the road at dusk, so I only needed to find a really
good hidden campsite well before it got dark. Around here, that should not be
too hard. I suddenly felt much better.</p>

<p>Now I started to realise where I was. I became present. I noticed the beauty
of the forest I was cycling through. It was quite unlike the Selva Lacandon -
it was more open and pretty. I noticed the different coloured flowers. Then I
noticed the air. I really started to feel the air - a thick, significant
substance through which I moved, and I thought about how it came from the
trees. I considered how the air and the trees and everything are linked.</p>

<p>Not too much later, I saw a potentially good camp site. I stopped by the road
for a while to consider my location and possible distance for tomorrow, and
decide whether to stop here. I did.</p>

<p>I went into an orange grove. It looks like a really good campsite, because the
trees provide excellent cover from the road. Also, between the trees is
relatively flat ground where I could push the bike easily, and even cycle on a
track initially, so I got off the road fast and was not seen.</p>

<p>I was still not relaxed though, because I had various things to do before it
gets dark. Ideally I want to be in the hammock before dark, to avoid the
mosquitoes, and so that I can see to avoid snakes and spiders. There are some
very poisonous snakes all around Central America. So I cooked, brushed my
teeth, made tea and put up the hammock. Tonight I was pleased with myself
because I got everything squared away. The only things not packed in their
place on the bike now are my hammock, computer, which I'm using in the hammock
now, and clothes and shoes which I will put on in the morning.</p>

<p>I'm relatively relaxed in the hammock now, but somewhat alert to vehicle
noise. A vehicle playing music sounded like it stopped near here for a
while. I became concerned that it was a farmer going to come done the track I
did earlier, or maybe someone had seen the light of my computer screen (quite
unlikely} so I closed the computer and listened for a while. Then it moved on.</p>

<p>There we have a day of cycle touring. From a fairly neutral start, to something
approaching joy at a car ride, to fear and paranoia and wanting to magically
be somewhere else caused by a slight suspicion, to presence and joy in nature,
to relative, but wary calm in a campsite.</p>

<p>I think a lot of this would be easier if I had a friend with me. It would
allow a second opinion on the analysis of situations - did that guy seem
dodgy to you too? It would probably also reduce fear - having some backup in
case of a fight. I'm coming around to the idea of cycling with someone
else. Maybe if I decide to do so, the universe will provide.</p>
]]></content>
   <georss:point>17.163385 -88.756828</georss:point>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Chino]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/05/09/Chino.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/05/09/Chino.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2013-05-09T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/05/09/Chino</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8732330809/" title="DSCF4447 by
mm0hai, on Flickr"><img
src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7289/8732330809_b85b9f81b6_z.jpg"
width="640" height="480" alt="DSCF4447"></a></p>

<p>I passed the Shanghai service station. This was after all the Chinese
shops. Nearly all the shops are Chinese. Belmopan is a dump (I'm in Belize
now). I read there was not much there but government buildings, but there
really is nothing. I was expecting at least a zocalo and a coffee shop. No.</p>

<p>I found the "Eastern Guest House" - the English translation under the
Chinese. The concrete floor was covered in ripped plastic, hair and dirt. I
wheeled my bike in, with the Chinese cow still hanging on the back. The
bathroom hadn't been cleaned. I brushed my teeth with Chinese toothpaste.</p>

<p>In the morning, I left. I should have made more effort to learn Chinese from
Fengqin, then I could have asked for directions to somewhere for breakfast. I
only knew how to ask for the cat temple.</p>

<p>Later I passed Japan, and Santorini, a Greek island. I sat down in a restaurant
to Caribbean food and Spanish conversation at the neighbouring table.</p>
]]></content>
   <georss:point>17.247998 -88.778801</georss:point>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bella]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/05/09/Bella.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/05/09/Bella.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2013-05-09T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/05/09/Bella</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I stayed at Bella's hostel in San Ignacio. My room had the feel of a log
cabin, with a bookshelf beside my bed. It was built to a design, not bashed
together like the constructions I was used to in Guatemala. One night became
three. "Stand in your truth", said a fairy in the bathroom.</p>

<p>I was invited to visit the farm. It was down a road which headed into the
jungle, but here was mostly farms. The government gives away land here at
election time, if you vote, or if you don't want land you can have money. If
I'd gone further, I'd have reached an army base ("bring cigarettes and rum")
and later Caracol, a Mayan ruin. I stopped at the farm.</p>

<p>Ernest, a very friendly and relaxed, presumably Garifuna, man gave me a tour
of the medicine trail. This was a path through the jungle with signs on many
plants with medicinal uses. I picked some leaves which I later used to make a
poultice for the wounds on my feet. I also met the pig, who was very happy and
wagged his tail when sprayed with water from the hose. I saw some pineapples
growing on the ground, and plenty of chickens.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8729834116/" title="DSCF4269 by
mm0hai, on Flickr"><img
src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7425/8729834116_0b8c5e1b18_z.jpg"
width="480" height="640" alt="DSCF4269"></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8730258925/" title="DSCF4372 by
mm0hai, on Flickr"><img
src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7459/8730258925_121581df05_z.jpg"
width="640" height="480" alt="DSCF4372"></a></p>

<p>I spent the rest of the evening lying in a hammock at the top of the hill
above the river. Not much happened. The sheep grazed. The sun set behind the
hill.</p>

<p>Bella wasn't the woman who seemed to run the hostel, or the crazy skankin
rastaman who helped. It turned out Bella was a beautiful little rasta
girl. She ran around and cartwheeled through the kitchen, with dreads
flying. "Do you do your dreads yourself?", I asked. "No, my mum does. I see
you <em>try</em>". I got out the crochet hook and worked with that while I
watched Forest Gump. "I just felt like running." I just felt like cycling.</p>

<p>In the morning I didn't leave at 5am, as would be sensible to avoid the heat
when cycling. I spent some time sitting by the river, meditating, and
listening to the birds. I heard a toucan, and the screeching one which sounds
like a piezo buzzer. The turtles were hiding, or maybe they were all on the
wall at the hostel, where their backs painted in rasta colours told everyone
to "DO YOUR DISHES".</p>

<p>I'm en route to Caye Calker now. Maybe I'll visit Bella's hostel there.</p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Actun Tunichil Muknal (ATM) Cave]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/05/07/ATM-Cave.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/05/07/ATM-Cave.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2013-05-07T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/05/07/ATM-Cave</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In Belize, I went on a tour of the <a
href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Actun_Tunichil_Muknal">Actun Tunichil Muknal
(ATM)</a> cave, which I had seen mentioned on a crazyguy blog. I was shocked
at the price, $100US, especially after having come from Mexico, but I did it
anyway because of the rave reviews on trip adviser.</p>

<p>After a short walk on a well beaten path through the jungle we, a group of 8,
arrived at an area with some palapas and firepits. Then we went down to the
river which was flowing out of the cave. It was a bit cold in the water, and
after the entrances, totally dark. It is limestone and has formed all sorts of
interesting formations. In some parts it sparkles, I think with quartz.</p>

<p>After a while we climbed up to a dry part of the cave. Here there are many
pieces of Mayan pottery, and bones. It seems they conducted ceremonies here,
probably to ask gods for help in times of need. They believe caves are a
gateway to the afterlife.</p>

<p>The grand finale of the tour is the skeleton called the Crystal Maiden. It has
been fused with the floor by the limestone, and it sparkles.</p>

<p><img width="640"
src="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/5/54/Actun_Tunichil_Muknal.jpg"
alt="Crystal Maiden, ATM Cave" title="Crystal Maiden, ATM Cave. Photo by Peter
Andersen, licence details at
http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:Actun_Tunichil_Muknal.jpg"></p>

<p>I think I liked seeing the cave itself more than any of the archaeology in
particular. The rock formations were very varied, interesting and impressive.
Of course, because this was a tour group we were not really experiencing any
of this at its best.</p>

<p>The right way to visit this cave would be to go with some friends, probably at
night, not that it matters inside, and experience it, not be told about it. It
is not a place for talking, it is a place to feel. It should be a place to
explore your mind and soul. It would be enhanced greatly by finding some local
psychedelic - possibly consult a shaman or priest if such a person still
exists around there, and by fire. They don't allow fire now to preserve the
cave, but I feel like it is very important. This could be a life changing
experience, and you would see it as the Mayans did.</p>

<p>I said before it was cold in the cave, but not just physically. It is a deep,
dark place of the dead, or the never alive, or wondering if you are or not,
and of time disappearing.</p>

<p>I found it reassuring that there were some women in our group. I think because
they seemed alive, and can make new life. I was relived when I exited the cave
and could see the sun again and feel the warmth. The world was still
there. Exiting this cave is like being born again, or knowing you are alive
again.</p>

<p>There was some life in the cave. A tiny green shoot with one leave was growing
in a corner of a passage. The guide thought it lived on the light from our
headlamps.</p>

<h3>Aside, on Conservation</h3>

<p>I was considering the balance beetween conservation and use. The best way to
conserve it is to let noone in, but then there is no point. If noone sees it,
it makes no difference if it is destroyed or not. I don't think use of this
cave should be stopped now - our civilisation may even benefit from it more
than the Maya. Study it thoroughly, then allow people to use it. This won't
happen as long as someone is making a lot of money from controlling access,
though.</p>
]]></content>
   <georss:point>17.200690 -88.851199</georss:point>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Guatemala]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/05/04/Guatemala.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/05/04/Guatemala.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2013-05-04T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/05/04/Guatemala</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I don't have a lot to say about this country, because I wasn't there for very
long. I travelled through the North of Peten, and then a short distance in the
south east to the border with Honduras.</p>

<p>In general, it seemed to be very much like Mexico. There was no sudden change
after crossing the border. I enjoyed cycling from Flores to Belize, I think
partly because it was more colourful. Physically - houses and fences are
painted, the hammocks are maybe more colourful, and also there seemed to be a
bit more variety. In Mexico, everything was the same. The businesses, the
products available were usually exactly the same as each other. I don't think
it was as bad here.</p>

<p>One noticable change is the guns. There are armed guards, usually with
shotguns, nearly everywhere. That includes ice cream shops. I was amused by
one gun shop called "Magnum" just beside an ice cream shop.</p>

<p>There are various places I would have liked to go but they were a bit too out
of the way for me just now. The hot waterfalls near Rio Dulce, and the river
and caves at Semuc Champey certainly sound worth visiting. I also skipped Lago
Atitlan and Antigua. I think Antigua is much like San Cristobal de las Casas,
though.</p>
]]></content>
   <georss:point>16.914282 -89.917603</georss:point>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[An unpleasant day]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/04/30/Hospital.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/04/30/Hospital.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2013-04-30T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/04/30/Hospital</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The day I woke up with a fever and ended up in hospital.</p>

<p>I woke up in my hammock at the Guatemalan migration post at about 5am with a
fever, but tried to ignore it for the moment. I started cycling later, and got
about 20km along the road before I stopped at a petrol station. I was feeling
pretty bad now. I could only just eat a biscuit thing (bran fruit, it was
called) and I drank a bottle of Gatorade. I didn't think it was a good idea to
cycle further, and I would not have enjoyed cycling feeling like that, so I
waited for a bus.</p>

<p>I had read that if you get a fever after being in a malarious area the first
thing you need to do is get checked for Malaria. I thought I would go to the
nearest town for a doctor, but I wanted to go to Flores as I thought that
would be a nice place to recover, and also there would be a cash machine
there. I didn't know the exchange rate so only risked very little in pesos to
the border based moneychangers.</p>

<p>The bus was something like a large minibus, with a roofrack where my bike
went. This was the worst bus ride of my life. The road was stony, long,
straight, and with nothing interesting at all to see. It is, I think, also the
worst road to cycle I have ever seen. The bus was hot, and as the journey went
on it got hotter. More people got on, and I started to feel worse.</p>

<p>At 1200, I got hold of my paracetamol and started pouring water on my head and
face to try and avoid my brain overheating.</p>

<p>When it was getting really quite bad, on got a preacher who started screaming
stuff about jesus at the top of his voice right beside me. I considered
trying to tell him to stop but realised that arguing with a mad man would just
encourage him. Interestingly the driver seemed to allow this. I was also
concerned that if I said anything the rest of the bus would lynch me for being
an evil atheist. I told myself that the kind of malaria you get around here is
not fatal, but I was concerned about it anyway. I considered asking the
preacher for the last rites - that would probably get him to shut up. In the
end I realised I had some earplugs to hand, so fitted them to some
improvement.</p>

<p>It would be a reasonable way to die anyway. A jungle in some exotic country
seems a respectable death for a British gentleman explorer.</p>

<p>We stopped at petrol station. Here some men threw buckets of water over the
bus and washed it, while some others stood around with guns. I was soon to
discover Guatemalans like standing around with guns. I wasn't happy about the
lack of sense of urgency to reach our destination.</p>

<p>Finally we got to somewhere urban, near our destination. It was crazily busy,
with Tuk-Tuks, other vehicles and people. People getting on the bus to sell
refrescos and snacks. When we got going again it wasn't too far to the hospital.</p>

<p>I had asked about a doctor initially but later asked them to drop me at the
hospital. I thought they would actually take me there, but they dumped me on
the other side of the road a few hundred meters away. I felt very weak and
probably couldn't think properly, but out of necessity I managed to load up my
bike and push it across the road without being run over.</p>

<p>There was a kind man at the reception who took me to the emergency department,
with my bike. They wanted to register me with my passport, but otherwise no
paperwork, and treatment was free. I had to speak to several doctors before
they decided someone knew enough English to understand. I tried Spanish first
but apparently they were not happy with that.</p>

<p>They took blood and urine samples. I was severely dehydrated so I was given
two bags of saline i.v. and some drug I can't remember to reduce fever and
pain. The tests for malaria and dengue were negative, but I might have had
some infection. I think the main problem was that I didn't eat and drink
enough.</p>

<p>I watched a bit of Marc Beaumont's Americas film before I left San Cris. It
said he has to eat six meals a day. I laughed at that because there is no way
I was eating that much. On the road through the forest mostly there was just
biscuits and sugar drinks. Usually shops also had some rice and tuna, and
occasionally some veg., but generally it was very difficult to eat
properly. Anyway, it turns out if you go cycling in 35C, midday sun and don't
eat and drink properly, you end up in hospital.</p>

<p>I have now been recovering for a few days in an hotel and now a hostel in
Flores. I couldn't eat for the first couple of days but I had some
smoothies. I'm pretty much recovered now and enjoying the food at Los Amigos
hostel, which includes tofu and vegetable curry - possibly the only place in
the country (except maybe Antigua) to have such things.</p>

<p>I think I'll go and check out the warm showers place near here, clean the
bike, and head to Belize in a few days maybe.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8696706948/" title="DSCF4210 by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8396/8696706948_209dc5e844_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="DSCF4210"></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8695285843/" title="DSCF4201 by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8535/8695285843_69d392516c_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="DSCF4201"></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8696405860/" title="DSCF4199 by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8399/8696405860_486a234a45_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="DSCF4199"></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8696705644/" title="DSCF4208 by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8114/8696705644_c7e56dac62_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="DSCF4208"></a></p>
]]></content>
   <georss:point>16.913470 -89.912978</georss:point>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Some Recent Karma]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/03/29/Recent-Karma.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/03/29/Recent-Karma.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2013-03-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/03/29/Recent-Karma</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I very rarely lose things, but recently I lost a cooking pot, by proxy. I lent
it to someone. The last thing I remember losing before that was a lighter. The
lighter I was given by someone at a house I stayed in, and it was lost when I
lent it to someone in another house.</p>

<p>The lost pot I bought, but then I remembered when I was on La Palma, I had
acquired a pot after a party, because I needed one to go walking in the
mountains. People told me it would be ok to take one if I asked around and
checked it did not belong to anyone in particular. I think it came from the
communal equipment collection at the nearby cave community, where many of the
people were Rainbow. I think my pot was taken by someone when it was left
lying around at the Oaxaca Rainbow gathering.</p>

<p>I started to wonder if I was going to lose the spoon I got on La Palma too,
but then I remembered I had given a KFS to someone at the Palenque Rainbow, so
it is probably safe. :)</p>

<p>Property seems to flow more when travelling. Property and people.</p>

<p>When I set off on this cycling journey I left a girl in Edinburgh. This
morning a girl left me to travel south.</p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Babylon by Bus]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/03/18/Babylon-by-Bus.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/03/18/Babylon-by-Bus.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2013-03-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/03/18/Babylon-by-Bus</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When it came time to leave the Oaxaca Rainbow Gathering, we were offered a
lift up the road. This turned out to be in an orange VW Bus called Gail, with
a figurehead of a ginger woman painted on the spare wheel.</p>

<p>We were given a joining briefing. She runs on gas, oil and love. Normally she
has a driver, driver's assistant, navigator, and band who sit in the back. She
was certainly well used, and I can see that she really must be held together
with love, as the string may not otherwise have been strong enough. I can see
how you can love a bus like this. My dreads kept getting caught in something
on the roof. Maybe she wanted a lock of my hair. :)</p>

<p>As we went up the sandy road through the coconut palms a man told a travel
horror story, over the considerable noise of the engine.</p>

<p>We made it to the main road, and after saying hello to some people on another
bus, returned to Babylon on a bus where we had to pay a fare.</p>

<p>We arrived at Salina Cruz, and I went a bit mad. At the Rainbow I was eating
healthily, vegan food, no sugar or caffeine. Now there were bright lights,
food and smells. I thought I smelt popcorn. It was esquites - corn. I bought a
cup. Then I wanted to try everything I saw - ice cream, burgers, tortas,
coffee. I ate churros next, which are similar to donuts but shaped like a star
prism. I also drank coffee and ate a cheese torta which was recommended by a
local. I felt very strange and didn't stop talking until asleep on the bus
home to San Cristobal.</p>

<p>I would like to travel by hippie bus one day.</p>
]]></content>
   <georss:point>15.970548 -95.621588</georss:point>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Wind and Fire]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/03/17/Wind-and-Fire.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/03/17/Wind-and-Fire.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2013-03-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/03/17/Wind-and-Fire</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I could feel something today. Some energy in the air, like something was going
to happen. Everyone could feel it. The wind was building and shaking the
trees. It had been building for days.</p>

<p>The wind drove us to eat in a huddle in the camp, sensibly breaking the
protocol of eating in the exposed, sandblasted, main circle. It felt like a
tribe coming together in the face of adversity. It was. The wind blew all
night and bounced my hammock.</p>

<p>The next morning, I broke up with my girlfriend. We were sitting in camp. As I
was talking, something hit me in the back. A girl sat up in my hammock. My now
ex-gf left to make her own camp, and I talked to my friend.</p>

<p>She was sleeping there, she told me, on account of being very tired from the
previous night's activity. She had sex with a guy she liked, and the girl he
was with. She felt very free now. Free from jealousy, ego and social
limits. It sounds like it was a very liberating experience, and a cleansing
from the past. Past problems blown away with the wind.</p>

<p>Later, I was dwelling on the past. As I was thinking about what went wrong
with the gf, ruminating, a pan whacked me on the head. Stop it! Be present
now! The wind had blown it from the tree.</p>

<p>That night, there was an orange glow in the distance. With the wind coming
from there, it was not long before it brought the fire to the camp. Everyone
was driven out. Anything left behind was burnt. Many people lost things,
attachments maybe, and many moved on that morning.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8543751136/" title="DSCF3623 by
mm0hai, on Flickr"><img
src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8522/8543751136_b140416fd0_z.jpg"
width="640" height="480" alt="DSCF3623"></a></p>
]]></content>
   <georss:point>15.927404 -95.632076</georss:point>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Oaxaca Healing Rainbow]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/03/16/Oaxaca-Healing-Rainbow-Gathering.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/03/16/Oaxaca-Healing-Rainbow-Gathering.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2013-03-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/03/16/Oaxaca-Healing-Rainbow-Gathering</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8542647331/" title="Rainbow
Welcome by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img
src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8087/8542647331_1bf5f02ec0_z.jpg"
width="640" height="481" alt="Rainbow Welcome"></a></p>

<p>Somewhere over the rainbow, I found a coconut palm beach. Tropical, on the
pacific coast, warm sea and freshwater lagoon, plentiful coconuts and mangoes,
and rainbows living there.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8546100414/" title="DSCF3667 by
mm0hai, on Flickr"><img
src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8105/8546100414_b26a1edde2_z.jpg"
width="640" height="480" alt="DSCF3667"></a></p>

<p>This was a Healing Rainbow Gathering. This meant that there was no smoking,
alcohol, sugar or caffeine. The food was not all raw, but that was an option,
and it was of course all vegan. The gathering felt happier, calmer and more
relaxed than Palenque. There were far fewer people, and they were not coming
and going all the time.</p>

<p>I stayed there for a week. Meditating, reading, drinking tea, eating coconut,
swimming, and I learnt something about energy healing.</p>

<p>Whenever I used to hear people talk of healing, I did not know what they
meant. People do all sorts of things for healing: energy healing, music
therapy, laughter therapy and diets such as raw food, for example. I didn't
understand this because I thought healing is something you do or need if you
are injured or ill. I did not think I needed to be healed.</p>

<p>However, I came to realise that there are things that can be improved, and
what is taken to be normal is a far worse state than it should be. Many people
are not happy. They argue and fight and do not feel good about life. There is
something wrong which can be fixed. I think it is this sort of thing that
people mean when they talk of healing. I asked someone what it meant, and he
said something about increasing your vibrational frequency. I'm not sure what
that means though.</p>

<p>Someone ran an energy healing workshop. I didn't know what this was, but I
thought I might as well go and try it. The technique was to try and reach a
state of mind without ego, and then allow energy, or qi, or the great spirit,
or whatever you want to call it, to guide your hands over the patient. I think
the idea was to guide energy to flow in some way such as to heal. He explained
that you were not really doing anything, and were more like a conduit.</p>

<p>I tried it. I could feel, or imagined I could feel - it is hard to tell -
something when I held my hands over someone. I didn't think too much about
what I was doing. Asking her, it seems that there was no effect on my patient,
but the experience certainly left me feeling different. I attained a very
relaxed, meditative state of presence which lasted for some time afterwards. I
didn't feel much when I was worked on.</p>

<p>A couple of people I have spoken to about things like this have spoken of
intention. The idea is that what you do does not really matter, what matters
is your intention, and what you give your attention to. He spoke of putting
his hand on an injury, and focusing on it with an intention to heal. I would
guess that things like this have a strong placebo effect in credulous patients
and could indeed make people feel better. Ultimately the purpose of medicine is
to make people feel better, so you could say that this is useful, even if it
does not physically do anything.</p>

<p>Another interesting thing about this gathering was that I did not get ill. I
was eating some raw food prepared by innumerable dirty hippies who were not
washing their hands with soap, and probably some where not washing hands at
all. I felt healthy the whole time. Since I have been back in civilisation I
have had soft stools and been farting a lot, and generally not feeling as
good. I have not been sleeping as well either. Artificial food and light
really do seem to be bad for me. Maybe it is the tap water here which I
consume in small quantities from things like washed vegetables and tooth
brushing. At the rainbow though I drank well water and accidentally swallowed
some from the laguna than many birds swam in, and I did not get ill.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8544851505/" title="DSCF3658 by
mm0hai, on Flickr"><img
src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8235/8544851505_f9b04fae13_z.jpg"
width="640" height="480" alt="DSCF3658"></a></p>

<p>I was also introduced to coconut cheese. Some people discovered that some old
coconuts taste like gorgonzola. The texture is similar to cheese as well. This
was considered a delicacy, but I was a bit suspicious of it. It could be
marketed as a vegan cheese replacement, and I am surprised it has not been
already, as it is very good.</p>

<p>I slept in my hammock most of the time. I slept well. It turns out thought that
it was not very comfortable for two, because there was no space to move.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8544856681/" title="DD Frontline
Hammock by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img
src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8086/8544856681_e83c8aa46c_z.jpg"
width="640" height="480" alt="DD Frontline Hammock"></a></p>

<p>Overall, I enjoyed this gathering. I was much happier than at the Palenque
one, and I learnt some things. It was good to be by the sea after so long in
the mountains.</p>

<p>There was some excitement at the end of the gathering too. I'll write about
that in a further blov post.</p>
]]></content>
   <georss:point>15.927404 -95.632067</georss:point>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[<span title="My hobby: asking for Buddhist temples in German. If they don't understand then I try Chinese">gibt es einen buddhistischen Tempel in der Nähe?</span>]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/03/07/Buddhist.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/03/07/Buddhist.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2013-03-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/03/07/Buddhist</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8549721861/" title="San Cristobal NKT Buddhist Centre by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8391/8549721861_29da425226_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="San Cristobal NKT Buddhist Centre"></a></p>

<p>I noticed this Buddhist centre when I first came to San Cristobal. I am now
living very close to it so there was no excuse not to have a look. They have a
"guided meditation" each day at 10am. On Thursday I went to it.</p>

<p>The main room or hall of the centre had a shrine at the end, with cushions on
the floor at the front and some seats in rows behind them. The shrine had
golden Buddhas and Bodhisattvas, 3 sets of 7 water bowls, a chocolate bar at
the right side, and various other things. On the wall behind the central
Buddha was a portrait of Kelsang Gyatso. Another, lager, portrait of him sat
in front of the Buddha. The way it was displayed reminded me of pictures of
Saddam Hussein in Iraq.</p>

<p>The session was not what I was expecting. The type of meditation I have
encountered before is about presence, silently concentrating on the senses and
body. This was mostly chanting with a few shorter periods of silence to
contemplate what was said.</p>

<p>It was surprisingly like a christian church service. There was the equivalent
of a hymn book for the chants or songs, and it followed a set program from the
book. The main difference was there were some periods of silence to
contemplate. I'm afraid it also felt rather like church - something you go to
because you are required to for some reason but you don't actually feel
anything or get the point. The order of service if you can call it that was
from a book by the founder of this type of Buddhism. I read the book
afterwards in a couple of hours and then researched it more on the web.</p>

<p>I discovered that this place was of the New Kadampa Tradition (NKT), founded
by Geshe Kelsang Gyatso in England in 1991 and now based in the Lake
District. This form of Buddhism seems to be somewhat controversial, and has
some aspects I do not like and which are somewhat suggestive of a cult. It
seems people are taught only to read the books by Kelsang Gyatso, and I
noticed in the centre all the books were by him.</p>

<p>The only book that did not have his name on the cover was by the Western
Shugden Society, which seems to be mostly run by Kadampa Buddhists. The
worship of Shugden seems to be a controversial issue. The Dalai Lama banned
it, but Kelsang Gyatso supported it.</p>

<p>I also found a story about a monk being financially exploited, and there are
websites for "recoverers". I don't know if these indicate systematic problems,
but the fact that there is an official <a
href="http://www.newkadampatruth.org">site</a> which tries to defend against
various accusations does not look good.</p>

<h2>The Teachings</h2>

<p>In any case, it does not matter what the organisation is like unless the
teachings are good. Kelsang Gyatso seems to be distinguished by designing a
clearly organised 21 step meditation plan, or lamrim in Tibetan, which I read
in one of his books.</p>

<p>Many of the steps seem like a good idea, but there were a few I really didn't
like, which I will point out below. This post may seem rather negative because
of this, and admittedly I was looking for problems. I think this is important
though, because I do not want to spend a lot of time on something if there are
basic problems with it. I don't know how much of this is specific to NKT and
how much is common to other Buddhist traditions.</p>

<h3>Fear</h3>

<p>The first point is entitled "Our precious human life" but in reality it is
designed to instil fear!</p>

<blockquote><p>"This feeling of fear is the object of our meditation. We then hold this
without forgetting it; our mind should remain on this feeling of fear
single-pointedly for as long as possible."</p></blockquote>

<p>The fear he is talking about is that of a lower rebirth. I should explain
samsara - the idea that we are trapped in a continuous cycle of death and
rebirth. This is common to many religions. Birth can be in any of six realms -
God, demi-god, human, animal, hungry ghost, and hell. Buddhas have escaped
from this cycle, and the idea is that by following the lamrim, you can achieve
this.</p>

<p>Christian Heaven and Hell seems like a special case of samsara where the
number of births is exactly two, or possibly three if purgatory counts as
one. Churches use fear of hell as a method of controlling people. It seems
here that fear of lower rebirth is being used to convince people to follow this
path.</p>

<p>I don't like this idea of instilling fear because it is not something
inherently good and it can be abused to control people. Is it really necessary
to invent something for people to fear? Are there not enough problems readily
apparent that we can fix? I can certainly see things in my life which I could
improve with some Buddhist teachings without having to fear hell. Rather than
creating fear, then running to Buddha and your guru ("taking refuge"), don't
unnecessarily create fear to start with. You can still learn, reduce existing
fear, and love.</p>

<p>All of this assumes that samsara exists. I tried searching for evidence of
this, or even where this idea came from, but I didn't find anything convincing
enough to base my life on it. Perhaps this is the religious part of Buddhism -
something you are just required to believe without evidence.</p>

<p>I found this on <a href="http://typing-sound.livejournal.com/63084.html">someones livejournal</a></p>

<blockquote><p>"Getting back to the NKT, I would advise anyone reading this to stay well
  away from it. If you don't and they get you inside, you will find yourself
  locked in beliefs and fear. You will be overloaded with practices and
  commitments prematurely, and then you will be afraid not to do them for fear
  of hell. Once you're deeply submerged in the NKT, it is very difficult to
  get out again, because in a way you get brainwashed."</p></blockquote>

<h3>Death</h3>

<p>Gyatso would also have you meditate on death.</p>

<blockquote><p>"I shall definitely die. There is no way to prevent my body from finally
decaying."</p></blockquote>

<p>This seems negative and may cause fear. Some people argue it is not even true
that you must die. Maybe it won't if you don't believe it, or if you become
more than a normal human. Again there is a more positive alternative. Instead
of saying I must work hard because I will die soon, think, I will work hard to
improve my life now. This works whether you believe in rebirth or not.</p>

<h3>Gurus</h3>

<p>He claims that it is necessary to have a spiritual teacher - it is the only
way. I won't say that it is not helpful to have a teacher, but I object to the
idea that it is absolutely necessary. Where did these teachers get their
knowledge from? It must be discoverable. The Buddha did not have a Dharma
teacher. Yes, he probably had several teachers he learned from, but he moved
between them and thought for himself to develop his ideas. He did not swear
loyalty to one guru who told him never to read the books of someone else.</p>

<p>I read that some schools practice guru yoga or worship, basically treating a
guru as a god. This doesn't seem like a good idea to me at all.</p>

<p>They also seem a bit obsessed about the lineage of teachers - students
becoming teachers and continuing the line. I think they see this line leading
back to Buddha as something to establish their legitimacy.</p>

<p>From the same livejournal post quoted above:</p>

<blockquote><p>"I did learn a valuable lesson from it all, which was not to believe
  anything that didn't depend upon experience, otherwise you get trapped in
  fear. And I learned to be self-reliant, not reliant on some Guru without
  thinking for myself."</p></blockquote>

<h3>Absolute statements</h3>

<p>The book is filled with definite statements which are clearly not true. For
example, that following this lamrim is the only way to give your life
meaning. It is obvious that I can do many valuable things without practising
Buddhism. The requirement for a guru is another example.</p>

<blockquote><p>"We need to practise Buddha’s teachings because there is no other real method
to solve human problems." - Geshe Kelsang Gyatso, "Modern Buddhism".</p></blockquote>

<p>Obviously this is not true either.</p>

<h3>Positive Teachings</h3>

<p>On the positive side, the rest of the steps of this lamrim may be good ideas,
although I have not read about all of them in enough detail. They include
loving everyone equally, believing in the kindness and love of others,
avoiding attachment, compassion and cherishing others rather than
yourself.</p>

<h2>Money</h2>

<p>They seem to be partly a way to sell "Buddhist Holidays". The retreats they
are selling in Mexico are about 100 GBP a day. For comparison I pay about 75
GBP a month in rent for rooms here.</p>

<p>The lama said we were invited to a lesson. I went. Afterwards I was asked for
money, "only if I had it", but they asked several times. I didn't want to pay
for something I thought was free.</p>

<h2>Conclusions</h2>

<p>Unless there is good evidence for some pain after death it does not make sense
change your behaviour because of this. Focus on fixing real problems you have
now.</p>

<p>One needs to be very careful in choosing gurus.</p>

<p>Whatever the nature of the teachings or philosophy, there is a great risk of
corruption and exploitation when a large organisation is created around
it. Good people can be corrupted. The power a guru can have over his students
can also attract people who intend to abuse that power.</p>

<p>There are a great variety of practices and beliefs within Buddhism. You need
to research the specific teachings of different teachers rather than rely on a
simple label like Buddhist or Kadampa.</p>

<p>I should research other forms of Buddhism to see if there is one with less
religion, power and fear, and more useful lessons for living this life.</p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[San Cristobal de las Casas]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/01/11/San-Cristobal-de-las-Casas.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/01/11/San-Cristobal-de-las-Casas.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2013-01-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/01/11/San-Cristobal-de-las-Casas</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img
src="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/9/9a/Flag_of_the_EZLN.svg"
width="640" alt="EZLN Flag"/></p>

<p>The streets smell of roasting coffee, grown by the coöps in the surrounding
hills. I also smell chocolate and bread from the panaderias. There are punks
on bikes - real bikes, not rusting Mexican style ones. Restaurants advertise
vegetarian and vegan food. Colourful gnomes and greyed hippies sit in the
streets.</p>

<p>There are anarchist and squatting symbols painted on the walls. If you wear an
anarchist patch in Edinburgh it is ignored. Here, the town was actually
captured by rebels. I don't think it would be a good idea to cycle past the
army base they built down the road on my own with Zapatista colours. There are
armed police and soldiers around, which is a nice reminder of what is
possible. The government is wary.</p>

<p>There are at least two places here devoted to permaculture, with a vegan
community. Until recently there was a community bike workshop.</p>

<p>I wandered into the yard of some casa, following the sound of a woman singing
reggae. There was a guy contact juggling, and silks hanging from a frame. The
smoke was the pleasant smelling kind - not tobacco. A menu on the wall listed
hummus and verduras.</p>

<p>I wandered on aimlessly, and reached a cafe. Now I'm drinking tea that tastes
of the earth where it came from.</p>

<p>Mexico is sick and makes me feel sick. The world is sick. San Cristobal is a
hill station for the recovery of humanity.</p>
]]></content>
   <georss:point>16.7385777 -92.6332806</georss:point>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Getting into the Bathtub]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/01/09/Getting-into-the-Bathtub.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/01/09/Getting-into-the-Bathtub.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2013-01-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/01/09/Getting-into-the-Bathtub</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>My touring bike and gear had either very little or in some cases no testing at
all before leaving. I had replaced most of the bike, including rebuilding the
wheels with new rims, cones and ball bearings. The panniers were all brand
new. The ærobars and bar ends were new. The solar panel mounting was tested
only lightly around Edinburgh. Now I was on tour.</p>

<p>In engineering, there is something called a <a
href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bathtub_curve">bathtub curve</a>. This
shows the general shape of the probability of failures of many systems over
time. A new system might fail from manufacturing defects and an old one from
wearing out. In between, the chance of failure is lower. This curve looks like
a bathtub.</p>

<p><img
src="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/7/78/Bathtub_curve.svg"
width="640" alt="Bathtub curve" ></p>

<p>There was so much new on the bike that I knew I was not in the bath yet, and
was almost expecting things to fail. They did.</p>

<p>First my solar panel rack broke. I was worried it might on the Rainbow Road -
an awful, bumpy, rough track. 30km or so did it. The front tube broke where it
touched the carrier rack. The point at the rear where the tube was over bent,
that I was concerned about before I left, also broke. I needed to get this
fixed before I could cycle further. It did keep the panel on the bike like
this, but without fixing it would probably totally fail soon. Getting it
repaired is a story for another post.</p>

<p>The other problem I had was the front wheel started to make a nasty noise. I
found that something in the hub was catching when it rotated. When I left, the
balls were new and the cones were recycled but only had one very minor pit in
the track. The cups are built into the hub and had some wear but did not look
too bad. I found someone at the Rainbow Gathering who had cone spanners and we
had a look inside. The cones still looked good and the grease was clean. We
didn't take the balls out though or would inevitably have lost them in the
forest. He did not know what was wrong either, but took out one ball from each
side, so the hub now had 9 per side. I am sure it had 10 before I rebuilt it,
but the problem has now stopped, so I'm leaving it like that.</p>

<p>I found my headset was loose. I didn't use a headset press when I fitted it -
only a hammer - so maybe the bumpy road pushed the races in further. This was
easily tightened by borrowing a large adjustable spanner from a local bike
shop. I don't think they had a proper headset spanner so I couldn't hold the
bearing for exact adjustment as I tightened the locknut. It's probably
slightly overtight now but I decided to leave it as good enough for a change
rather than spending all day tweaking. It was a cheap headset anyway so I'll
probably have to replace it soon.</p>

<p>I've also been moving my saddle. I've mostly been using the ærobars and so I
have a different riding position. The saddle is a Brooks I've had for some
time, but it has not been used on a tour before. It's breaking in much faster
than at home, probably because of the heat and humidity.</p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[PEMEX]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/01/07/PEMEX.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/01/07/PEMEX.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2013-01-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/01/07/PEMEX</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8387837666/" title="PEMEX"><img
src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8361/8387837666_ed618aa2b2_z.jpg"
width="640" height="480" alt="PEMEX Station"></a></p>

<p>Before I really started cycling here in Mexico, a couple of people told me
they camped and hammocked at PEMEX, the only brand of petrol station I have
seen so far in Mexico. I thought that sounded a bit crazy but that is because
I had only toured in Europe before.</p>

<p>In Europe, I found I could camp almost anywhere by the side of the road. There
might be a forest, or a field, a picnic spot, a public park or even a
campsite. Here the roads I have seen so far are lined by ditches and fences
unbroken for miles. The slopes to the ditches are often very steep, the
ditches quite wide and full of water and then there is a barbed wire fence on
the other side. Getting the bike across this would be very difficult. Getting
self over would be possible, but would involve getting wet, muddy, and
possibly injured. There are venomous snakes around here, ticks and maybe
leeches. It generally is not something I want to do.</p>

<p>Last night I found a small space between the road and the water. I stopped
there because I saw some flatter ground. I was not the first to notice it
though - there was an old camp fire, and lots of rubbish. I moved down from
the road a bit for cover from sight. I thought it would be better not to be
seen because that was my only defence against robbers. Down here though was
where people had been using as a toilet and rubbish dump.</p>

<p>In the morning I had to get the bike back up the slope, which was not
easy. Then I spent probably spent half an hour stopping and trying to work out
what was making a scraping noise as the wheels turned. Eventually I found a
piece of wire stuck in the back tyre was scraping on the inside of the
mudgaurd. This and the sticks that jammed in the gears are more reasons to
avoid these sites.</p>

<p>If you want a flat site with short grass (to avoid snakes) it seems like the
only option usually is to ask at someones house to camp in the garden. This
can be quite successful - I did this the night before and was also given a
meal. Some people at the Rainbow told me they had done this and it happened to
be the occasion of the Granny's 101st birthday. A pig was slaughtered for them
and they were basically forced to stay for two days eating and drinking.</p>

<p>The other option though is a petrol station. Now that I have seen one it makes
sense. I'm camping now on a large area of flat, short grass, about 20 meters
from the hardstanding. I can see my bike locked near the pumps, lit and under
cover from rain. There is a toilet, sink for washing, food and water right
outside. There is also a useful amount of light but not so much as to stop
sleep.</p>

<p>In Europe, I would avoid a petrol station as noisy and possibly dangerous and
camp somewhere quiet. I also think of them as expensive and of course
supporting an oil based system. But now I look out of the tent and the PEMEX
sign is like a marker of an oasis. This and the glowing traffic cone landing
lights, are beautiful.</p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Bike is Important]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/01/05/The-Bike-is-Important.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/01/05/The-Bike-is-Important.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2013-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/01/05/The-Bike-is-Important</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I don't think you understand how important this is. This is not a toy or for
going to the shops. This is for tens of thousands of miles of dirt roads,
jungles, deserts and mountains. This is my home for years. For the majority
of people I meet for the next few years, this is all they will remember of
me. You did this like you had no time for better, then spent the rest of the
day standing around doing nothing.</p>

<p>This morning I started to cry. I put on Runrig, "Road and the River", which
triggered it, although I almost felt like crying when I saw your work
yesterday. I should have insisted you do it better. I didn't negotiate the
price down because I wanted you to be interested enough in it to do a good
job. Apparently that didn't work. The only reason I let you continue and paid
you is because I couldn't move without it. Something that might last a few
hundred miles would at least let me escape this place now. The one thing that
was good about this work was that it was done by 3pm the day it started.</p>

<p>Now I am sitting right next to a freedom machine but still feel trapped. I
don't know if I can cycle because of illness. If I do I'll probably get wet
when my tent leaks again. If I want better gear I will need to wait for it to
be delivered here - I think there is no chance of buying something that is not
rubbish here. That means waiting somewhere - again I am trapped. All the time
I can't even eat anything that is not poison, so it's not surprising I have
been ill for nearly two weeks. The current cold that is, not diarrhoea and
vomiting immediately preceding. And it will probably take days to choose things
and order them on the internet, and most of the days will be wasted trying to
find working wifi.</p>

<p>I am thinking too much. I can get out of an hotel room in the morning without
thinking - I have done this before. I am going to cycle, kit be dammed. I am
going to ride my bike today whether I have a map and a waterproof tent or not.</p>

<p>Now I feel better. I'm going to have breakfast.</p>
]]></content>
   <georss:point>17.510204 -91.98104</georss:point>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Finally Moving]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/01/05/Finally-Moving.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/01/05/Finally-Moving.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2013-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/01/05/Finally-Moving</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I spent over two weeks at the Rainbow Gathering, then a couple of days in
Palenque getting my solar rack fixed. Before that I had been in hostels
working on computer related stuff, so apart from the road to the Rainbow I had
cycled very little. I was starting to get frustrated and feeling trapped by my
gear, admin and thoughts.</p>

<p>The bike was so far mostly a burden and extra expense on busses. It had already
needed repair work. I had almost forgotten what it was for, and felt I could
not move. I didn't know whether to go on to Merida, then across to Chichen
Itza and Tulum as planned, to head straight over to Chetumal and Belize, or to
go to San Cristobal de las Casas, which I had heard was a bike and vegan
friendly town. I was thinking and not moving.</p>

<p>Suddenly I realised I was right beside a freedom machine. I resolved I was
going to cycle today no matter what. Without a map, without doing a better job
of the solar rack or testing it, without any more gear, and without a well
considered decision about where to go. I just had to move.</p>

<p>I started cycling and it worked. I felt better as soon as I was rolling.</p>
]]></content>
   <georss:point>17.510204 -91.98104</georss:point>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Palenque Rainbow Gathering]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/01/03/Palenque-Rainbow-Gathering.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/01/03/Palenque-Rainbow-Gathering.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2013-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/01/03/Palenque-Rainbow-Gathering</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I spent the last two weeks at the Palenque Rainbow Gathering. Unfortunately I
didn't enjoy it very much. There were times I did - the few days I was not ill
I enjoyed swimming and slacklining over the river. Most of the time though I
was ill with various ailments. I suspect I had Giardia from the river, and
then a cold. Sanitation is difficult with so many people living in a temporary
camp.</p>

<p>Some amusing moments though included going for a night out at the theatre, in
the forest, singing and listening to music, and a music therapy session. I
also tried to fix Mykal's dynamo to USB voltage regulator, but I didn't have
any gas for my soldering iron.</p>

<p>I spent some time asking people about hammocks and trying some out,
because I was thinking of replacing my tent with one. I had to get something
new anyway, because I found my tent now leaks badly and is not a comfortable
home.</p>

<p>One day I went for a walk up the road to a wee village. It was the first time
I felt I was seeing Mexico. There were horses on the road and it generally
felt rural and like it was really Mexico, not just another town.</p>

<p>I visited the Mayan ruins one day as well. I didn't enjoy it much though
because I was generally in a bad mood at least partly because of illness, and
because it was so hot I found it tiring to walk. I also didn't like how there
were so many people trying to sell things.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8362733937/" title="DSCF3053 by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8080/8362733937_29a136bb45_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="DSCF3053"></a></p>

<p>I learnt something about how palm oil is produced. The gathering was in a palm
plantation, and one day some people came round with a donkey to harvest the
nuts from which oil is extracted.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8362701093/" title="DSCF3024 by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8378/8362701093_2e4e3d9fb6_z.jpg" width="480" height="640" alt="DSCF3024"></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8362703347/" title="DSCF3025 by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8186/8362703347_7b85d7f92f_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="DSCF3025"></a></p>

<p>I had a couple of quite special experiences. One evening I participated in an
Angel Walk. Another day I had a good experience when I decided to stop thinking
and follow my feelings, which led to an interesting result. I might write
about these later.</p>
]]></content>
   <georss:point>17.483017 -91.925139</georss:point>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Intimate Shitting]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/23/Intimite-Shitting.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/23/Intimite-Shitting.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2012-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/23/Intimite-Shitting</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<!--- date approximate -->


<p>Someone told me one special Rainbow experience I had to have was sharing a
shit pit. She said if you haven't been elbow to elbow with someone on the next
trench then you don't know them, or something like that.</p>

<p>Ten minutes later I was using the shit pit and someone came along and asked if
he could join me, so I said yes. Of everyone this could have been, he was a
nurse, and apart, therefore, from being an expert on shit, he seemed to have a
particular interest.</p>

<p>Unprovoked, he explained his ideas. He thought illness could be a beautiful
thing because an inability to do things yourself such as wiping your bum means
you must become closer to other people. He thought illnesses were for a
reason, and must teach you something or have some benefit.</p>

<p>Another nurse I spoke to said she hated wiping bums. She quit to go
travelling.</p>

<p>I'm afraid I didn't take a photo for this post.</p>
]]></content>
   <georss:point>17.483017 -91.925139</georss:point>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Gods]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/22/Gods.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/22/Gods.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2012-12-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/22/Gods</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I don't believe in any gods, and think religion is dangerous and very
harmful. The Rainbow Gathering had a good selection of them though. There were
temples for Hare Krishna, Shiva, and even a few Jesuses and Marys around. This
flippant attitude changed though, at the End of the World.</p>

<p>When everything is wet, it feels like it will never stop raining, you are
vomiting and the jungle is trying to eat you, Gods seem to come back. I like
sacred songs whatever I think of the content. In the dark I prayed to the rain
to stop, and apologised to Krishna for singing but not believing.</p>

<p>A Christian minister once told me, when questioned, that praying is something
people do because it is all they can do. Find a real way to control the
environment and prayer is useless.</p>

<p>Gods aren't disappearing directly because of science taking over as a method
of understanding the world, they are disappearing because there is less
suffering. Modern life gives more comfort and less disease. With control of
your environment, waterproof roofs, heating, and factory farming, there is no
desperation, and no need for gods of rain and corn.</p>
]]></content>
   <georss:point>17.483017 -91.925139</georss:point>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Great Flood and a Rainbow]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/21/End-of-the-World.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/21/End-of-the-World.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2012-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/21/End-of-the-World</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One reason I left on <a href="/blog/tag/cyclewho/">this trip</a> before I was
ready was to get to Palenque in time for the end of the world. There is a
Mayan prophecy about the end of an era of Babylon, the broken world, and the
transformation to a new world where people live consciously. I made it to the
Rainbow Gathering near Palenque a few days before the 21st.</p>

<p>The 21st of December 2012 was to be the end of the world. In the morning there
was going to be a ceremony at the Palenque ruins. Before that, a global
meditation at 0411, I think it was. That is not a time when I would find it
easy to get up. Someone suggested going to sleep at the main circle so I might
wake up, so I went out there with my bivvy bag.</p>

<p>I lay down to sleep, and it started to rain. I was not concerned about this,
because I had previously tested this bivvy bag up a hill in Scotland when it
rained all night and I remained dry, so I tried to go to sleep.</p>

<p>The rain started to become very heavy. I could feel the lumps of water
whacking into me. I started to get wet. I don't think it was coming in the
opening - probably it was so hard it was forced through the material. I stayed
for a while anyway hoping it would stop, but after maybe half an hour it was
still raining heavily.</p>

<p>The drummers had left and the previously strong fire had been extinguished by
the rain. I was now on my own in the dark, getting cold in the heaviest rain I
had every seen, which showed no sign of stopping. I started to wonder if this
was the end. If you want to clean the world ready for a new one rain might be
a good way to do it. It would not be the first time there had been a Great
Flood for something like this.</p>

<p>I decided to get up before I became hypothermic. I made it back to my camp on
the paths which were now mud rivers. My tent was still there, but full of
water. I slept in my damp sleeping bag and missed the morning ceremonies.</p>

<p>The world seemed the same in the morning, but then I realised that actually
anything could have happened. Maybe the rest outside the Rainbow had gone. I
would have to check it out later.</p>
]]></content>
   <georss:point>17.483017 -91.925139</georss:point>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Going to the Palenque Rainbow Gathering]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/18/To-the-Rainbow.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/18/To-the-Rainbow.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2012-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/18/To-the-Rainbow</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>When the earth is ravaged and the animals are dying, a new tribe of people
shall come unto the earth from many colors, classes, creeds, and who by
their actions and deeds shall make the earth green again. They will be known
as the warriors of the Rainbow.
-- Native American Prophecy, seen <a
href="http://www.welcomehome.org/rainbow/">here</a>.</p></blockquote>

<p>The Palenque Rainbow Gathering is one reason I came to Mexico now, to begin
cycling at the End of the World.</p>

<p>I arrived in Palenque by overnight bus, had breakfast and set off down the road.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8339829385/" title="Beginning of
the dirt road to the Rainbow by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img
src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8213/8339829385_0530a24c5b_z.jpg"
width="640" height="480" alt="Beginning of the dirt road to the Rainbow"></a></p>

<p>Leaving Palenque there was a short section of main road before reaching the
turnoff for the Rainbow. Then the road was awful. Very bumpy surface, rocks,
and it went up and down. My bike was heavily loaded and I was not particularly
fit. On the way up the road, though, I met a friend I last saw in Europe a
year ago, who was walking to town. :)</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8339845737/" title="DSCF3008 by
mm0hai, on Flickr"><img
src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8359/8339845737_314e8af703_z.jpg"
width="640" height="480" alt="DSCF3008"></a></p>

<p>Eventually I arrived, and one of the first things I did was go for a swim in
 the river pools.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8384100203/" title="DSCF3203 by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8189/8384100203_7f75dba767_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="DSCF3203"></a></p>

<p>I went for a walk around to explore and look for a campsite. On the way back
to get my bike and things I met three other cycle tourists who had just
arrived. <a href="http://chaingethecycle.org/">Mykal and Nico</a>, who were
cycling to Guatemala to help build an earth ship, and Lance, who was cycling
to Panama. We set up camp together. I stayed for the next two weeks.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8364983083/" title="DSCF3133 by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8055/8364983083_4131357bf4_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="DSCF3133"></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8366114804/" title="DSCF3146 by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8083/8366114804_cc0cd31ccb_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="DSCF3146"></a></p>
]]></content>
   <georss:point>17.510204 -91.98104</georss:point>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[First Test of Solar Charger]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/14/First-Test-of-Solar-Charger.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/14/First-Test-of-Solar-Charger.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2012-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/14/First-Test-of-Solar-Charger</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I designed and built a charger for Thinkpad batteries before I left, but there
was not enough sun in Scotland to test it properly. Today in Tulum I tried it
for real for the first time.</p>

<p>Tropical mid-day sun was sufficient. It charged the battery for a while. When
I tried a battery that was at a higher voltage, it did not charge it as
designed. The voltage cutoff was lower than I had set at home, but basically
it seems to work. I did not leave it long enough to see it cutoff when full
though. I also would like to measure the power supplied so I know how long
charging will let the computer run.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8272408443/" title="First test of
solar charger by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img
src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8352/8272408443_0390543aa4_z.jpg"
width="640" height="480" alt="First test of solar charger"></a></p>

<p>The charger is not mounted on the bike yet, so it's just sitting on top while
I measure voltages.</p>
]]></content>
   <georss:point>20.211944 -87.465833</georss:point>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Cancun]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/13/Cancun.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/13/Cancun.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2012-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/13/Cancun</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Cancun is a tourist resort. It's made of hotels. It doesn't seem quite as bad
as Maspalomas - there are some areas where people live, but it's still not
somewhere I would like to spend much time. It was hard to find any food that
would not make me feel sick. Maybe there are good parts but I felt I had to
get out of there before I went mad.</p>

<p>I took the bus, as crazyguyonabike blogs told me the only routes out were big
boring roads. Cycling to the bus was quite exciting - mostly busses and
collectivos on the dual carriageway. Large roundabouts and weird junctions I
had not seen before. The general idea seems to be to drive on the right but
overtaking is done on whichever side is convenient.</p>

<p>Putting the bike on the bus was trivial. Did not even need to remove
panniers. Far superior service to busses in the UK.</p>

<p>My bike felt like a bus. Total weight of bike and gear was 55kg when I left
Manchester. The ADO bus, when I was on it, rolled along with a similar
feeling.</p>
]]></content>
   <georss:point>21.164483 -86.828384</georss:point>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Fruit is not Allowed]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/12/Fruit-is-not-allowed.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/12/Fruit-is-not-allowed.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2012-12-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/12/Fruit-is-not-allowed</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>"Fruit is not allowed", the customs officer said dissaprovingly. This seems
true not only of imports, but generally in Cancun. There are plenty of small
shops but they pretty much just sell crisps and sugary drinks. I ate mostly
sugar and felt sick.</p>

<p>I quickly gave up on finding vegan food and tried for vegetarian. I ordered
some quesadillas after carefull study of the menu and dictionary, but still
got meat. I ate it anyway. I think not to would be adding insult to injury. I
wouldn't be very impressed if someone killed me for food and then decided to
throw me in the bin instead. I felt sick.</p>

<p>Tortilla vegetariano for breakfast, served with refried beans. Interesting,
but eggs and cheese. Felt a bit sick.</p>

<p>Then I found Walmart. Here fruit is allowed - it is quite overwhelming. It's
stacked high - it would crush you if it fell over - and is all perfect. Every
apple is shiny and without blemish, and lit by green light. They must be
genetically engineered, irradiated, and coated with insectiside. Nevertheless,
I imagine the scale of the place and quantity of food could make a hungy
person cry.</p>

<p>The last time I tried to use a McDonalds drive through (in Penrith (England))
they wouldn't let me. Here they did. McDonalds was a theme on my last cycle tour
I wanted to avoid this time, but it seem to have happened already. I wanted
food without having to leave my bike. I didn't want to try the street vendors
because I have plenty of things to do for the moment without being sick. I
tried to order a vegeburger but they didn't understand. It was not the
langugae, I tried Spanish and English, they did not understand the concept of
not eating meat. I ordered chicken and felt nothing. It tasted of nothing, was
probably mostly breadcrumbs. I need to get out of here.</p>

<p>My water bottle holder does not work well for coffee cups. There is another
gadget to rig up.</p>

<p>In Nigeria if there is no meat in a meal people will be unimpressed and think
you are poor. I suspect poor countries go through a phase of everyone wanting
meat as a sign of affluence. Maybe they will grow out of it.</p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[First day in Mexico]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/11/Mexico-First-Day.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/11/Mexico-First-Day.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2012-12-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/11/Mexico-First-Day</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Police truck with armed man standing in back. I can't imagine how this is a
useful strategy from a military perspective - he is far too exposed and would
be shot before he could do anything. I guess it is primarily security theatre
- an attempt to intimidate the people into doing what they are told.</p>

<p>Tried to find vegan food, settled for vegetarian. Ordered peas, got meat -
pork I think. Ate it - think throwing away would be adding serious insult to
injury.</p>

<p>Still hot at night - not like Canaries where temp drops with the sun.  Very
humid - outside like a warm sauna. Later noted condensation on the <em>outside</em>
of bus windows.</p>

<p>Could not find fruit - wee shops pretty much just sell crisps and fizzy
drinks. Contraband fruit taken at airport. Probably a sign of a troublesome
free thinker.</p>

<p>In Germany drinking tea means are ill, here you must be a hippie.</p>

<p>The Simpsons speak Spanish in Mexico.  Almost all TV dubbed. Probably when
English limited here, cf. Netherlands.</p>

<p>Being forced to remember / learn Spanish already. Maybe should take a course.
Many menu words not in Spanish dictionary. Mexican only terms maybe? Should
have bought Mexican Spanish book saw at airport.</p>

<p>Not seen many Mexicans yet.</p>

<p>I am hearing accents I have only heard before on American T.V. shows. I really
like the (American) Indian accent from them, which a hotel receptionist
has. It is reassuring, as if his knowledge about the location of Walmart is
something passed through generations of tribes.</p>

<p>First shop I found was an electronics one. I mean one which actually had
multimeters and components, not washing machines. They had isopropanol and
thermal paste. I wanted to do that job on Thinkpad before I left. Ha. You can
always buy stuff later.</p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Leaving Edinburgh]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/10/Leaving-Edinburgh-for-Mexico.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/10/Leaving-Edinburgh-for-Mexico.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2012-12-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/10/Leaving-Edinburgh-for-Mexico</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After far too long in Edinburgh I am finally moving. I decided that even if I
was not really ready yet I had to leave because the weather was getting quite
unpleasant in Scotland and if I did not just decide to leave would I ever
really be ready anyway? I had booked a flight to Cancun, Mexico about two
weeks ago but was still not ready. The photos below I took myself just before
cycling to the train station. I hadn't finished packing when it came time to
leave to catch the train so I had to throw things in without time to decide
what I really needed. It was the first time I had ridden the bike loaded with
the new panniers and all gear.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8340847482/" title="Leaving by
mm0hai, on Flickr"><img
src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8072/8340847482_4f02f7752a_z.jpg"
width="480" height="640" alt="Leaving"></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8340848528/" title="Leaving by
mm0hai, on Flickr"><img
src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8498/8340848528_82c8c559b5_z.jpg"
width="640" height="480" alt="Leaving"></a></p>

<p>The handling with front panniers is very different. It felt like I had a flat
tyre, I think because of the weight compressing the tyre and giving more
friction on the ground. I cycled slowly and hoped nothing was going to break.</p>

<p>I got to the platform just as the train was about to leave. Someone told me I
would not make it but I ran to the far end where bikes go. The box for my
solar panel fell off as I ran but I did not have time to pick it up. Someone
picked it up for me though and threw it on the train - it turned out to be
Jannette who had come to see me off. :)</p>
]]></content>
   <georss:point>55.951095 -3.195691</georss:point>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Cycle Who]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/10/Cycle-Who.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/10/Cycle-Who.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2012-12-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/10/Cycle-Who</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I am cycling from Mexico to Patagonia, the southern most part of South
America. I have fitted the bike with a solar panel, and am adding more
electronic gadgets as I travel. I started my trip on 10th of December 2012 and
have no plans about when it will finish. This is an introduction to what I am
doing and why.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8384962554/" title="Leaving Edinburgh by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8214/8384962554_1461cea29d_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="Leaving Edinburgh"></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8272408443/" title="First test of solar charger by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8352/8272408443_0390543aa4_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="First test of solar charger"></a></p>

<h2>Exploring Lifestyles</h2>

<p>There is a standard life pattern that where I'm people are expected to
follow. School, university, job. Buy house and car. Work most of
life. Retire. Die. Is this the best way to be happy? I'm pretty sure it's not.</p>

<p>Some questions I would like to answer:</p>

<ul>
<li>Do you need a house?</li>
<li>Do you need to stay in one place?</li>
<li>What are good forms of transport for a nomadic life?</li>
<li>What makes me happy. What could make everyone happy?</li>
<li>What is needed to allow more or even most people to be nomadic? What could be
done to make travellers lives easier? For example, I think more community
workshops, for bikes, electronics and other things, would help.</li>
<li>How can people achieve freedom from:</li>
<li>Work</li>
<li>Location</li>
<li>Oil</li>
<li>Everything, as far as possible</li>
</ul>


<h2>Promoting</h2>

<ul>
<li>Independent, sustainable travel.</li>
<li>The bicycle as a practical means of transport - not just a toy.</li>
<li>Alternative energy sources.</li>
<li>Thought, and rational behaviour. I would like more people to think about how
they are living their lives - analyse them. Is what you are doing really what
is best for you, or are you doing what you have been told to do by society,
even though it's making you miserable? How many people do you see smiling in
the morning on their way to work? It doesn't need to be like that.</li>
</ul>


<h2>Where</h2>

<p>After failing to get a lift across the Atlantic in a yacht last year, I still
wanted to go to Patagonia. In December I wanted to escape the Scottish winter
to somewhere warm. I knew there was going to be a Rainbow Gathering in
Palenque, Mexico, near a Mayan ruin site, around the time of the end of the
cycle of the Mayan Calendar. This, the climate and a very cheap flight to
Cancun came together to give me the start point of Palenque, at the End of the
World. Now I am heading down to another end.</p>

<p>I don't suppose the exact location really matters though - it is probably most
important that it is just somewhere different from what I already know.</p>

<h2>Why</h2>

<p>I wanted to travel - actually I felt I had to. When I went travelling in the
Canary Islands I missed my bike too much - walking around can be very
tedious. So I decided to travel by bicycle.</p>

<p>I'm looking for happiness. I think that is ultimately what it is all
about. Therefore, I'm exploring different ways of living, and different
places, to see what could make me happy and the world a better place.</p>

<h2>What can you Contribute?</h2>

<p>I think I can inspire people and help them to be happier. I suspect most
people have ideas about how to have a better life but they just don't do
it. Hopefully I can show that something apparently difficult, like cycling a
long way, is actually easily achievable, so more people will do what they know
they want to anyway.</p>

<p>Maybe I can learn things about happiness that I can pass on. Rather than
providing some fixed solution though, which is not likely to work for anyone
but me, getting people to think and improve their situation rather than
accept what is given would be an excellent result.</p>

<p>Happiness and love are contagious.</p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Making a Solar Panel Mount for a Bike]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/10/09/Building-the-Solar-Mounting.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/10/09/Building-the-Solar-Mounting.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2012-10-09T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/10/09/Building-the-Solar-Mounting</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I had chosen to use a 15W, monocrystaline panel mounted under glass in a metal
frame. It was made by ET Solar and bought on ebay for 33 GBP. This seems like
a good panel, but it weighs 2kg and measures 450 x 299 x 35 mm. I had to find
a way to attach it to my bike.</p>

<p>I considered putting it at the front, but the back seemed to be the easiest
and best place. In placing it I wanted to avoid shading from me or any radio
antennas as much as possible, and it was very important to try and design to
my principle of minimising faff.</p>

<p>I decided I needed to mount it above the rear rack somehow. Getting it higher
also has the advantage of getting more sun if I am in the way at the time.</p>

<h1>Ideas</h1>

<h2>Bungees</h2>

<p>The simplest way to mount it was to bungee it on top of the other gear on the
rear rack - my tent and roll mat. This was very easy to do, kept the weight
low - so reducing forces from putting at at the end of a lever higher up, and
it was well cushioned from shock by the gear. However, the problem with this
setup is that it makes it harder to get at my tent and to fix and remove and
other gear. One think I remember really hating when touring before is the time
spent mucking around trying packing and unpacking things. I wanted to get the
panel out the way.</p>

<h2>Custom Metal frame</h2>

<p>A rack could be built in metal, as an addition to the existing luggage racks,
or a custom rack for panniers and solar panel could be built.</p>

<h2>Seat Post Rack</h2>

<p>I looked at rear racks that attach to the seat post - this would give an
additional rack to the conventional one I had fitted. This would add even more
weight though, and they did not go very high, so there would not be much space
between the racks. I also wanted to save money on buying things, but given the
time spent it turned out this was not a valid reason.</p>

<h2>Fibreglass / Composite Luggage storage</h2>

<p>The idea is to build a custom structure that would serve as luggage storage
and solar mount. This would remove the need for panniers. It could also
incorporate spaces for electronics and batteries - for example giving an easily
accessible slot for changing batteries.</p>

<p>One way I've seen to do this that looks very good is a cardboard core glass
reinforced plastic structure. This can be easily built and hacked to any
shape. This was the technique used by Steve Roberts for a similar project.</p>

<p><a href="http://microship.com/resources/cardboard-core-composites.html">Cardboard Core Composites</a></p>

<p><a
href="http://www.solarpoweredbike.com/2008/04/solar-bike-faq-what-is-solar-panel-for.html">Another
fibreglass method</a> was used for a solar bike project:</p>

<p>I think the idea for this was:</p>

<ol>
<li>Build with cardboard.</li>
<li>Fill with expanding foam.</li>
<li>Remove cardboard.</li>
<li>Fibreglass over.</li>
</ol>


<p>So it doesn't end up as a composite with the cardboard core as with the other
method.</p>

<h1>Build / Test</h1>

<p>I decided to make a metal frame myself. This would put the panel where I
wanted it, and it should be possible to make it much lighter than a seat post
rack. Fibreglass looked like it could give a very nice structure, but it would
also be messy to work with and I didn't have anywhere I could do that work. It
would also be expensive and I suspect very time consuming.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/sets/72157632529416559/"><img
src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8515/8384167611_3eb618f479_z.jpg"
width="640" height="480" alt="101_0663"></a></p>

<p>The final design. More detailed photos are on <a
href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/sets/72157632529416559/">flickr</a>.</p>

<p>I had never made anything like this before and didn't know anything about
working metal. I didn't even know where to buy it. One day though I found what
I think might have been a bike rack for a car dumped beside a bin. I recovered
the smaller tubes and started working out what I could do with them.</p>

<p>The design I ended up with was mostly determined by the material I had
available. I used aluminium tube, which seemed like a good choice because it
was light and probably strong enough.</p>

<p>The most difficult part was bending the tubes. Bending a tube by hand can
cause it to collapse. I researched online and read that filling tubes with
sand first would work. I did this, but one of the bends still flattened out to
the point I was concerned it might break. It survived a little testing round
Edinburgh though so I kept it.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8385254986/" title="I was concerned about these bends, particularly on the left."><img
src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8351/8385254986_5cb5afc812_m.jpg"
width="240" height="180" alt="101_0665"></a></p>

<p>The tubes I attached to the bike at the front by screwing onto the rack
mounting points, and at the back with Jubilee clips (hose clamps) padded with
inner tube. The panel is attached to the rack with p-clips, which are horrible
to work with because they are so difficult to bend into the right shape. It
worked though.</p>

<p>It worked until an awful road in Mexico. Update to follow...</p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
</feed>
