<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss">

  <title><![CDATA[Alistair MacLeod, MM0HAI: Posts tagged cycling]]></title>

  <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/tag/cycling/index.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mm0hai.net/"/>
  <updated>2013-05-05T14:57:41-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/tag/cycling</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alistair N. MacLeod]]></name>
  </author>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[An unpleasant day]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/04/30/Hospital.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/04/30/Hospital.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2013-04-30T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/04/30/Hospital</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The day I woke up with a fever and ended up in hospital.</p>

<p>I woke up in my hammock at the Guatemalan migration post at about 5am with a
fever, but tried to ignore it for the moment. I started cycling later, and got
about 20km along the road before I stopped at a petrol station. I was feeling
pretty bad now. I could only just eat a biscuit thing (bran fruit, it was
called) and I drank a bottle of Gatorade. I didn't think it was a good idea to
cycle further, and I would not have enjoyed cycling feeling like that, so I
waited for a bus.</p>

<p>I had read that if you get a fever after being in a malarious area the first
thing you need to do is get checked for Malaria. I thought I would go to the
nearest town for a doctor, but I wanted to go to Flores as I thought that
would be a nice place to recover, and also there would be a cash machine
there. I didn't know the exchange rate so only risked very little in pesos to
the border based moneychangers.</p>

<p>The bus was something like a large minibus, with a roofrack where my bike
went. This was the worst bus ride of my life. The road was stony, long,
straight, and with nothing interesting at all to see. It is, I think, also the
worst road to cycle I have ever seen. The bus was hot, and as the journey went
on it got hotter. More people got on, and I started to feel worse.</p>

<p>At 1200, I got hold of my paracetamol and started pouring water on my head and
face to try and avoid my brain overheating.</p>

<p>When it was getting really quite bad, on got a preacher who started screaming
stuff about jesus at the top of his voice right beside me. I considered
trying to tell him to stop but realised that arguing with a mad man would just
encourage him. Interestingly the driver seemed to allow this. I was also
concerned that if I said anything the rest of the bus would lynch me for being
an evil atheist. I told myself that the kind of malaria you get around here is
not fatal, but I was concerned about it anyway. I considered asking the
preacher for the last rites - that would probably get him to shut up. In the
end I realised I had some earplugs to hand, so fitted them to some
improvement.</p>

<p>It would be a reasonable way to die anyway. A jungle in some exotic country
seems a respectable death for a British gentleman explorer.</p>

<p>We stopped at petrol station. Here some men threw buckets of water over the
bus and washed it, while some others stood around with guns. I was soon to
discover Guatemalans like standing around with guns. I wasn't happy about the
lack of sense of urgency to reach our destination.</p>

<p>Finally we got to somewhere urban, near our destination. It was crazily busy,
with Tuk-Tuks, other vehicles and people. People getting on the bus to sell
refrescos and snacks. When we got going again it wasn't too far to the hospital.</p>

<p>I had asked about a doctor initially but later asked them to drop me at the
hospital. I thought they would actually take me there, but they dumped me on
the other side of the road a few hundred meters away. I felt very weak and
probably couldn't think properly, but out of necessity I managed to load up my
bike and push it across the road without being run over.</p>

<p>There was a kind man at the reception who took me to the emergency department,
with my bike. They wanted to register me with my passport, but otherwise no
paperwork, and treatment was free. I had to speak to several doctors before
they decided someone knew enough English to understand. I tried Spanish first
but apparently they were not happy with that.</p>

<p>They took blood and urine samples. I was severely dehydrated so I was given
two bags of saline i.v. and some drug I can't remember to reduce fever and
pain. The tests for malaria and dengue were negative, but I might have had
some infection. I think the main problem was that I didn't eat and drink
enough.</p>

<p>I watched a bit of Marc Beaumont's Americas film before I left San Cris. It
said he has to eat six meals a day. I laughed at that because there is no way
I was eating that much. On the road through the forest mostly there was just
biscuits and sugar drinks. Usually shops also had some rice and tuna, and
occasionally some veg., but generally it was very difficult to eat
properly. Anyway, it turns out if you go cycling in 35C, midday sun and don't
eat and drink properly, you end up in hospital.</p>

<p>I have now been recovering for a few days in an hotel and now a hostel in
Flores. I couldn't eat for the first couple of days but I had some
smoothies. I'm pretty much recovered now and enjoying the food at Los Amigos
hostel, which includes tofu and vegetable curry - possibly the only place in
the country (except maybe Antigua) to have such things.</p>

<p>I think I'll go and check out the warm showers place near here, clean the
bike, and head to Belize in a few days maybe.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8696706948/" title="DSCF4210 by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8396/8696706948_209dc5e844_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="DSCF4210"></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8695285843/" title="DSCF4201 by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8535/8695285843_69d392516c_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="DSCF4201"></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8696405860/" title="DSCF4199 by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8399/8696405860_486a234a45_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="DSCF4199"></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8696705644/" title="DSCF4208 by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8114/8696705644_c7e56dac62_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="DSCF4208"></a></p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Getting into the Bathtub]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/01/09/Getting-into-the-Bathtub.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/01/09/Getting-into-the-Bathtub.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2013-01-09T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/01/09/Getting-into-the-Bathtub</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>My touring bike and gear had either very little or in some cases no testing at
all before leaving. I had replaced most of the bike, including rebuilding the
wheels with new rims, cones and ball bearings. The panniers were all brand
new. The ærobars and bar ends were new. The solar panel mounting was tested
only lightly around Edinburgh. Now I was on tour.</p>

<p>In engineering, there is something called a <a
href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bathtub_curve">bathtub curve</a>. This
shows the general shape of the probability of failures of many systems over
time. A new system might fail from manufacturing defects and an old one from
wearing out. In between, the chance of failure is lower. This curve looks like
a bathtub.</p>

<p><img
src="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/7/78/Bathtub_curve.svg"
width="640" alt="Bathtub curve" ></p>

<p>There was so much new on the bike that I knew I was not in the bath yet, and
was almost expecting things to fail. They did.</p>

<p>First my solar panel rack broke. I was worried it might on the Rainbow Road -
an awful, bumpy, rough track. 30km or so did it. The front tube broke where it
touched the carrier rack. The point at the rear where the tube was over bent,
that I was concerned about before I left, also broke. I needed to get this
fixed before I could cycle further. It did keep the panel on the bike like
this, but without fixing it would probably totally fail soon. Getting it
repaired is a story for another post.</p>

<p>The other problem I had was the front wheel started to make a nasty noise. I
found that something in the hub was catching when it rotated. When I left, the
balls were new and the cones were recycled but only had one very minor pit in
the track. The cups are built into the hub and had some wear but did not look
too bad. I found someone at the Rainbow Gathering who had cone spanners and we
had a look inside. The cones still looked good and the grease was clean. We
didn't take the balls out though or would inevitably have lost them in the
forest. He did not know what was wrong either, but took out one ball from each
side, so the hub now had 9 per side. I am sure it had 10 before I rebuilt it,
but the problem has now stopped, so I'm leaving it like that.</p>

<p>I found my headset was loose. I didn't use a headset press when I fitted it -
only a hammer - so maybe the bumpy road pushed the races in further. This was
easily tightened by borrowing a large adjustable spanner from a local bike
shop. I don't think they had a proper headset spanner so I couldn't hold the
bearing for exact adjustment as I tightened the locknut. It's probably
slightly overtight now but I decided to leave it as good enough for a change
rather than spending all day tweaking. It was a cheap headset anyway so I'll
probably have to replace it soon.</p>

<p>I've also been moving my saddle. I've mostly been using the ærobars and so I
have a different riding position. The saddle is a Brooks I've had for some
time, but it has not been used on a tour before. It's breaking in much faster
than at home, probably because of the heat and humidity.</p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[PEMEX]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/01/07/PEMEX.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/01/07/PEMEX.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2013-01-07T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/01/07/PEMEX</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8387837666/" title="PEMEX"><img
src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8361/8387837666_ed618aa2b2_z.jpg"
width="640" height="480" alt="PEMEX Station"></a></p>

<p>Before I really started cycling here in Mexico, a couple of people told me
they camped and hammocked at PEMEX, the only brand of petrol station I have
seen so far in Mexico. I thought that sounded a bit crazy but that is because
I had only toured in Europe before.</p>

<p>In Europe, I found I could camp almost anywhere by the side of the road. There
might be a forest, or a field, a picnic spot, a public park or even a
campsite. Here the roads I have seen so far are lined by ditches and fences
unbroken for miles. The slopes to the ditches are often very steep, the
ditches quite wide and full of water and then there is a barbed wire fence on
the other side. Getting the bike across this would be very difficult. Getting
self over would be possible, but would involve getting wet, muddy, and
possibly injured. There are venomous snakes around here, ticks and maybe
leeches. It generally is not something I want to do.</p>

<p>Last night I found a small space between the road and the water. I stopped
there because I saw some flatter ground. I was not the first to notice it
though - there was an old camp fire, and lots of rubbish. I moved down from
the road a bit for cover from sight. I thought it would be better not to be
seen because that was my only defence against robbers. Down here though was
where people had been using as a toilet and rubbish dump.</p>

<p>In the morning I had to get the bike back up the slope, which was not
easy. Then I spent probably spent half an hour stopping and trying to work out
what was making a scraping noise as the wheels turned. Eventually I found a
piece of wire stuck in the back tyre was scraping on the inside of the
mudgaurd. This and the sticks that jammed in the gears are more reasons to
avoid these sites.</p>

<p>If you want a flat site with short grass (to avoid snakes) it seems like the
only option usually is to ask at someones house to camp in the garden. This
can be quite successful - I did this the night before and was also given a
meal. Some people at the Rainbow told me they had done this and it happened to
be the occasion of the Granny's 101st birthday. A pig was slaughtered for them
and they were basically forced to stay for two days eating and drinking.</p>

<p>The other option though is a petrol station. Now that I have seen one it makes
sense. I'm camping now on a large area of flat, short grass, about 20 meters
from the hardstanding. I can see my bike locked near the pumps, lit and under
cover from rain. There is a toilet, sink for washing, food and water right
outside. There is also a useful amount of light but not so much as to stop
sleep.</p>

<p>In Europe, I would avoid a petrol station as noisy and possibly dangerous and
camp somewhere quiet. I also think of them as expensive and of course
supporting an oil based system. But now I look out of the tent and the PEMEX
sign is like a marker of an oasis. This and the glowing traffic cone landing
lights, are beautiful.</p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Bike is Important]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/01/05/The-Bike-is-Important.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/01/05/The-Bike-is-Important.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2013-01-05T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/01/05/The-Bike-is-Important</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I don't think you understand how important this is. This is not a toy or for
going to the shops. This is for tens of thousands of miles of dirt roads,
jungles, deserts and mountains. This is my home for years. For the majority
of people I meet for the next few years, this is all they will remember of
me. You did this like you had no time for better, then spent the rest of the
day standing around doing nothing.</p>

<p>This morning I started to cry. I put on Runrig, "Road and the River", which
triggered it, although I almost felt like crying when I saw your work
yesterday. I should have insisted you do it better. I didn't negotiate the
price down because I wanted you to be interested enough in it to do a good
job. Apparently that didn't work. The only reason I let you continue and paid
you is because I couldn't move without it. Something that might last a few
hundred miles would at least let me escape this place now. The one thing that
was good about this work was that it was done by 3pm the day it started.</p>

<p>Now I am sitting right next to a freedom machine but still feel trapped. I
don't know if I can cycle because of illness. If I do I'll probably get wet
when my tent leaks again. If I want better gear I will need to wait for it to
be delivered here - I think there is no chance of buying something that is not
rubbish here. That means waiting somewhere - again I am trapped. All the time
I can't even eat anything that is not poison, so it's not surprising I have
been ill for nearly two weeks. The current cold that is, not diarrhoea and
vomiting immediately preceding. And it will probably take days to choose things
and order them on the internet, and most of the days will be wasted trying to
find working wifi.</p>

<p>I am thinking too much. I can get out of an hotel room in the morning without
thinking - I have done this before. I am going to cycle, kit be dammed. I am
going to ride my bike today whether I have a map and a waterproof tent or not.</p>

<p>Now I feel better. I'm going to have breakfast.</p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Finally Moving]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/01/05/Finally-Moving.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/01/05/Finally-Moving.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2013-01-05T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/01/05/Finally-Moving</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I spent over two weeks at the Rainbow Gathering, then a couple of days in
Palenque getting my solar rack fixed. Before that I had been in hostels
working on computer related stuff, so apart from the road to the Rainbow I had
cycled very little. I was starting to get frustrated and feeling trapped by my
gear, admin and thoughts.</p>

<p>The bike was so far mostly a burden and extra expense on busses. It had already
needed repair work. I had almost forgotten what it was for, and felt I could
not move. I didn't know whether to go on to Merida, then across to Chichen
Itza and Tulum as planned, to head straight over to Chetumal and Belize, or to
go to San Cristobal de las Casas, which I had heard was a bike and vegan
friendly town. I was thinking and not moving.</p>

<p>Suddenly I realised I was right beside a freedom machine. I resolved I was
going to cycle today no matter what. Without a map, without doing a better job
of the solar rack or testing it, without any more gear, and without a well
considered decision about where to go. I just had to move.</p>

<p>I started cycling and it worked. I felt better as soon as I was rolling.</p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Palenque Rainbow Gathering]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/01/03/Palenque-Rainbow-Gathering.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/01/03/Palenque-Rainbow-Gathering.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2013-01-03T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/01/03/Palenque-Rainbow-Gathering</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I spent the last two weeks at the Palenque Rainbow Gathering. Unfortunately I
didn't enjoy it very much. There were times I did - the few days I was not ill
I enjoyed swimming and slacklining over the river. Most of the time though I
was ill with various ailments. I suspect I had Giardia from the river, and
then a cold. Sanitation is difficult with so many people living in a temporary
camp.</p>

<p>Some amusing moments though included going for a night out at the theatre, in
the forest, singing and listening to music, and a music therapy session. I
also tried to fix Mykal's dynamo to USB voltage regulator, but I didn't have
any gas for my soldering iron.</p>

<p>I spent some time asking people about hammocks and trying some out,
because I was thinking of replacing my tent with one. I had to get something
new anyway, because I found my tent now leaks badly and is not a comfortable
home.</p>

<p>One day I went for a walk up the road to a wee village. It was the first time
I felt I was seeing Mexico. There were horses on the road and it generally
felt rural and like it was really Mexico, not just another town.</p>

<p>I visited the Mayan ruins one day as well. I didn't enjoy it much though
because I was generally in a bad mood at least partly because of illness, and
because it was so hot I found it tiring to walk. I also didn't like how there
were so many people trying to sell things.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8362733937/" title="DSCF3053 by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8080/8362733937_29a136bb45_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="DSCF3053"></a></p>

<p>I learnt something about how palm oil is produced. The gathering was in a palm
plantation, and one day some people came round with a donkey to harvest the
nuts from which oil is extracted.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8362701093/" title="DSCF3024 by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8378/8362701093_2e4e3d9fb6_z.jpg" width="480" height="640" alt="DSCF3024"></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8362703347/" title="DSCF3025 by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8186/8362703347_7b85d7f92f_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="DSCF3025"></a></p>

<p>I had a couple of quite special experiences. One evening I participated in an
Angel Walk. Another day I had a good experience when I decided to stop thinking
and follow my feelings, which led to an interesting result. I might write
about these later.</p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Going to the Palenque Rainbow Gathering]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/18/To-the-Rainbow.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/18/To-the-Rainbow.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2012-12-18T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/18/To-the-Rainbow</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>When the earth is ravaged and the animals are dying, a new tribe of people
shall come unto the earth from many colors, classes, creeds, and who by
their actions and deeds shall make the earth green again. They will be known
as the warriors of the Rainbow.
-- Native American Prophecy, seen <a
href="http://www.welcomehome.org/rainbow/">here</a>.</p></blockquote>

<p>The Palenque Rainbow Gathering is one reason I came to Mexico now, to begin
cycling at the End of the World.</p>

<p>I arrived in Palenque by overnight bus, had breakfast and set off down the road.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8339829385/" title="Beginning of
the dirt road to the Rainbow by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img
src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8213/8339829385_0530a24c5b_z.jpg"
width="640" height="480" alt="Beginning of the dirt road to the Rainbow"></a></p>

<p>Leaving Palenque there was a short section of main road before reaching the
turnoff for the Rainbow. Then the road was awful. Very bumpy surface, rocks,
and it went up and down. My bike was heavily loaded and I was not particularly
fit. On the way up the road, though, I met a friend I last saw in Europe a
year ago, who was walking to town. :)</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8339845737/" title="DSCF3008 by
mm0hai, on Flickr"><img
src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8359/8339845737_314e8af703_z.jpg"
width="640" height="480" alt="DSCF3008"></a></p>

<p>Eventually I arrived, and one of the first things I did was go for a swim in
 the river pools.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8384100203/" title="DSCF3203 by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8189/8384100203_7f75dba767_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="DSCF3203"></a></p>

<p>I went for a walk around to explore and look for a campsite. On the way back
to get my bike and things I met three other cycle tourists who had just
arrived. <a href="http://chaingethecycle.org/">Mykal and Nico</a>, who were
cycling to Guatemala to help build an earth ship, and Lance, who was cycling
to Panama. We set up camp together. I stayed for the next two weeks.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8364983083/" title="DSCF3133 by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8055/8364983083_4131357bf4_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="DSCF3133"></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8366114804/" title="DSCF3146 by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8083/8366114804_cc0cd31ccb_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="DSCF3146"></a></p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[First Test of Solar Charger]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/14/First-Test-of-Solar-Charger.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/14/First-Test-of-Solar-Charger.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2012-12-14T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/14/First-Test-of-Solar-Charger</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I designed and built a charger for Thinkpad batteries before I left, but there
was not enough sun in Scotland to test it properly. Today in Tulum I tried it
for real for the first time.</p>

<p>Tropical mid-day sun was sufficient. It charged the battery for a while. When
I tried a battery that was at a higher voltage, it did not charge it as
designed. The voltage cutoff was lower than I had set at home, but basically
it seems to work. I did not leave it long enough to see it cutoff when full
though. I also would like to measure the power supplied so I know how long
charging will let the computer run.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8272408443/" title="First test of
solar charger by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img
src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8352/8272408443_0390543aa4_z.jpg"
width="640" height="480" alt="First test of solar charger"></a></p>

<p>The charger is not mounted on the bike yet, so it's just sitting on top while
I measure voltages.</p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Leaving Edinburgh]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/10/Leaving-Edinburgh-for-Mexico.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/10/Leaving-Edinburgh-for-Mexico.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2012-12-10T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/10/Leaving-Edinburgh-for-Mexico</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After far too long in Edinburgh I am finally moving. I decided that even if I
was not really ready yet I had to leave because the weather was getting quite
unpleasant in Scotland and if I did not just decide to leave would I ever
really be ready anyway? I had booked a flight to Cancun, Mexico about two
weeks ago but was still not ready. The photos below I took myself just before
cycling to the train station. I hadn't finished packing when it came time to
leave to catch the train so I had to throw things in without time to decide
what I really needed. It was the first time I had ridden the bike loaded with
the new panniers and all gear.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8340847482/" title="Leaving by
mm0hai, on Flickr"><img
src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8072/8340847482_4f02f7752a_z.jpg"
width="480" height="640" alt="Leaving"></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8340848528/" title="Leaving by
mm0hai, on Flickr"><img
src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8498/8340848528_82c8c559b5_z.jpg"
width="640" height="480" alt="Leaving"></a></p>

<p>The handling with front panniers is very different. It felt like I had a flat
tyre, I think because of the weight compressing the tyre and giving more
friction on the ground. I cycled slowly and hoped nothing was going to break.</p>

<p>I got to the platform just as the train was about to leave. Someone told me I
would not make it but I ran to the far end where bikes go. The box for my
solar panel fell off as I ran but I did not have time to pick it up. Someone
picked it up for me though and threw it on the train - it turned out to be
Jannette who had come to see me off. :)</p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Cycle Who]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/10/Cycle-Who.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/10/Cycle-Who.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2012-12-10T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/10/Cycle-Who</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I am cycling from Mexico to Patagonia, the southern most part of South
America. I have fitted the bike with a solar panel, and am adding more
electronic gadgets as I travel. I started my trip on 10th of December 2012 and
have no plans about when it will finish. This is an introduction to what I am
doing and why.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8384962554/" title="Leaving Edinburgh by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8214/8384962554_1461cea29d_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="Leaving Edinburgh"></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8272408443/" title="First test of solar charger by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8352/8272408443_0390543aa4_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="First test of solar charger"></a></p>

<h2>Exploring Lifestyles</h2>

<p>There is a standard life pattern that where I'm people are expected to
follow. School, university, job. Buy house and car. Work most of
life. Retire. Die. Is this the best way to be happy? I'm pretty sure it's not.</p>

<p>Some questions I would like to answer:</p>

<ul>
<li>Do you need a house?</li>
<li>Do you need to stay in one place?</li>
<li>What are good forms of transport for a nomadic life?</li>
<li>What makes me happy. What could make everyone happy?</li>
<li>What is needed to allow more or even most people to be nomadic? What could be
done to make travellers lives easier? For example, I think more community
workshops, for bikes, electronics and other things, would help.</li>
<li>How can people achieve freedom from:</li>
<li>Work</li>
<li>Location</li>
<li>Oil</li>
<li>Everything, as far as possible</li>
</ul>


<h2>Promoting</h2>

<ul>
<li>Independent, sustainable travel.</li>
<li>The bicycle as a practical means of transport - not just a toy.</li>
<li>Alternative energy sources.</li>
<li>Thought, and rational behaviour. I would like more people to think about how
they are living their lives - analyse them. Is what you are doing really what
is best for you, or are you doing what you have been told to do by society,
even though it's making you miserable? How many people do you see smiling in
the morning on their way to work? It doesn't need to be like that.</li>
</ul>


<h2>Where</h2>

<p>After failing to get a lift across the Atlantic in a yacht last year, I still
wanted to go to Patagonia. In December I wanted to escape the Scottish winter
to somewhere warm. I knew there was going to be a Rainbow Gathering in
Palenque, Mexico, near a Mayan ruin site, around the time of the end of the
cycle of the Mayan Calendar. This, the climate and a very cheap flight to
Cancun came together to give me the start point of Palenque, at the End of the
World. Now I am heading down to another end.</p>

<p>I don't suppose the exact location really matters though - it is probably most
important that it is just somewhere different from what I already know.</p>

<h2>Why</h2>

<p>I wanted to travel - actually I felt I had to. When I went travelling in the
Canary Islands I missed my bike too much - walking around can be very
tedious. So I decided to travel by bicycle.</p>

<p>I'm looking for happiness. I think that is ultimately what it is all
about. Therefore, I'm exploring different ways of living, and different
places, to see what could make me happy and the world a better place.</p>

<h2>What can you Contribute?</h2>

<p>I think I can inspire people and help them to be happier. I suspect most
people have ideas about how to have a better life but they just don't do
it. Hopefully I can show that something apparently difficult, like cycling a
long way, is actually easily achievable, so more people will do what they know
they want to anyway.</p>

<p>Maybe I can learn things about happiness that I can pass on. Rather than
providing some fixed solution though, which is not likely to work for anyone
but me, getting people to think and improve their situation rather than
accept what is given would be an excellent result.</p>

<p>Happiness and love are contagious.</p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Making a Solar Panel Mount for a Bike]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/10/09/Building-the-Solar-Mounting.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/10/09/Building-the-Solar-Mounting.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2012-10-09T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/10/09/Building-the-Solar-Mounting</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I had chosen to use a 15W, monocrystaline panel mounted under glass in a metal
frame. It was made by ET Solar and bought on ebay for 33 GBP. This seems like
a good panel, but it weighs 2kg and measures 450 x 299 x 35 mm. I had to find
a way to attach it to my bike.</p>

<p>I considered putting it at the front, but the back seemed to be the easiest
and best place. In placing it I wanted to avoid shading from me or any radio
antennas as much as possible, and it was very important to try and design to
my principle of minimising faff.</p>

<p>I decided I needed to mount it above the rear rack somehow. Getting it higher
also has the advantage of getting more sun if I am in the way at the time.</p>

<h1>Ideas</h1>

<h2>Bungees</h2>

<p>The simplest way to mount it was to bungee it on top of the other gear on the
rear rack - my tent and roll mat. This was very easy to do, kept the weight
low - so reducing forces from putting at at the end of a lever higher up, and
it was well cushioned from shock by the gear. However, the problem with this
setup is that it makes it harder to get at my tent and to fix and remove and
other gear. One think I remember really hating when touring before is the time
spent mucking around trying packing and unpacking things. I wanted to get the
panel out the way.</p>

<h2>Custom Metal frame</h2>

<p>A rack could be built in metal, as an addition to the existing luggage racks,
or a custom rack for panniers and solar panel could be built.</p>

<h2>Seat Post Rack</h2>

<p>I looked at rear racks that attach to the seat post - this would give an
additional rack to the conventional one I had fitted. This would add even more
weight though, and they did not go very high, so there would not be much space
between the racks. I also wanted to save money on buying things, but given the
time spent it turned out this was not a valid reason.</p>

<h2>Fibreglass / Composite Luggage storage</h2>

<p>The idea is to build a custom structure that would serve as luggage storage
and solar mount. This would remove the need for panniers. It could also
incorporate spaces for electronics and batteries - for example giving an easily
accessible slot for changing batteries.</p>

<p>One way I've seen to do this that looks very good is a cardboard core glass
reinforced plastic structure. This can be easily built and hacked to any
shape. This was the technique used by Steve Roberts for a similar project.</p>

<p><a href="http://microship.com/resources/cardboard-core-composites.html">Cardboard Core Composites</a></p>

<p><a
href="http://www.solarpoweredbike.com/2008/04/solar-bike-faq-what-is-solar-panel-for.html">Another
fibreglass method</a> was used for a solar bike project:</p>

<p>I think the idea for this was:</p>

<ol>
<li>Build with cardboard.</li>
<li>Fill with expanding foam.</li>
<li>Remove cardboard.</li>
<li>Fibreglass over.</li>
</ol>


<p>So it doesn't end up as a composite with the cardboard core as with the other
method.</p>

<h1>Build / Test</h1>

<p>I decided to make a metal frame myself. This would put the panel where I
wanted it, and it should be possible to make it much lighter than a seat post
rack. Fibreglass looked like it could give a very nice structure, but it would
also be messy to work with and I didn't have anywhere I could do that work. It
would also be expensive and I suspect very time consuming.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/sets/72157632529416559/"><img
src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8515/8384167611_3eb618f479_z.jpg"
width="640" height="480" alt="101_0663"></a></p>

<p>The final design. More detailed photos are on <a
href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/sets/72157632529416559/">flickr</a>.</p>

<p>I had never made anything like this before and didn't know anything about
working metal. I didn't even know where to buy it. One day though I found what
I think might have been a bike rack for a car dumped beside a bin. I recovered
the smaller tubes and started working out what I could do with them.</p>

<p>The design I ended up with was mostly determined by the material I had
available. I used aluminium tube, which seemed like a good choice because it
was light and probably strong enough.</p>

<p>The most difficult part was bending the tubes. Bending a tube by hand can
cause it to collapse. I researched online and read that filling tubes with
sand first would work. I did this, but one of the bends still flattened out to
the point I was concerned it might break. It survived a little testing round
Edinburgh though so I kept it.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8385254986/" title="I was concerned about these bends, particularly on the left."><img
src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8351/8385254986_5cb5afc812_m.jpg"
width="240" height="180" alt="101_0665"></a></p>

<p>The tubes I attached to the bike at the front by screwing onto the rack
mounting points, and at the back with Jubilee clips (hose clamps) padded with
inner tube. The panel is attached to the rack with p-clips, which are horrible
to work with because they are so difficult to bend into the right shape. It
worked though.</p>

<p>It worked until an awful road in Mexico. Update to follow...</p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Streetmachine Gte and Bacchetta Bella test ride]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/09/13/Streetmachine-Gte.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/09/13/Streetmachine-Gte.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2012-09-13T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/09/13/Streetmachine-Gte</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/ahOll.png" alt="Streetmachine Gte"
title="Streetmachine Gte" /></p>

<p>I'm looking for a bike to become <a
href="/blog/2012/08/26/Music-Hack-Day-Scotland.html">River Song</a>, which is
what I think I'll call my technomadic geek world touring platform.</p>

<p>Today I went to Glasgow to test ride an HP Velotechnik Streetmachine Gte at
the Kinetics bike shop. From what I have read this bike seems to be a highly
rated world tourer. It's an under seat steering short wheel base, with full
suspension.</p>

<p>I think I want under seat steering because it seems more comfortable. I am lazy
and would rather not have to hold my arms up to the handlebars. A short wheel
base makes the bike easier to maneuver, particularly in cases such as putting
in on trains or other vehicles and taking it into hotel rooms.</p>

<p>Suspension is interesting. I'm not sure if it's really useful if the bike is
just used on the road and it adds complexity and weight. It might be good for
landrover tracks and dirt roads. I went quite fast down a potholed road and it
seemed to work quite well. The rigid frame Bacchetta was not uncomfortable
either though, presumably because of the seat padding. I suppose a more
reclined position may make suspension more important because the force goes
more through your back rather than a cushioning gluteus maximus. I was riding
both bikes without luggage. The suspension might also matter more if the bike
is heavily loaded.</p>

<p>I thought I would really like this bike but I'm afraid I didn't. I had some
particular problems with it and I wasn't sure about the overall feel. When
steering at low speed my heel hit the mudgaurd. This would not be a problem if
I had longer legs but for me the boom was almost fully in. After only about 10
minutes on the bike I already felt a pressure point on my back, at the corner
of the seat from the bum part to the flatter back section. This is quite
concerning because feeling something after so little time means it would
probably become a serious sore after constant riding. It might be possible to
fix this by changing the padding though. It had the basic foam pad velcroed
onto the fiberglass seat. There is also a mesh pad and another type of seat
available.</p>

<p>Another concern I had about the Streetmachine Gte was that it's made of
aluminium alloy, rather than steel. Everything I read about choosing a touring
bike frame says that steel is better because it is less likely to break, and
if it does it can be repaired by any welder in even very remote
places. Aluminium requires a TIG or MIG welder which are much rarer. The
previous version of the bike, the Streetmachine Gt, was steel. I emailed
HP Velotechnik to ask why they had made what seemed to be a change for the
worse and received the following reply.</p>

<blockquote>
<p>we changed the material as we discovered, that our frames will last even
longer with the new 7005 Aluminium. Doing this, we extended our frame warranty
from 5 to 10 years.</p>

<p>yours sincerely from Kriftel</p>

<p>Alex Kopp</p>
</blockquote>


<p>I don't really know much about metal, but it seems that aluminium fails from
repeated flexing. If the frame is designed to be rigid enough that it doesn't
flex, then it won't break because of this. Presumably HP Velotechnik have done
of good job of this design and in practice it is probably not a problem.</p>

<p>I also tried a Bacchetta Bella. This is a long wheel base, over seat steered
bike with a more American style upright seat. I didn't expect to like it but I
did. It was easier to control than the Streetmachine. This probably doesn't
matter with practice but it was noticeable as a beginner recumbent rider. I
preferred the general feel of it. I could also imagine mounting a computer
screen or tablet on the handlebars.</p>

<p>I now know that I'll have to try some more bikes before I make a decision
about this.</p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bolts for Bikes]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/09/01/Bolts-and-Fasteners-for-Bike.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/09/01/Bolts-and-Fasteners-for-Bike.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2012-09-01T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/09/01/Bolts-and-Fasteners-for-Bike</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For my geek bike project I needed to choose some fastenings to make the solar
panel mount, and also for attaching carrier racks to the frame.</p>

<p>The choice is quite important and I have had problems with them before. On my
last tour one of the bolts attaching the rear carrier to the frame fell out. I
had to remove another one of these to fit the solar panel and almost couldn't
because it had rusted solid.</p>

<h2>Size</h2>

<p>The brazeons on my bike are M5 threads. This is the same as used in my SPD
shoes, which saved me when I lost one last time, so I'm standardising on M5.</p>

<h2>Drive</h2>

<p>I want something common so I don't need special tools and can find tools if I
need to. This means slot, cross / phillips, or hex / allan key. Slot and cross
heads can be deformed too easily - hex gives much more torque and is harder to
damage. This is important if the bolt gets stuck.</p>

<h2>Head shape</h2>

<p>Some hex socket screws have a rounded off head and some are cylindrical. The
later kind could be gripped with pliers if the socket was damaged so I favour
these.</p>

<h2>Material</h2>

<p>For strength I think it has to be some sort of steel. The options are zinc
plated, galvanised or stainless steel. Hot dip galvanisation gives too thick a
layer of zinc for threads of this size, so the real options are zinc plated or
stainless.</p>

<p>The screws in my rack which have rusted solid were zinc plated. Clearly this
is inadequate unless you constantly attend to them by oiling and
replacment. That leaves stainless steel. The specific grade of stainless steel
is probably irrelevent for this application.</p>

<h2>Galvanic corrosion</h2>

<p>There is a possible problem with stainless though. When dissimilar metals are
in contact in the presence of water they form an electrical cell which
oxidises the less noble metal. My bike frame is made of aluminium, which is
less noble than stainless steel but more noble than zinc. Stainless steel
risks corroding the frame whereas zinc plated screws would not. According to
the British Stainless Steel Association, the <a
href="http://www.bssa.org.uk/topics.php?article=89">risk of problems</a> from
a small amount of stainless in contact with a larger piece of aluminium is
quite low. Additionally, galvanic corrosion is only a problem if the parts are
wet, and particularly with salt water. Most of the time I expect to be touring
in warm dry weather (this is an advantage of being able to move all the time)
so the risk seems quite low. Nevertheless, I could reduce this risk my adding
some sacrificial zinc somewhere. An easy way to do this would be to use zinc
plated washers.</p>

<h2>Locking</h2>

<p>As well as the carrier bolt which fell out, in testing my solar panel mount
around town I lost another screw. I suspect this is because of the vibration,
particularly from hard tyres I like to reduce rolling resistance.</p>

<p>The one which came out used a nyloc nut but the bolt was very short so it
might not have reached the plastic. I think I will use nyloc again with the
correct size of bolt and also use threadlock. I would like to use copper
grease to avoid seizing but I'm not sure about how to use this and threadlock.</p>

<p>Someone told me you can use nail polish instead of threadlock. Presumably
threadlock is better, but I don't know. I also found the <a
href="http://www.thunderboltrc.com/tutorials/tutorial_six.html">idea</a> when
searching about this to use nail polish to indictade movement of the bolt -
put it accross bolt and other part and it will crack if the bolt turns.</p>

<p>The value of lock washers seems to be debatable, so I think I won't use them
for now.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>The ANM standard bolt is an M5, cylindrical hex socket head, stainless
steel. It should be used with threadlock, stainless nyloc nut and plain
stainless or zinc plated washers.</p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[River Song - Music Hack Day Scotland]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/08/26/Music-Hack-Day-Scotland.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/08/26/Music-Hack-Day-Scotland.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2012-08-26T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/08/26/Music-Hack-Day-Scotland</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This weekend saw a music hack day in Edinburgh. I signed up with a couple of
ideas of things I might do but I wasn't really sure if I'd get much done. In
the end my hack was quite successful and I won an iPad!</p>

<p>One idea I had was to make a virtual <a
href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Singing_bowl">Singing Bowl</a> using a wire
and capacitive touch sensing. I thought this would be quite difficult because
to do it at all well would probably require quite a sophisticated sensor,
something like used in <a
href="http://www.disneyresearch.com/research/projects/hci_botanicus_drp.htm">Disney's
interactive plant project</a>.</p>

<p>My other, which I built, was related to my touring bike. I was thinking about
what to call my new bike when I get her, and I think I might choose <a
href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/River_Song_(Doctor_Who)">River
Song</a>. The bike is for open ended touring without any particular rush to
get anywhere. It is for living. I like the idea of the bike flowing through
life, time and space.</p>

<p>Make the bike sing.</p>

<p>This gave me the idea that she ought to have a song. I wanted something to
represent movement and flow. The most obvious idea was the sound of a river. I
could also have tried to compose something but that seemed more difficult
because it would require musical ability. I decided to make river sounds.</p>

<p>I wanted the sound to change with movement. The simplest thing is to take the
current speed. I also thought about using distance traveled recently
(i.e. adding integral action to the music controller). I considered modeling
a water system, such that movement caused rainfall, which then soaked through
the ground and eventually reached the river. For this hack, I kept it simple
and used only speed.</p>

<p><img
src="/res/2012-08-26-Music-Hack-Day-Scotland/river-song-block-diagram.png"
alt="Block diagram of system."
title="The unicycle is not actually radially spoked." /></p>

<p>Above is a diagram of the system I demonstrated. I used a unicycle rather than
a bike for the demo because it was easier to get it into the lecture theatre
and turn the wheel. I'll now discuss the design choices.</p>

<p>I considered two ways of making the sound. One was synthesising from scratch,
and the other using samples. I realised that I actually had recordings of a
river and of water flowing in a pipe, the later which I took when walking on
La Palma. I chose to use synthesis because it seemed like it would be easier
to modify the sound with data and it made it more hackable for future changes
to the sound.</p>

<p>I had never done any sound synthesis before so I didn't know what software I
should use. I thought about using a library for some programming language I
already knew but decided to try using something designed for sound. The main
contenders seemed to be SuperCollider and Pure Data. Asking around I found
Pure Data seems to be the most popular, and this was confirmed at the
presentation when I saw several hacks used it.</p>

<p>Pure Data was difficult to get started with, and I almost gave up. The
documentation is very poor and the Ubuntu package had various things wrong
with it, like the sound test not working. I managed to get it working in the
end. I didn't have time to learn much about the language never mind actually
designing synthesisers and sounds but I found a Pure Data patch which made
something which sounded like running water. Random hacking at this discovered
a place where I could change a value to make the water sound more violent. I
used this and also increased the volume when the bike went faster.</p>

<p>To detect movement I used a magnet on the wheel and a reed switch from an old
bike computer. This I connected to an Arduino (actually <a
href="/blog/2011/05/25/Arduino-Getting-started-with-Seeeduino.html">Seeeduino</a>)
which measured the time between switch pulses and sent this over a USB serial
connection to a laptop running Pure Data.</p>

<p>In Pure Data, I used the comport module to receive data from the serial
port. This was also not well documented but I worked it out from some blog
posts.</p>

<p>I finished soldering connectors together about 10 minutes before the
presentations were meant to start and then ran to the event. I was tweaking
the sensor position and patch parameters during the talks but soldering proper
connectors paid off because there was no trouble - amazingly the thing
actually worked at a demonstration! I was now on stage with a unicycle, so of
course I had to try and ride it. I managed to idle briefly and long enough to
trigger the sensor, so overall successful.</p>

<p>I would have been quite pleased at that, but then there were prizes, and I won
an iPad! I'm not sure what to do with it yet. Maybe duck tape it to my
bike. :)</p>

<p><img src="http://twitpic.com/show/large/anmlwj.jpg"
alt="Demonstration with unicycle at the hackday." /></p>

<p><img src="http://distilleryimage4.s3.amazonaws.com/da4b156aeed311e1aaa822000a1de2ba_7.jpg"
alt="Preparing unicycle for talk." /></p>

<p>I was still tweaking while the presentations were happening, but the demo
worked!</p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Coderace, and trying an Android phone for navigation]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/08/04/Coderace.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/08/04/Coderace.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2012-08-04T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/08/04/Coderace</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img width="640" src="http://www.coderace.co.uk/images/Event2012/Screenshot2.jpg" alt="Final game map" /></p>

<p>Today I participated in an event called <a
href="http://www.coderace.co.uk/">Coderace</a> with a team from the <a
href="http://edinburghhacklab.com/">Edinburgh Hacklab</a>.</p>

<p>The game used an Android app which showed points on a map. Each point had a
clue which could be answered using information available at the indicated
location, for example text on a sculpture or building. Cycling was recommend,
and all but one of us did. A car was used to reach the furthest points.</p>

<p>There were only two teams. The hacklab won 18 to 4, which was amusing because
we were not regular cyclists and the other team had people dressed up
as road racers.</p>

<p>It was sunny and ideal conditions for cycling. There were problems with the
application crashing, position tracking failing, and with phones but it mostly
worked. It was a good way to get some exercise and an idea of what can be done
with these devices. Thanks to Napier University for running it.</p>

<p><img width="640" src="http://www.coderace.co.uk/images/Event2012/DSC00459.JPG" alt="Bikes
and phones" /></p>

<p>I borrowed a phone for the game. My normal phone is a Sony Ericsson W800i and I
had never really used a smartphone before. I had been thinking about a general
purpose computing interface for my touring bike so it was interesting to try
an Android phone as this was one of the main ideas. I borrowed a Samsung
Galaxy S II (GT-I9100).</p>

<p>There were several problems, which without changing things make this system
rather poor. I could hardly see the screen in sunlight. My O2 connection only
allowed 50MB per day, and offered no option to pay for more. This was used in
1.5 hours of occasional map usage. I would think navigation with moving map
is a standard use case for these devices so clearly the limit is not enough
for normal use. The battery was also nearly flat after 1.5 hours, from a near
full charge. The battery in this phone is tiny compared to the screen size. It
seems that a solar or dynamo charging system is not just needed for extend off
grid operation but even when used in a city.</p>

<p>Mobile networks still don't get it when it comes to data. It used to be that
they charged about £3/MB, which is as good as infinite. I suspect what
happened is they had the idea people would want to use WAP and they made up a
price such that the per page cost was what they wanted. This of course made
the tariff useless for actual web browsing. I thought that with the
introduction of smart phones they would have sorted this out but although it's
an order of magnitude less bad it needs another two. The most they offer if
pre arranged is 1GB / month for £10.</p>

<p>And if you want to use it to navigate when cycling through more than one
country you can forget it - back to £3/MB, or something on the order of £1000
/ day. It would be possible if the maps are preloaded but still you can see
the situation is ridiculous.</p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Make a bicycle parking brake with inner tube]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/06/27/Bike-Inner-Tube-Handbrake.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/06/27/Bike-Inner-Tube-Handbrake.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2012-06-27T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/06/27/Bike-Inner-Tube-Handbrake</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Cut a piece of inner tube to make strong elastic bands. These can then be
used to hold the brake levers. This stops the steering from turning so the
bike does not fall over.</p>

<p><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8020/7454535600_ff5221bb02_z.jpg"
width="640" height="480" alt="Bicycle parking brake"></p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[HF Bicycle Mobile Experiment - Part 3 - Illustration]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2011/03/25/HF-Bicycle-Mobile-Experiment-Part-3.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2011/03/25/HF-Bicycle-Mobile-Experiment-Part-3.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2011-03-25T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2011/03/25/HF-Bicycle-Mobile-Experiment-Part-3</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today the unusually good weather required me to take the bike out for
a spin. I took some photos and video of the station while I was
out. It's described in more detail in <a rel="start"
href="/blog/2011/03/19/HF-Bicycle-Mobile-Experiment-Part-1.html">Part
1</a>.</p>

<iframe title="YouTube video player" width="480" height="390"
src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/4OeF0XLYJO8" frameborder="0"
allowfullscreen></iframe>


<p>Pay no attention to the audio behind the wind-noise - I think all I
said was that I was using the FT-817 and 5W.</p>

<p><img
src="http://farm6.static.flickr.com/5309/5557283960_fc600b3d91.jpg"
width="375" height="500" alt="HF Bike Mobile on Blackford Hill" /></p>

<p>15m 1/4 wave and 2 J-Pole. The latter is held together with masking
tape - I'll need to fix that better as well. Two sections of pole is
the minimum for the J-Pole. Three sections seems to be ok on most
roads. Four sections, as shown here, hits trees on some roads. It is
no higher than a bus though so should be ok on main roads.</p>

<p><img
src="http://farm6.static.flickr.com/5252/5557297492_6a1be9e006.jpg"
width="375" height="500" alt="101_0474.JPG" /></p>

<p>The ground tuning capacitor. Red goes to coax braid, yellow to frame.</p>

<p>Everything survived being bashed down the back of the hill, where
there are now steps, some of which I rode over. Low trees ripped off
the J-Pole though.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/58967572@N03/sets/72157626343215344/">More photos</a></p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[HF Bicycle Mobile Experiment - Part 2]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2011/03/21/HF-Bicycle-Mobile-Experiment-Part-2.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2011/03/21/HF-Bicycle-Mobile-Experiment-Part-2.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2011-03-21T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2011/03/21/HF-Bicycle-Mobile-Experiment-Part-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This evening I tested the antenna system described in my <a
rel="prev" href="/blog/2011/03/19/HF-Bicycle-Mobile-Experiment-Part-1.html">last
post</a>, as well as a 2m J-pole.</p>

<p>Immediately on leaving the house I was answered on 2m by GM8OTI. This
was an unexpectedly good start - most often when I have tried 2m bike
radio I get nothing. The J-Pole was probably much better than previous
antennas and he said he had seen my post on SOTA watch so was
expecting me. I extended only one section of the mast for the journey,
which was just enough for the J-pole.</p>

<iframe style="" width="425" height="350" frameborder="0"
scrolling="no" marginheight="0" marginwidth="0"
src="http://maps.google.co.uk/maps?f=q&amp;source=s_q&amp;hl=en&amp;geocode=&amp;q=&amp;sll=55.982293,-3.196529&amp;sspn=0.000407,0.00121&amp;gl=uk&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;t=h&amp;ll=55.982313,-3.196528&amp;spn=0.000263,0.00057&amp;z=20&amp;output=embed"></iframe>


<p>I planned to operate in the vicinity of Newhaven Lighthouse in the
hope that proximity to sea water would provide a good ground
plane. When I arrived at the lighthouse I could start operating very
quickly as I only had to extend the mast. This is in contrast to the
usual faff of setting up for <a href="/sota">SOTA</a> which involves guy lines.</p>

<p>The band (15 meters) sounded dead - I heard no stations at all. I
thought conditions must be bad but I tried calling CQ anyway and,
although rather slow, I got some results!</p>

<table>
<tr><th>Time</th> <th>f</th> <th>Station</th><th>Sent</th> <th>Received</th></tr>
<tr><td>~1830</td> <td>145.500</td> <td>GM8OTI</td> <td>59</td> <td>59-57</td></tr>
<tr><td>~1915</td> <td>21.280</td>  <td>GM8OTI</td> <td>21</td> <td>?</td></tr>
<tr><td>1929</td>  <td>21.280</td>  <td>KA1ANW</td> <td>57</td> <td>57</td> </tr>
<tr><td>1942</td>  <td>21.280</td>  <td>WD8BEY</td> <td>59</td> <td>59</td></tr>
<tr><td>2007</td>  <td>21.315</td>  <td>N8YHY</td>  <td>58</td> <td>59? Did not note</td></tr>
<tr><td>2009</td>  <td>21.290</td>  <td>C06LC</td>  <td>59</td> <td>59</td></tr>
</table>


<p>I had never heard the CO prefix before but didn't think much of it
until I got home and looked it up. QRZ.com tells me C06LC is in Cuba,
4441 miles away. I think voltage was down to about 10V or less at this
point so I probably wasn't even using the nominal 5W I usually
claim. I think that is my furthest contact - QRP or otherwise. It's at
least 888 miles / watt and probably over 1000.</p>

<p><img class="centre"
src="http://farm6.static.flickr.com/5016/5548844826_fa0f65df1a_z.jpg"
width="480" height="640" alt="Newhaven Lighthouse" title="Newhaven
Lighthouse" /></p>

<p>Effectiveness varied greatly with location. Near the lighthouse
was good but when I tried moving north west along the coast it was far
worse. I heard N8YHY at S1 - when I moved back to the lighthouse it
increased to S8.</p>

<p>I spent some time after these contacts listening on bands from 160m to
10m. I was surprised to hear stations on 160 meters with my short
antenna - one who sounded English on SSB and several morse which I
didn't try and decode. I also tried adding a miracle whip tuner. I
think it tuned on 17m and 20m but battery was now flat so could not
test properly.</p>

<p>It was generally a pleasant evening - warm and dry but windy. The sky
was clear giving good star display and a shooting star. There were
some very good photos I would like to have taken - with railings, bike
and mast in the foreground, lighthouse beyond that and stars behind -
but my camera phone was not up to the job. I was not, on this
occasion, questioned by police or public about my unusual activities,
nor about the fact my bike had wires on it. As we now know, <a
href="http://afp.google.com/article/ALeqM5i_pDxEAYSiWgBNlLs8ALAyGID7Lw">wires
are evil</a> unless they come in a box with the name of a big company
on it.</p>

<p>In conclusion, I declare this operation successful and intend to
experiment further.</p>

<div class="centre"> 
<img src="http://farm6.static.flickr.com/5103/5548844604_b085b8452f_z.jpg"
width="640" height="480" alt="Bicycle mobile - FT-817 in bar bag"
title="The clock is on GMT + 1 (local time was GMT)" />
</div>




<h3>Solar Data</h3>


<p> For future reference / comparison, the solar data
from N0NBH for this evening (2115 UTC I think it was but I can't find
historical data to check) was:</p>

<p>SFI 101
SN 47
A-Index 3
K-Index 1</p>

<p>15 meter conditions were pronounced to be fair.</p>

<p><a
rel="next" href="/blog/2011/03/25/HF-Bicycle-Mobile-Experiment-Part-3.html">Part
3 - Illustration - Photos and Video on Blackford Hill</a></p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[HF Bicycle Mobile Experiment - Part 1]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2011/03/19/HF-Bicycle-Mobile-Experiment-Part-1.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2011/03/19/HF-Bicycle-Mobile-Experiment-Part-1.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2011-03-19T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2011/03/19/HF-Bicycle-Mobile-Experiment-Part-1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today I decided to make an HF antenna for my bike. I did an experiment
with this once last year but it was not terribly successful. That
experiment used the <a href="http://www.g4ilo.com/atx.html">ATX
antenna</a>. No contacts were made but I learned something about
grounding.</p>

<p>I decided to use the frame as a ground. <a
href="http://www.qrz.com/callsign/G4AKC">G4AKC</a> says that this can
be improved by tuning the frame. I found that with a variable capacitor
in series with the frame I could adjust for low SWR with the ATX set
up as in the instructions. I can't remember what bands I tried it on.</p>

<p>The primary aim this time was to improve the ground. Last time, I had
a very temporary setup with croc clips to the frame so I decided to
improve it with fixed wires. I cleaned and sanded around a bolt on the
carrier and two brazons on the frame and connected the points with
some mains wire. I also attached a flexible wire to connect to the
antenna system.</p>

<p>While I was pondering how best to connect the aerial and earth with
the very limited selection of BNC parts I had I decided I might as
well make a proper antenna, which would make this easier. I took some
of the sections of the fishing pole I use for SOTA and duct taped them
to the carrier. The longest I thought I could reasonably get away with
was 4m which is what I used. I decided to use the lowest HF band I
could with the given antenna space, as the higher bands seem to be
open far less often, so I decided on a 1/4 wave for the 21MHz band.</p>

<p>I started with 3.5m of wire and found the tuning was way off. I
decided to try and tune it against a good earth so I drove in an earth
stake. This actually made it slightly worse. I then laid out three
radials and tried various combinations before giving up on finding an
improvement. I then started trying to tune to what I had. I had to cut
away quite a lot of wire but got the SWR down to 1.1. This was with
the capacitor in series with the frame.</p>

<p>I tied a SLAB to the carrier and put the FT-817 in the bar bag and set
off for a maiden voyage. The SWR remained constant despite shaking,
moving of antenna and presumably different ground, although I did only
go around the block. I could hear several American stations and one in
Africa but my CQs were not answered. Eventually though, some
unexpected success! I replied to N8RA in Connecticut and received a
(contest) 59. He had no trouble copying my callsign first time so it
must have been a reasonable signal. I tried for a while longer but
with no further contacts so stopped for the day.</p>

<h3>Future Work</h3>


<p>Some ideas:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Other bands - I think I can fit in 17m and 10m may be useful now too.</p></li>
<li><p>Replace top section of fibreglass and wire with bendy steel
wire. This should reduce wind resistance, weight and effect of
crashing into trees.</p></li>
<li><p>Try other earth tuning arrangements. Measure earth current -
possibly with a clip on ferrite transformer I got from the
electricity company.</p></li>
<li><p>Physical improvement - replace duct tape. I require a system
for easy removal, connection and disconnection. Must also be
weather, oil and dirt proof. Should not reduce load carrying
capacity of rack - needs to stay out the way of panniers.</p></li>
</ul>


<p><a
rel="next" href="/blog/2011/03/21/HF-Bicycle-Mobile-Experiment-Part-2.html">Part
2 - Testing by the Sea</a></p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
</feed>
