<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss">

  <title><![CDATA[Alistair MacLeod, MM0HAI: Posts tagged oaxaca]]></title>

  <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/tag/oaxaca/index.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mm0hai.net/"/>
  <updated>2013-05-24T23:14:00-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/tag/oaxaca</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alistair N. MacLeod]]></name>
  </author>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Babylon by Bus]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/03/18/Babylon-by-Bus.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/03/18/Babylon-by-Bus.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2013-03-18T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/03/18/Babylon-by-Bus</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When it came time to leave the Oaxaca Rainbow Gathering, we were offered a
lift up the road. This turned out to be in an orange VW Bus called Gail, with
a figurehead of a ginger woman painted on the spare wheel.</p>

<p>We were given a joining briefing. She runs on gas, oil and love. Normally she
has a driver, driver's assistant, navigator, and band who sit in the back. She
was certainly well used, and I can see that she really must be held together
with love, as the string may not otherwise have been strong enough. I can see
how you can love a bus like this. My dreads kept getting caught in something
on the roof. Maybe she wanted a lock of my hair. :)</p>

<p>As we went up the sandy road through the coconut palms a man told a travel
horror story, over the considerable noise of the engine.</p>

<p>We made it to the main road, and after saying hello to some people on another
bus, returned to Babylon on a bus where we had to pay a fare.</p>

<p>We arrived at Salina Cruz, and I went a bit mad. At the Rainbow I was eating
healthily, vegan food, no sugar or caffeine. Now there were bright lights,
food and smells. I thought I smelt popcorn. It was esquites - corn. I bought a
cup. Then I wanted to try everything I saw - ice cream, burgers, tortas,
coffee. I ate churros next, which are similar to donuts but shaped like a star
prism. I also drank coffee and ate a cheese torta which was recommended by a
local. I felt very strange and didn't stop talking until asleep on the bus
home to San Cristobal.</p>

<p>I would like to travel by hippie bus one day.</p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
</feed>
