<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss">

  <title><![CDATA[Alistair MacLeod, MM0HAI: Posts tagged oaxaca]]></title>

  <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/tag/oaxaca/index.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mm0hai.net/"/>
  <updated>2013-06-01T14:43:50-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/tag/oaxaca</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alistair N. MacLeod]]></name>
  </author>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Babylon by Bus]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/03/18/Babylon-by-Bus.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/03/18/Babylon-by-Bus.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2013-03-18T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/03/18/Babylon-by-Bus</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When it came time to leave the Oaxaca Rainbow Gathering, we were offered a
lift up the road. This turned out to be in an orange VW Bus called Gail, with
a figurehead of a ginger woman painted on the spare wheel.</p>

<p>We were given a joining briefing. She runs on gas, oil and love. Normally she
has a driver, driver's assistant, navigator, and band who sit in the back. She
was certainly well used, and I can see that she really must be held together
with love, as the string may not otherwise have been strong enough. I can see
how you can love a bus like this. My dreads kept getting caught in something
on the roof. Maybe she wanted a lock of my hair. :)</p>

<p>As we went up the sandy road through the coconut palms a man told a travel
horror story, over the considerable noise of the engine.</p>

<p>We made it to the main road, and after saying hello to some people on another
bus, returned to Babylon on a bus where we had to pay a fare.</p>

<p>We arrived at Salina Cruz, and I went a bit mad. At the Rainbow I was eating
healthily, vegan food, no sugar or caffeine. Now there were bright lights,
food and smells. I thought I smelt popcorn. It was esquites - corn. I bought a
cup. Then I wanted to try everything I saw - ice cream, burgers, tortas,
coffee. I ate churros next, which are similar to donuts but shaped like a star
prism. I also drank coffee and ate a cheese torta which was recommended by a
local. I felt very strange and didn't stop talking until asleep on the bus
home to San Cristobal.</p>

<p>I would like to travel by hippie bus one day.</p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Wind and Fire]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/03/17/Wind-and-Fire.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/03/17/Wind-and-Fire.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2013-03-17T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/03/17/Wind-and-Fire</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I could feel something today. Some energy in the air, like something was going
to happen. Everyone could feel it. The wind was building and shaking the
trees. It had been building for days.</p>

<p>The wind drove us to eat in a huddle in the camp, sensibly breaking the
protocol of eating in the exposed, sandblasted, main circle. It felt like a
tribe coming together in the face of adversity. It was. The wind blew all
night and bounced my hammock.</p>

<p>The next morning, I broke up with my girlfriend. We were sitting in camp. As I
was talking, something hit me in the back. A girl sat up in my hammock. My now
ex-gf left to make her own camp, and I talked to my friend.</p>

<p>She was sleeping there, she told me, on account of being very tired from the
previous night's activity. She had sex with a guy she liked, and the girl he
was with. She felt very free now. Free from jealousy, ego and social
limits. It sounds like it was a very liberating experience, and a cleansing
from the past. Past problems blown away with the wind.</p>

<p>Later, I was dwelling on the past. As I was thinking about what went wrong
with the gf, ruminating, a pan whacked me on the head. Stop it! Be present
now! The wind had blown it from the tree.</p>

<p>That night, there was an orange glow in the distance. With the wind coming
from there, it was not long before it brought the fire to the camp. Everyone
was driven out. Anything left behind was burnt. Many people lost things,
attachments maybe, and many moved on that morning.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8543751136/" title="DSCF3623 by
mm0hai, on Flickr"><img
src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8522/8543751136_b140416fd0_z.jpg"
width="640" height="480" alt="DSCF3623"></a></p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
</feed>
