<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss">

  <title><![CDATA[Alistair MacLeod, MM0HAI: Posts tagged belize]]></title>

  <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/tag/belize/index.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mm0hai.net/"/>
  <updated>2013-08-21T13:30:42-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/tag/belize</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alistair N. MacLeod]]></name>
  </author>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Belize]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/05/21/Belize.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/05/21/Belize.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2013-05-21T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/05/21/Belize</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Belize is mental, and I love it. This was one of my first thoughts on
arriving, and it basically stayed the same.</p>

<p>By mental, I mean the mixture of cultures, which can be quite
disorientating. When I first arrived, I knew that people were meant to speak
English, but I didn't quite believe it. I had been in Spanish speaking
countries for months, and had to remember to use English. When I first tried
it I was surprised that it worked.</p>

<p>In this country, I have cycled through a Menonite community with fancy modern
farming equipment and horse drawn buggies, where I ate a burger from "Fat
Boys" American fast food van. I was in the Mid-west, and an oil field. I
passed Santorini, a Greek island, then the Shanghai service station to a
Chinese hotel. Soon I reached the Caribbean where everyone called me Rasta
instead of Gringo, and I drank rum and went sailing from an island. Later I
cycled through Garifuna towns - black people from St Vincent, and later an
East Indian town. I saw no other white people in Dangringa - a Garifuna
town. In Belize, it would be helpful to know Chinese, and Kriol, and Garifuna.</p>

<p>Belize used to be British Honduras, and it still has the Queen on the
money. It is closer to the USA though, and is probably popular with Americans
because of the language. It's now a place where you can buy Cabdury's or
Hershey's, and choose between Oreos or Ginger Nuts and Bourbon biscuits. US
dollars are accepted everywhere, and are worth two Belize Dollars.</p>

<p>Belize is mostly jungle, which is filled with Mayan ruins, rivers and cave
systems. One day, I took a tour to the <a
href="/blog/2013/05/07/ATM-Cave.html">ATM Cave</a>.</p>

<p>I also stopped at the zoo briefly, initially for ice cream, but then I had a
look around too. It is an unusual zoo. All the animals are rescued, for example
from private captors who should not have had them or didn't want them
anymore. Also, they are in the area where they would normally live - they are
all native animals. I actually had a good feeling about the place.</p>

<p>Belize city, I was told to avoid because it is dangerous. I went through only
to get a ferry to Caye Calker, where I did some snorkelling.</p>

<p>I took a tour by sailing boat to the reef and saw various interesting animals,
like a sea turtle, sharks, rays, and a manatee. It took me a while to get used
to the gear but then I enjoyed seeing things I had never before. I recommend
this trip. Otherwise, I didn't like Caye Calker very much. It was far too
crowded, touristic, and expensive.</p>

<p>I think I would like to go back to Belize, either to explore the jungle, or by
sea around the cayes.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8805598786/" title="DSCF4600 by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8274/8805598786_fb68f00bda_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="DSCF4600"></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8737210820/" title="Arriving Caribbean Island, with bike by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7285/8737210820_0575be9bd9_z.jpg" width="480" height="640" alt="Arriving Caribbean Island, with bike"></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8736198721/" title="DSCF4534 by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7287/8736198721_cd501ac959_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="DSCF4534"></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8800093221/" title="DSCF4690 by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2883/8800093221_5ebc9725a0_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="DSCF4690"></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8800062227/" title="DSCF4672 by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3734/8800062227_d263fb0e4a_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="DSCF4672"></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8810633594/" title="DSCF4669 by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5332/8810633594_f7114b047e_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="DSCF4669"></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8799626577/" title="DSCF4624 by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3669/8799626577_9760dacabe_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="DSCF4624"></a></p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[An emotional day]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/05/15/An-Emotional-Day.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/05/15/An-Emotional-Day.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2013-05-15T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/05/15/An-Emotional-Day</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I thought this day might be interesting as an example of some thoughts and
feelings experienced during a day of cycle touring.</p>

<p>This morning I left a hostel where I had been staying for several days. I
didn't miss it, but when leaving somewhere I usually do think about what I
might not have done there that I might have liked to do. Also, I am usually
slightly anxious about leaving something. I check several times that I haven't
left anything.</p>

<p>I went to the post office to send a letter and post card. The pretty stamps
made me happy, as did completing a task. Then I had breakfast at "Amor y
Cafe". They lived up to their name with some heart shaped ice cubes made of
coffee. I liked that, but was not totally relaxed because I didn't want to
miss the boat back to the mainland.</p>

<p>The sea is beautiful around there - mostly green, not blue - and I enjoyed the
ride back. I had a lunch sandwich and spoke a little to the guy at my table in
the ferry terminal. I had decided earlier that I would try and hitchhike to
Belmopan. I had already cycled this road, and where I was could be considered
a side trip, so this would not compromise a claim of having cycled all the way
south, and I didn't want to cycle this road again. It was not too bad, but I
had seen it before and it was not very interesting. I thought hitching a lift
would be easy because people in Belize are generally friendly, and I think
interested in the cyclist they see. More than one person I have met has said
they saw me cycling at some point. It is a small country with few roads.</p>

<p>Anyway, my expectation of it being easy was exceeded - the man asked me if I
wanted to stay at his place in Belmopan before I asked anything. I mentioned
hitchhiking and he offered a lift, which I accepted. So I didn't even mount the
bike before I got a lift, and it was to nearly exactly where I wanted to go.</p>

<p>When we got going I was really happy. I enjoyed moving so fast,
effortlessly. I felt the universe was looking after me today, in providing
exactly what I asked for. I laughed to myself at the drivers singing to the
radio.</p>

<p>I had offered him some money when he filled up petrol in Belize City. Around
here, at least in most other Central American countries, I believe pure
hitchhiking is not common. People generally expect to be paid what it would
cost in a bus. Busses here are really cheap, so I was thinking of offering a
couple of dollars. He said when we arrived I could give him something
depending on my means.</p>

<p>We arrived and he asked for money. I offered Quetzales, which I didn't need,
and thought he would because he travelled to Guatemala often. He said he
didn't want them, and wanted trustworthy currencies. He must have seen my
emergency 100 EUR not in my wallet, because he then asked for Euros. I offered
three dollars, and he said he wanted 20. 20 would pay for a bus journey to
Guatemala, about four times the distance we just did. This didn't seem like
the deal I was expecting. In the end I gave him ten, which I think is about
double what the bus would have cost. He then walked away without saying
anything.</p>

<p>I cycled off, but had a bad feeling now. I couldn't quite work out why to
start with. Initially I kept checking and rechecking I hadn't lost anything -
things that might have fallen off in his car, or been taken my his friend when
we were at the shop near the house we stopped at. I finally convinced myself I
had everything, but still had a bad feeling. After further thinking, I worked
out that the source of this feeling was seeing that man again. I knew if I did
it would be a bad thing. Either me returning because I had lost something,
which I had now ruled out, or him coming down the road to rob me. I remembered
that the first thing he asked in the cafe was how much did my bike cost. That
is always an unpleasant question. Then he had seen I had a lot of money, and
was demanding it. He know where I was going. Maybe he would get back in the
car later, maybe at dusk with his mate, and come for my bike and money.</p>

<p>Then I started to have other thoughts, like what if I had been drugged. I
didn't think he really had a good opportunity to do this - it is a pretty
unlikely thing. I was being a bit paranoid now, but that is the point of this
story, to show how some emotions can occur and probably be rather too
strong. I was thinking about this because I had heard stories about the use of
a drug on travellers that makes them like zombies. They will then do what they
are told by the attacker, such as taking all the money out their bank account
and giving it to them. Someone I met in Oaxaca said this happened to him, and
the internet claims it is true also. I was feeling a bit funny too. Maybe I
was drugged - by myself with an unaccustomed amount of caffeine this morning.</p>

<p>At one point I remembered an idea a fellow traveller was talking about -
teleportation. If you had a teleporter, would you use it when travelling? I
felt that if I had it, I would right now jump to Edinburgh and not come back
till the morning, or maybe 24hours later to preserve a sort of continuity of
my journey.</p>

<p>Later, once I had examined and realised the source of the emotion - seeing the
man again, I could work out a logical solution to the problem. I was concerned
about being attacked on the road at dusk, so I only needed to find a really
good hidden campsite well before it got dark. Around here, that should not be
too hard. I suddenly felt much better.</p>

<p>Now I started to realise where I was. I became present. I noticed the beauty
of the forest I was cycling through. It was quite unlike the Selva Lacandon -
it was more open and pretty. I noticed the different coloured flowers. Then I
noticed the air. I really started to feel the air - a thick, significant
substance through which I moved, and I thought about how it came from the
trees. I considered how the air and the trees and everything are linked.</p>

<p>Not too much later, I saw a potentially good camp site. I stopped by the road
for a while to consider my location and possible distance for tomorrow, and
decide whether to stop here. I did.</p>

<p>I went into an orange grove. It looks like a really good campsite, because the
trees provide excellent cover from the road. Also, between the trees is
relatively flat ground where I could push the bike easily, and even cycle on a
track initially, so I got off the road fast and was not seen.</p>

<p>I was still not relaxed though, because I had various things to do before it
gets dark. Ideally I want to be in the hammock before dark, to avoid the
mosquitoes, and so that I can see to avoid snakes and spiders. There are some
very poisonous snakes all around Central America. So I cooked, brushed my
teeth, made tea and put up the hammock. Tonight I was pleased with myself
because I got everything squared away. The only things not packed in their
place on the bike now are my hammock, computer, which I'm using in the hammock
now, and clothes and shoes which I will put on in the morning.</p>

<p>I'm relatively relaxed in the hammock now, but somewhat alert to vehicle
noise. A vehicle playing music sounded like it stopped near here for a
while. I became concerned that it was a farmer going to come done the track I
did earlier, or maybe someone had seen the light of my computer screen (quite
unlikely} so I closed the computer and listened for a while. Then it moved on.</p>

<p>There we have a day of cycle touring. From a fairly neutral start, to something
approaching joy at a car ride, to fear and paranoia and wanting to magically
be somewhere else caused by a slight suspicion, to presence and joy in nature,
to relative, but wary calm in a campsite.</p>

<p>I think a lot of this would be easier if I had a friend with me. It would
allow a second opinion on the analysis of situations - did that guy seem
dodgy to you too? It would probably also reduce fear - having some backup in
case of a fight. I'm coming around to the idea of cycling with someone
else. Maybe if I decide to do so, the universe will provide.</p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Chino]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/05/09/Chino.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/05/09/Chino.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2013-05-09T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/05/09/Chino</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8732330809/" title="DSCF4447 by
mm0hai, on Flickr"><img
src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7289/8732330809_b85b9f81b6_z.jpg"
width="640" height="480" alt="DSCF4447"></a></p>

<p>I passed the Shanghai service station. This was after all the Chinese
shops. Nearly all the shops are Chinese. Belmopan is a dump (I'm in Belize
now). I read there was not much there but government buildings, but there
really is nothing. I was expecting at least a zocalo and a coffee shop. No.</p>

<p>I found the "Eastern Guest House" - the English translation under the
Chinese. The concrete floor was covered in ripped plastic, hair and dirt. I
wheeled my bike in, with the Chinese cow still hanging on the back. The
bathroom hadn't been cleaned. I brushed my teeth with Chinese toothpaste.</p>

<p>In the morning, I left. I should have made more effort to learn Chinese from
Fengqin, then I could have asked for directions to somewhere for breakfast. I
only knew how to ask for the cat temple.</p>

<p>Later I passed Japan, and Santorini, a Greek island. I sat down in a restaurant
to Caribbean food and Spanish conversation at the neighbouring table.</p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bella]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/05/09/Bella.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/05/09/Bella.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2013-05-09T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/05/09/Bella</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I stayed at Bella's hostel in San Ignacio. My room had the feel of a log
cabin, with a bookshelf beside my bed. It was built to a design, not bashed
together like the constructions I was used to in Guatemala. One night became
three. "Stand in your truth", said a fairy in the bathroom.</p>

<p>I was invited to visit the farm. It was down a road which headed into the
jungle, but here was mostly farms. The government gives away land here at
election time, if you vote, or if you don't want land you can have money. If
I'd gone further, I'd have reached an army base ("bring cigarettes and rum")
and later Caracol, a Mayan ruin. I stopped at the farm.</p>

<p>Ernest, a very friendly and relaxed, presumably Garifuna, man gave me a tour
of the medicine trail. This was a path through the jungle with signs on many
plants with medicinal uses. I picked some leaves which I later used to make a
poultice for the wounds on my feet. I also met the pig, who was very happy and
wagged his tail when sprayed with water from the hose. I saw some pineapples
growing on the ground, and plenty of chickens.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8729834116/" title="DSCF4269 by
mm0hai, on Flickr"><img
src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7425/8729834116_0b8c5e1b18_z.jpg"
width="480" height="640" alt="DSCF4269"></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/8730258925/" title="DSCF4372 by
mm0hai, on Flickr"><img
src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7459/8730258925_121581df05_z.jpg"
width="640" height="480" alt="DSCF4372"></a></p>

<p>I spent the rest of the evening lying in a hammock at the top of the hill
above the river. Not much happened. The sheep grazed. The sun set behind the
hill.</p>

<p>Bella wasn't the woman who seemed to run the hostel, or the crazy skankin
rastaman who helped. It turned out Bella was a beautiful little rasta
girl. She ran around and cartwheeled through the kitchen, with dreads
flying. "Do you do your dreads yourself?", I asked. "No, my mum does. I see
you <em>try</em>". I got out the crochet hook and worked with that while I
watched Forest Gump. "I just felt like running." I just felt like cycling.</p>

<p>In the morning I didn't leave at 5am, as would be sensible to avoid the heat
when cycling. I spent some time sitting by the river, meditating, and
listening to the birds. I heard a toucan, and the screeching one which sounds
like a piezo buzzer. The turtles were hiding, or maybe they were all on the
wall at the hostel, where their backs painted in rasta colours told everyone
to "DO YOUR DISHES".</p>

<p>I'm en route to Caye Calker now. Maybe I'll visit Bella's hostel there.</p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Actun Tunichil Muknal (ATM) Cave]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/05/07/ATM-Cave.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/05/07/ATM-Cave.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2013-05-07T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/05/07/ATM-Cave</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In Belize, I went on a tour of the <a
href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Actun_Tunichil_Muknal">Actun Tunichil Muknal
(ATM)</a> cave, which I had seen mentioned on a crazyguy blog. I was shocked
at the price, $100US, especially after having come from Mexico, but I did it
anyway because of the rave reviews on trip adviser.</p>

<p>After a short walk on a well beaten path through the jungle we, a group of 8,
arrived at an area with some palapas and firepits. Then we went down to the
river which was flowing out of the cave. It was a bit cold in the water, and
after the entrances, totally dark. It is limestone and has formed all sorts of
interesting formations. In some parts it sparkles, I think with quartz.</p>

<p>After a while we climbed up to a dry part of the cave. Here there are many
pieces of Mayan pottery, and bones. It seems they conducted ceremonies here,
probably to ask gods for help in times of need. They believe caves are a
gateway to the afterlife.</p>

<p>The grand finale of the tour is the skeleton called the Crystal Maiden. It has
been fused with the floor by the limestone, and it sparkles.</p>

<p><img width="640"
src="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/5/54/Actun_Tunichil_Muknal.jpg"
alt="Crystal Maiden, ATM Cave" title="Crystal Maiden, ATM Cave. Photo by Peter
Andersen, licence details at
http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:Actun_Tunichil_Muknal.jpg"></p>

<p>I think I liked seeing the cave itself more than any of the archaeology in
particular. The rock formations were very varied, interesting and impressive.
Of course, because this was a tour group we were not really experiencing any
of this at its best.</p>

<p>The right way to visit this cave would be to go with some friends, probably at
night, not that it matters inside, and experience it, not be told about it. It
is not a place for talking, it is a place to feel. It should be a place to
explore your mind and soul. It would be enhanced greatly by finding some local
psychedelic - possibly consult a shaman or priest if such a person still
exists around there, and by fire. They don't allow fire now to preserve the
cave, but I feel like it is very important. This could be a life changing
experience, and you would see it as the Mayans did.</p>

<p>I said before it was cold in the cave, but not just physically. It is a deep,
dark place of the dead, or the never alive, or wondering if you are or not,
and of time disappearing.</p>

<p>I found it reassuring that there were some women in our group. I think because
they seemed alive, and can make new life. I was relived when I exited the cave
and could see the sun again and feel the warmth. The world was still
there. Exiting this cave is like being born again, or knowing you are alive
again.</p>

<p>There was some life in the cave. A tiny green shoot with one leave was growing
in a corner of a passage. The guide thought it lived on the light from our
headlamps.</p>

<h3>Aside, on Conservation</h3>

<p>I was considering the balance beetween conservation and use. The best way to
conserve it is to let noone in, but then there is no point. If noone sees it,
it makes no difference if it is destroyed or not. I don't think use of this
cave should be stopped now - our civilisation may even benefit from it more
than the Maya. Study it thoroughly, then allow people to use it. This won't
happen as long as someone is making a lot of money from controlling access,
though.</p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
</feed>
