<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss">

  <title><![CDATA[Alistair MacLeod, MM0HAI: Posts tagged shit]]></title>

  <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/tag/shit/index.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mm0hai.net/"/>
  <updated>2013-10-13T00:41:12-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/tag/shit</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alistair N. MacLeod]]></name>
  </author>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Mother Aya, Aunt Jurema]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/08/05/Mother-Aya.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/08/05/Mother-Aya.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2013-08-05T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/08/05/Mother-Aya</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/9497148473/" title="Magic Potions
from the Rainforest by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img
src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7439/9497148473_c779f76ed7_z.jpg"
width="640" height="480" alt="Magic Potions from the Rainforest"></a></p>

<p>Burning bush? Yes, you can talk with plants.</p>

<p>It tasted like black treacle, but sweeter, and with a hint of marmite.</p>

<p>I had read "DMT: The Spirit Molecule", and wondered if I would experience any
of the common patterns. Maybe I would meet alien entities, or find myself in a
nursery. Maybe I would learn the secrets of the universe. What is its true
nature? What is it all about?</p>

<p>I started to feel the effect of the Ayahuasca in my body after the first dose,
but did not notice any mental effect until shortly after the second, which was
double the size and washed down with a glass of the bitter, astringent,
Jurema. I am wary of mixing things, especially if I've not had them before,
but these plants both contain the same chemically active ingredient, DMT, and
spiritually I guess they are sisters so I thought they would be able to get
along.</p>

<p>At first all was black, but then colour noise appeared - red, green and blue
dots, always switching on and off. Then these formed into lines, which made up
constantly changing shapes. They were square and triangular and zig
zag. Seemed quite binary, angular, computer generated. The lines were in
rainbow colours, the rainbows moved and sparkled. It was very beautiful. With
open eyes, the picture seem quantised into simpler geometrical shapes. Leaves
and gaps between them angular, and they moved like an animation with
insufficient framerate. The images were very beautiful, and if I would have
noticed pain, my face would probably have been hurting from smiling.</p>

<p>I enjoyed this a lot, but I didn't just want pretty pictures. I wanted to
learn something. I said this and asked, "what can you show me?". I didn't get
a direct answer - no voice or character speaking to me - but the answer became
obvious. You are a baby. You know nothing about how the world works. You're
not ready for that sort of thing. Here - play with the pretty sparklies. I
realised I knew nothing, and I might as well enjoy it. When I accepted it, I
realised that being a baby is wonderful. You don't need to do anything or
worry about anything. You are looked after. Like any mother, Mother Aya just
wants her babies to healthy and happy.</p>

<p>I thought I was just happy because of the beauty, but then I realised it was
not just beauty, it was love. I thought I was loving the pictures, but then I
realised that was ridiculous - I am just a tiny spec - almost nothing - how
could I produce so much love? It was clear that this was all there - an
immense field of love - is this what everything is made of? I could only bathe
in it.</p>

<p>Ayahuasca is what is politely called purgative, or cleansing. I was sick
once. When I crawled out of the circle to vomit I felt like a snake. It was
worse for the boy next to me though, who had diarrhoea which at one point
splatted on my face. At first I tried to work out some way in which that had
not actually just happened, but my attempt to deny reality was clearly not
going to work.</p>

<p>There was a lesson though. I had been thinking earlier about how a baby has an
easy life, but it does things like shitting and pissing everywhere. Now I
experienced that this is not always enjoyable for everyone else who has to be
around it. While it is good and right to be a baby when you have to, when you
can you should grow up. I saw birds hatching and flying and making new nests.</p>

<p>I think it is clear that humans as a race are babies. How can we be told the
secrets of the universe when we can't even look after ourselves? We are
shitting all over this planet and can't even feed ourselves without making
such a mess that it will kill us all and everything else that lives
here. Maybe in a few million years, if we survive that long, we will will be
ready to understand.</p>

<p>I asked someone to heat water for me so I could wash my hair and face. Someone
else fed me chocolate. I could enjoy being looked after a little more, but
tomorrow I must grow up.</p>
]]></content>
   <georss:point>8.764126 -83.014069</georss:point>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Intimate Shitting]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/23/Intimite-Shitting.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/23/Intimite-Shitting.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2012-12-23T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/12/23/Intimite-Shitting</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<!--- date approximate -->


<p>Someone told me one special Rainbow experience I had to have was sharing a
shit pit. She said if you haven't been elbow to elbow with someone on the next
trench then you don't know them, or something like that.</p>

<p>Ten minutes later I was using the shit pit and someone came along and asked if
he could join me, so I said yes. Of everyone this could have been, he was a
nurse, and apart, therefore, from being an expert on shit, he seemed to have a
particular interest.</p>

<p>Unprovoked, he explained his ideas. He thought illness could be a beautiful
thing because an inability to do things yourself such as wiping your bum means
you must become closer to other people. He thought illnesses were for a
reason, and must teach you something or have some benefit.</p>

<p>Another nurse I spoke to said she hated wiping bums. She quit to go
travelling.</p>

<p>I'm afraid I didn't take a photo for this post.</p>
]]></content>
   <georss:point>17.483017 -91.925139</georss:point>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
