<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss">

  <title><![CDATA[Alistair MacLeod, MM0HAI: Posts tagged serbla]]></title>

  <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/tag/serbla/index.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mm0hai.net/"/>
  <updated>2013-04-09T01:52:52-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/tag/serbla</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alistair N. MacLeod]]></name>
  </author>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Living and Travelling without Money]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/08/11/Living-for-Free.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/08/11/Living-for-Free.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2012-08-11T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/08/11/Living-for-Free</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Many people assume that travel is expensive, but it doesn't need to be. I
wintered in the Canary Islands for three months and spent almost nothing. It's
just a matter of learning how to live without using money. You won't be
staying in five star hotels all the time, but it is quite possible to be happy
and there are actually many advantages of a money free lifestyle.</p>

<p>Without money, I think you are likely to meet more people, see more of the
places you travel to, and learn more. If you stay in an hotel and go on guided
tours you see the inside of an hotel and meet tourists. Then you come home a
week later because you can't afford any more and you think you've got to do
some job you would rather not be doing right then. If you sleep on a beach, in
a cave, or even on the street you will certainly have a more interesting
experience. You'll probably meet other travellers or locals who can help you
with things and show you interesting places.</p>

<p>Money forces things. This is maybe ok if you know exactly what you want all
the time, but you probably don't. The most obvious example is where to go. I
left Edinburgh with the idea of going to Patagonia. If I had bought a flight,
I would have gone straight there. I attempted to hitchhike, and because I was
not successful I had other adventures and learnt and did things which I might
not have otherwise. I think what should have happened did. Things tend to work
out for the best.</p>

<p>I think I'll write separately about the practicalities of living without
money. The main expenses which need to be removed are accommodation, <a
href="/blog/2012/08/12/Free-Food.html">food</a>, and transport. For now I'll
cover more general ideas.</p>

<h2>"The bare necessities of life will come to you."</h2>

<p>I've worked some of this out for myself on my recent travels, but I'm hardly
unique in doing so. First, I'll tell you a story. I met a guy in Las Palmas
called Toto. He helped me at a lower point with his story.</p>

<p>A few years ago he left home with 20 euros and his bike. Since then he has
travelled round the world. He sailed from Australia to Europe, then to the
Caribbean and back to Europe, and probably other places he didn't talk
about. He did some busking and when I met him had 100 euros. He didn't have
any special performing skill, he just did some silly dance. It's not really
important where he went, the story is that this is possible.</p>

<p>"Even if I only ate bread one day it doesn't matter, maybe I'll find something
else the next day."</p>

<p>I met another guy who makes a bit of money from playing music on the
street. You might call him homeless if you saw him, but since I've been back
in Edinburgh working on my geek bike project, he's been flying all over
Europe. He's probably happier than most people who work in an office.</p>

<p>It is important to be positive. You'll be interacting with people for things
like hitchhiking, and people like happy people. "You won't get a boat with a
sad face." It's also important for your own motivation.</p>

<h2>The kindness of Strangers</h2>

<p>When I was in the marina one day I went and said hello to some people. After I
short conversation I had to go and buy some food. They said no, you don't need
to, we have food. I was reluctant to take it from people who may need to more
than me but they insisted and later I found it is not really in short supply.</p>

<p>On La Palma I wanted some sort of shelter to take walking with me in the
wetter Northern part of the island. I mentioned this to someone I had just met
and so within a few minutes of meeting he had lent me his tent and a better
sleeping bag. I nearly skipped over the fact that this happened in a house I
was staying in - where I had been invited to stay by someone else I had just
met. There are many more examples but you'll need to read them in my other
blov entries when I get round to writing more.</p>

<h2>What you do need money for</h2>

<p>Basically, it comes down to convenience and speeding things up. There are a
few things you probably need it for though.</p>

<p>If you want food, you don't need money. If you want something particular to
eat, you'll probably need to buy it. If you want something now, you need to
buy it. If you can wait until you find it in a skip, you don't. If you have
time to hitchhike, you'll get there in the end. If you want to go now, you
have to pay for a bus. Of course, if you don't know where you are going,
hitchhiking is better anyway.</p>

<p>Things you pretty much do need money for are transport, some foods, and
medicines. Sometimes you might need to pay for transport: a ferry, for
example. It's very rare to find certain things in a bin, e.g. alcohol, coffee,
cooking oil, dried foods, and things with a long sell by date, but you can
live without these.</p>

<p>This post is rather unfocused because I have a lot to say on this subject and
I'm just trying to get some ideas out for now. Hopefully it is enough to show
you that this is possible. If you go out into the world with nothing but a
good attitude and an open mind you'll probably do very well.</p>

<p>I'll end with a particularly impressive story from a friend, and a link to
another blog post about this sort of thing, "<a
href="http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=18463814">The
Universe Is Conspiring to Help Us".</a></p>

<blockquote><p>"The magic is FULL ON when u arrive in a city and we have no where to sleep
and a beautiful girl called Ling comes up to u and says: I heard u play music
its is beautiful! Do u have anywhere to sleep? U can have my apartment for the
weekend when i go visit my boyfriend! So she gave us the key. AMAZING
LIFE!!!"</p></blockquote>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Love and Light as a Service]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/08/05/Love-and-Light-as-a-Service.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/08/05/Love-and-Light-as-a-Service.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2012-08-05T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/08/05/Love-and-Light-as-a-Service</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I was walking with a girl in Maspalomas and discussing the squatting and
recycling lifestyle when a tourist turned round and gave her €20. We don't
know why.</p>

<p>I asked her how she felt about taking money for nothing. I don't really like
the idea. She argued that she did not just take from the conventional society,
but provided some value, by spreading love and light.</p>

<p>Initially I thought this sounded like ridiculous hippie nonsense but later I
came to think that it is true. I think most people, ultimately, just want to be
happy. One thing that I find makes me happy is being around happy people.</p>

<p>I believe there is a French saying that "there is only one smile". When
someone sees the smile, zie then smiles, and so the smile is passed on. Thus a
pool of unfettered happy people should help to support global happiness.</p>

<p>I think the world would be a much better place if there were more people who
dedicated themselves to happiness. What else is life for?</p>

<p>So what about a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cloud_computing">Cloud
based</a> Love &amp; Light <a
href="https://www.google.co.uk/search?q=as+a+service">service</a>? I suppose
that's going to be called heaven.io and have plenty of node.js and rounded
corners.</p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Bulgarian]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2011/12/01/The-Bulgarian.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2011/12/01/The-Bulgarian.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2011-12-01T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2011/12/01/The-Bulgarian</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We walked in the sand, on wasteland at the top of the city. Around and below
us, I saw towerblocks, houses, the sea. Grass and brick in the sand. Above,
the night sky. It was warm, dark and timeless.</p>

<p>I was with The Bulgarian; I saw him, at least. He wore black, a black cloth on
his head. Round his neck, a white towel with coloured spots. He carried a
large teddy bear he had found somewhere.</p>

<p>The Bulgarian vomited.</p>

<p>"I thought you were a ghost. I thought you were my guide to see the aliens."</p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Welcome to Serendipitous Blaggagio]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2011/11/15/Serendipitous-Blaggagio.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2011/11/15/Serendipitous-Blaggagio.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2011-11-15T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2011/11/15/Serendipitous-Blaggagio</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I had a fairly normal life in Edinburgh. I worked as a software engineer from
Monday to Friday and lived in a <a
href="/blog/2011/07/26/Living.html">house</a>. I felt stuck.</p>

<p>I had read Into the Wild a while before - in which Christopher McCandless
decides after university to burn all his money and travel as a tramp around
America. He liked wilderness and ended up in Alaska, where he starved to
death. This was one thing which gave me inspiration to go travelling.</p>

<p>I also seem to like remote places. Scotland is actually quite good for this
given its size: I had walked in the Fisherfield Forest and Knoydart, and
visited Sandwood Bay on the North West coast. When I was there I wanted to
stay and try to live there for a while, by fishing and maybe in time farming,
but I had a job in Edinburgh pulling me back. On my to-visit list are
Antarctica, Siberia (with Samoyeds), Mongolia (by bike I think) and now
Alaska. The middle of the Atlantic is also a pretty remote place.</p>

<p><img
src="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/b/b6/Sandwood_Bay_North_View.jpg"
alt="Sandwood Bay" title="Sandwood Bay. Yes, Scotland." /></p>

<p>I had also done some sailing recently, around Scottish islands and Wales. I
thought then about going further and crossing the Atlantic.</p>

<p>Another source of inspiration for another life was Steve Roberts, the <a
href="http://microship.com/bike/index.html">Technomad</a>. I am a geek of
computing and radio and found his website when looking for designs for <a
href="/blog/2011/03/25/HF-Bicycle-Mobile-Experiment-Part-3.html">bicycle
mounted HF antenna systems</a>. He travelled round the USA for years on a bike
fitted with computer and radio systems. I have done some bike touring in
Europe and I thought about building a bike like this myself to go further.</p>

<p>Finally, while at work in Edinburgh I was reading In Patagonia, by Bruce
Chatwin. I realised it was wrong to stay in Edinburgh and Scotland for so long
and I should stop thinking and go out and see these places. The ideas of
sailing the Atlantic and travelling in Patagonia came together.</p>

<p>I resigned and started planning my trip. I heard that many boats cross from Las
Palmas de Gran Canaria so I flew there to look for a boat.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/58967572@N03/6431731859/" title="Cloud computing, or stupid things to carry to 6000ft by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7023/6431731859_5862ee9677_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="Cloud computing, or stupid things to carry to 6000ft"></a></p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
</feed>
