<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss">

  <title><![CDATA[River MacLeod, MM0HAI: Posts tagged serbla]]></title>

  <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/tag/serbla/index.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mm0hai.net/"/>
  <updated>2013-10-16T02:45:28-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/tag/serbla</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[River MacLeod]]></name>
  </author>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Cycles Closing in Colombia]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/10/12/Cycles-Closing-Colombia.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/10/12/Cycles-Closing-Colombia.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2013-10-12T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/10/12/Cycles-Closing-Colombia</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I keep finding myself talking about things which happened in the Canary
Islands. It's at least partly because many things started there, and now they
are coming to some completion.</p>

<p>I went to the Canaries to try and hitch a lift on a boat to South America. I
didn't manage that, but nearly two years later, I arrived in Colombia on a
sailing catamaran.</p>

<p>When I was in La Tomatera, Las Palmas de Gran Canaria, I learned to make
macramé, and started to decorate my computer power cable. On the boat to
Colombia, I finished it. About half an hour after completion, the cable
failed. It held out just long enough to allow me to complete it.</p>

<p>I also made a bracelet, which I have worn permanently since then. Today, I
gave it away to a stranger I met on the metro in Medellín, Colombia. I really
don't know why. I didn't know her name, and do not expect to see her again. I
said she could have it if she could get it off. The knot untied.</p>

<p>Now I think where that bracelet had been - so many places. Beaches, mountains,
cities, forests. Up to about 35,000 feet, and down to 30 meters under the
sea. Boats, trains, cars, planes, and of course the bike. Three continents,
and two oceans, and too many islands to remember. Many beds and hammocks, of
which most mine. But this is all past. I shouldn't be dwelling on it. I am
here now.</p>

<p>In Las Palmas, I learned to make dreadlocks and had one made for me. In Costa
Rica, I made one for someone.</p>

<p>In Costa Rica also, I ate fruit given to us, the rainbow caravan, by market
sellers. Today, in Colombia, I bought some bananas and gave them to a beggar
who told me she was hungry, and whom I saw foraging unsuccessfully near the
river, where there are some banana plants.</p>

<p>I have been cycling my bike. Maybe that will end soon too. I don't know, that
is for the future.</p>
]]></content>
   <georss:point>8.857256 -75.635376</georss:point>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Dreads]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/07/12/Dreads.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/07/12/Dreads.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2013-07-12T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/07/12/Dreads</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I have dreadlocks. The first one appeared on the 1st of December 2011. They
are more interesting than just hair, and I am still learning from them.</p>

<p>Not many people in Scotland have dreads. One of the first times I remember
seeing them was at my first university mountaineering club meet. She had long
blonde dreads. I didn't know what to think - I didn't think - but I felt like
she was some magical creature from another dimension.</p>

<p>When I went to the Canary Islands a few years later, I met lots of dready
travellers. One morning, I woke up on the beach. I washed my hair and applied
conditioner and hairbrush to stop it knotting itself up. This was rather a
fuss. Other people just got up and were ready.</p>

<p>I noticed some other practical advantages. They are a good way of identifying
people who might be interesting to talk to. There is a good chance someone
with dreads is a fellow traveller, or will know things like where to get free
food and good places to sleep, where the squats are, and the local juggling
club. It's sort of like a club itself - when you notice other people with
dreads on the street, you can say hi.</p>

<p>In Belize I discovered it's a bit more than that, because people think you are
Rasta. Many people confuse the terms, and call the hair "rastas". Really,
Rasta is a religion, and dreadlocks are commonly worn by people who follow
it. You can have dreads without being Rasta though, and you can be Rasta
without dreads. It's probably better not to argue though, when someone is so
happy to meet a Rastaman, and blesses you in the name of Jah.</p>

<p>I think Belize must have some of the friendliest beggars in the world. "When I
see you I don't see a white man. I see a brother from another mother." Yes, he
then asked me for money, but I don't think it totally invalidates what he was
saying. As the only white man in some of the places I visited, the locks made
me feel a bit more comfortable, and perhaps the locals where a bit friendlier
because of it. I don't know for sure, of course.</p>

<p>I never really decided to get dreads, but I was thinking about it and
mentioned it to people. One night in the marina in Las Palmas, the night
before Mariella was going to sea, heading for another continent, she took a
wooden bead from her hair and gave it to me, "for when you get dreads". I
asked her to braid it in for the moment, but she actually made my first dread
while we sat on a boat under the stars. The rest followed. Many of them were
made by friends, and they are named after them.</p>

<p>There are other ways they record memories. I have other beads in my hair, and
know where they came from. Some are ferrite cores from a recycled computer in
La Tomatera, a wonderful squat I lived in for a while. I remember hacking the
machine apart, and wrapping enameled magnet wire around someone else's hair.</p>

<p>A guy who made one of my dreads swaps his with people. They cut one off, swap
and reattach with a crochet hook. When we met, he had thirteen different
people's hair on his head. The variety of colours looked beautiful, and each
was a memory and a connection to a friend.</p>

<p>Dreads are like living things. They grow and change. They develop kinks and
twists, or straighten and flatten. They can join together or be split
apart. They also look like leaves, or grass, or tree branches or coral. They
exhibit gnarl.</p>

<p>There is a saying, that dreads grow in, not just out of your head. They grow
into your brain. People see you differently, and this no doubt changes your
behaviour. I started eating a vegan diet a few months after getting dreads. I'm
not saying dreads caused a diet change, but maybe they are somewhat related.</p>

<p>I think dreads are strongly associated with spiritual, or conscious people. By
conscious, I mean people who do things having given thought to their effects,
rather than by default. Food is a good example - I find it slightly strange
when I see someone with dreads eating meat. This also means doing things
because you think they are right, not because society told you to. Many parts
of society would avoid someone with dreads, for example I guess it would be
harder to get some jobs. This also shows commitment to doing what is right -
not sacrificing principles for money. Someone told me that in India, if you
dreads are long enough to wrap round your head three times, you can travel on
the trains for free. They respect a commitment to a spiritual life.</p>

<p>I think the main reason I like dreadlocks though is because they are
beautiful. It is hard not to just stare and wonder at all the shapes, and maybe
colours, that they form.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mm0hai/6506498593/" title="The Fairy by
mm0hai, on Flickr"><img
src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7147/6506498593_a347a0411c_z.jpg"
width="640" height="480" alt="The Fairy"></a></p>

<p>A few days ago I was sitting on the street one night in a village by the
Pacific Ocean in Costa Rica. Someone was talking about getting dreads again. I
made one impulsively, under the stars.</p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Minimising Water Usage when Travelling]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/06/01/Saving-Water.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/06/01/Saving-Water.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2013-06-01T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2013/06/01/Saving-Water</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Here are some tips on using less water when travelling, by bike or with
backpack. I learnt them from other travellers, and myself through necessity.</p>

<h2>Ration Sweat</h2>

<p>Ration sweat, so you don't need to drink as much. In hot places, don't cycle
in midday sun. Instead, sleep, read, or write, under shelter from the
sun. Start cycling as soon as it gets light, and also in the evening, and you
should have enough time to get in the distance you want. In Central America, I
think I need to drink about 1 litre an hour, except around midday, maybe 1130
to 1500, when 2 litres an hour is about right if cycling.</p>

<h2>Washing Up</h2>

<p>Avoid frying - this makes washing up tractable. To cook vegetables, add them
to the boiling rice or pasta you are making. This also saves time cooking.</p>

<p>To wash a pan with only a few millilitres of water, first scrape it out with
your spoon as well as you can. Then add very little water. Rub with fingers,
or a scrubber if you have one. Remove debris with fingers. Repeat maybe once
or twice. At his stage the pan will be mostly clean, but there will probably
still be some bits of food stuck on from cooking. Now make a cup of tea in the
pan. The boiling water will remove what's stuck, and sterilise the pan. The
tea will cover any slight taste from the food. You had to drinking something
anyway, so this uses the drinking water for cleaning too. Use a lid if
available to minimise water loss as steam.</p>

<h2>Water Bottles</h2>

<p>When you need some water for washing hands, or small quantities for washing
other things, there is a technique for dispensing it.</p>

<p>Using a normal bottle of water with a screwtop, do not remove the lid. Unscrew
it just enough to allow drips of water out when you squeeze the bottle. If you
then hold the bottle between your legs, you have a tap with controllable flow
under which you can wash your hands. Better, especially if you have a large
bottle, is to put it sideways on some raised platform. Turn the lid as a tap
and wash hands under it.</p>

<h2>Paper</h2>

<p>Paper is much lighter than water. Many things you would use water for at home
can be done with tissue paper instead. For example, cleaning some things to a
good enough standard. When brushing teeth, it can be used to remove toothpaste
foam from the face.</p>

<h2>Showers</h2>

<p>This one is actually about using lots of water, but it's fun. :-) If you are
living on a beach and feel the need for the luxury of a fresh water shower:</p>

<ol>
<li>Carry large bottle of water to the beach.</li>
<li>Get naked.</li>
<li>Get someone to pour it over you.</li>
</ol>


<p>I leaned this one when I was arriving at a hippie beach in Tenerife, and the
first person I saw was a girl doing this in the moonlight. She didn't mind,
and invited me for dinner with them.</p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Living and Travelling without Money]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/08/11/Living-for-Free.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/08/11/Living-for-Free.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2012-08-11T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/08/11/Living-for-Free</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Many people assume that travel is expensive, but it doesn't need to be. I
wintered in the Canary Islands for three months and spent almost nothing. It's
just a matter of learning how to live without using money. You won't be
staying in five star hotels all the time, but it is quite possible to be happy
and there are actually many advantages of a money free lifestyle.</p>

<p>Without money, I think you are likely to meet more people, see more of the
places you travel to, and learn more. If you stay in an hotel and go on guided
tours you see the inside of an hotel and meet tourists. Then you come home a
week later because you can't afford any more and you think you've got to do
some job you would rather not be doing right then. If you sleep on a beach, in
a cave, or even on the street you will certainly have a more interesting
experience. You'll probably meet other travellers or locals who can help you
with things and show you interesting places.</p>

<p>Money forces things. This is maybe ok if you know exactly what you want all
the time, but you probably don't. The most obvious example is where to go. I
left Edinburgh with the idea of going to Patagonia. If I had bought a flight,
I would have gone straight there. I attempted to hitchhike, and because I was
not successful I had other adventures and learnt and did things which I might
not have otherwise. I think what should have happened did. Things tend to work
out for the best.</p>

<p>I think I'll write separately about the practicalities of living without
money. The main expenses which need to be removed are accommodation, <a
href="/blog/2012/08/12/Free-Food.html">food</a>, and transport. For now I'll
cover more general ideas.</p>

<h2>"The bare necessities of life will come to you."</h2>

<p>I've worked some of this out for myself on my recent travels, but I'm hardly
unique in doing so. First, I'll tell you a story. I met a guy in Las Palmas
called Toto. He helped me at a lower point with his story.</p>

<p>A few years ago he left home with 20 euros and his bike. Since then he has
travelled round the world. He sailed from Australia to Europe, then to the
Caribbean and back to Europe, and probably other places he didn't talk
about. He did some busking and when I met him had 100 euros. He didn't have
any special performing skill, he just did some silly dance. It's not really
important where he went, the story is that this is possible.</p>

<p>"Even if I only ate bread one day it doesn't matter, maybe I'll find something
else the next day."</p>

<p>I met another guy who makes a bit of money from playing music on the
street. You might call him homeless if you saw him, but since I've been back
in Edinburgh working on my geek bike project, he's been flying all over
Europe. He's probably happier than most people who work in an office.</p>

<p>It is important to be positive. You'll be interacting with people for things
like hitchhiking, and people like happy people. "You won't get a boat with a
sad face." It's also important for your own motivation.</p>

<h2>The kindness of Strangers</h2>

<p>When I was in the marina one day I went and said hello to some people. After I
short conversation I had to go and buy some food. They said no, you don't need
to, we have food. I was reluctant to take it from people who may need to more
than me but they insisted and later I found it is not really in short supply.</p>

<p>On La Palma I wanted some sort of shelter to take walking with me in the
wetter Northern part of the island. I mentioned this to someone I had just met
and so within a few minutes of meeting he had lent me his tent and a better
sleeping bag. I nearly skipped over the fact that this happened in a house I
was staying in - where I had been invited to stay by someone else I had just
met. There are many more examples but you'll need to read them in my other
blov entries when I get round to writing more.</p>

<h2>What you do need money for</h2>

<p>Basically, it comes down to convenience and speeding things up. There are a
few things you probably need it for though.</p>

<p>If you want food, you don't need money. If you want something particular to
eat, you'll probably need to buy it. If you want something now, you need to
buy it. If you can wait until you find it in a skip, you don't. If you have
time to hitchhike, you'll get there in the end. If you want to go now, you
have to pay for a bus. Of course, if you don't know where you are going,
hitchhiking is better anyway.</p>

<p>Things you pretty much do need money for are transport, some foods, and
medicines. Sometimes you might need to pay for transport: a ferry, for
example. It's very rare to find certain things in a bin, e.g. alcohol, coffee,
cooking oil, dried foods, and things with a long sell by date, but you can
live without these.</p>

<p>This post is rather unfocused because I have a lot to say on this subject and
I'm just trying to get some ideas out for now. Hopefully it is enough to show
you that this is possible. If you go out into the world with nothing but a
good attitude and an open mind you'll probably do very well.</p>

<p>I'll end with a particularly impressive story from a friend, and a link to
another blog post about this sort of thing, "<a
href="http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=18463814">The
Universe Is Conspiring to Help Us".</a></p>

<blockquote><p>"The magic is FULL ON when u arrive in a city and we have no where to sleep
and a beautiful girl called Ling comes up to u and says: I heard u play music
its is beautiful! Do u have anywhere to sleep? U can have my apartment for the
weekend when i go visit my boyfriend! So she gave us the key. AMAZING
LIFE!!!"</p></blockquote>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Love and Light as a Service]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/08/05/Love-and-Light-as-a-Service.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/08/05/Love-and-Light-as-a-Service.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2012-08-05T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/08/05/Love-and-Light-as-a-Service</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I was walking with a girl in Maspalomas and discussing the squatting and
recycling lifestyle when a tourist turned round and gave her €20. We don't
know why.</p>

<p>I asked her how she felt about taking money for nothing. I don't really like
the idea. She argued that she did not just take from the conventional society,
but provided some value, by spreading love and light.</p>

<p>Initially I thought this sounded like ridiculous hippie nonsense but later I
came to think that it is true. I think most people, ultimately, just want to be
happy. One thing that I find makes me happy is being around happy people.</p>

<p>I believe there is a French saying that "there is only one smile". When
someone sees the smile, zie then smiles, and so the smile is passed on. Thus a
pool of unfettered happy people should help to support global happiness.</p>

<p>I think the world would be a much better place if there were more people who
dedicated themselves to happiness. What else is life for?</p>

<p>So what about a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cloud_computing">Cloud
based</a> Love &amp; Light <a
href="https://www.google.co.uk/search?q=as+a+service">service</a>? I suppose
that's going to be called heaven.io and have plenty of node.js and rounded
corners.</p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Bulgarian]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2011/12/01/The-Bulgarian.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2011/12/01/The-Bulgarian.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2011-12-01T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2011/12/01/The-Bulgarian</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We walked in the sand, on wasteland at the top of the city. Around and below
us, I saw towerblocks, houses, the sea. Grass and brick in the sand. Above,
the night sky. It was warm, dark and timeless.</p>

<p>I was with The Bulgarian; I saw him, at least. He wore black, a black cloth on
his head. Round his neck, a white towel with coloured spots. He carried a
large teddy bear he had found somewhere.</p>

<p>The Bulgarian vomited.</p>

<p>"I thought you were a ghost. I thought you were my guide to see the aliens."</p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Welcome to Serendipitous Blaggagio]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2011/11/15/Serendipitous-Blaggagio.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2011/11/15/Serendipitous-Blaggagio.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2011-11-15T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2011/11/15/Serendipitous-Blaggagio</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I had a fairly normal life in Edinburgh. I worked as a software engineer from
Monday to Friday and lived in a <a
href="/blog/2011/07/26/Living.html">house</a>. I felt stuck.</p>

<p>I had read Into the Wild a while before - in which Christopher McCandless
decides after university to burn all his money and travel as a tramp around
America. He liked wilderness and ended up in Alaska, where he starved to
death. This was one thing which gave me inspiration to go travelling.</p>

<p>I also seem to like remote places. Scotland is actually quite good for this
given its size: I had walked in the Fisherfield Forest and Knoydart, and
visited Sandwood Bay on the North West coast. When I was there I wanted to
stay and try to live there for a while, by fishing and maybe in time farming,
but I had a job in Edinburgh pulling me back. On my to-visit list are
Antarctica, Siberia (with Samoyeds), Mongolia (by bike I think) and now
Alaska. The middle of the Atlantic is also a pretty remote place.</p>

<p><img
src="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/b/b6/Sandwood_Bay_North_View.jpg"
alt="Sandwood Bay" title="Sandwood Bay. Yes, Scotland." /></p>

<p>I had also done some sailing recently, around Scottish islands and Wales. I
thought then about going further and crossing the Atlantic.</p>

<p>Another source of inspiration for another life was Steve Roberts, the <a
href="http://microship.com/bike/index.html">Technomad</a>. I am a geek of
computing and radio and found his website when looking for designs for <a
href="/blog/2011/03/25/HF-Bicycle-Mobile-Experiment-Part-3.html">bicycle
mounted HF antenna systems</a>. He travelled round the USA for years on a bike
fitted with computer and radio systems. I have done some bike touring in
Europe and I thought about building a bike like this myself to go further.</p>

<p>Finally, while at work in Edinburgh I was reading In Patagonia, by Bruce
Chatwin. I realised it was wrong to stay in Edinburgh and Scotland for so long
and I should stop thinking and go out and see these places. The ideas of
sailing the Atlantic and travelling in Patagonia came together.</p>

<p>I resigned and started planning my trip. I heard that many boats cross from Las
Palmas de Gran Canaria so I flew there to look for a boat.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/58967572@N03/6431731859/" title="Cloud computing, or stupid things to carry to 6000ft by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7023/6431731859_5862ee9677_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="Cloud computing, or stupid things to carry to 6000ft"></a></p>
]]></content>
   
  </entry>
  
</feed>
