<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Alistair MacLeod, MM0HAI: Posts tagged serbla]]></title>

  <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/tag/serbla/index.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mm0hai.net/"/>
  <updated>2012-10-03T04:34:41+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/tag/serbla</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alistair N. MacLeod]]></name>
  </author>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Love and Light as a Service]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/08/05/Love-and-Light-as-a-Service.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/08/05/Love-and-Light-as-a-Service.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2012-08-05T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2012/08/05/Love-and-Light-as-a-Service</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I was walking with a girl in Maspalomas and discussing the squatting and
recycling lifestyle when a tourist turned round and gave her €20. We don't
know why.</p>

<p>I asked her how she felt about taking money for nothing. I don't really like
the idea. She argued that she did not just take from the conventional society,
but provided some value, by spreading love and light.</p>

<p>Initially I thought this sounded like ridiculous hippie nonsense but later I
came to think that it is true. I think most people, ultimately, just want to be
happy. One thing that I find makes me happy is being around happy people.</p>

<p>I believe there is a French saying that "there is only one smile". When
someone sees the smile, zie then smiles, and so the smile is passed on. Thus a
pool of unfettered happy people should help to support global happiness.</p>

<p>I think the world would be a much better place if there were more people who
dedicated themselves to happiness. What else is life for?</p>

<p>So what about a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cloud_computing">Cloud
based</a> Love &amp; Light <a
href="https://www.google.co.uk/search?q=as+a+service">service</a>? I suppose
that's going to be called heaven.io and have plenty of node.js and rounded
corners.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Welcome to Serendipitous Blaggagio]]></title>
    <link href="http://mm0hai.net/blog/2011/11/15/Serendipitous-Blaggagio.html"/>
    <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http://mm0hai.net/blog/2011/11/15/Serendipitous-Blaggagio.html&amp;user_id=mm0hai" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2011-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://mm0hai.net/blog/2011/11/15/Serendipitous-Blaggagio</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I had a fairly normal life in Edinburgh. I worked as a software engineer from
Monday to Friday and lived in a <a
href="/blog/2011/07/26/Living.html">house</a>. I felt stuck.</p>

<p>I had read Into the Wild a while before - in which Christopher McCandless
decides after university to burn all his money and travel as a tramp around
America. He liked wilderness and ended up in Alaska, where he starved to
death. This was one thing which gave me inspiration to go travelling.</p>

<p>I also seem to like remote places. Scotland is actually quite good for this
given its size: I had walked in the Fisherfield Forest and Knoydart, and
visited Sandwood Bay on the North West coast. When I was there I wanted to
stay and try to live there for a while, by fishing and maybe in time farming,
but I had a job in Edinburgh pulling me back. On my to-visit list are
Antarctica, Siberia (with Samoyeds), Mongolia (by bike I think) and now
Alaska. The middle of the Atlantic is also a pretty remote place.</p>

<p><img
src="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/b/b6/Sandwood_Bay_North_View.jpg"
alt="Sandwood Bay" title="Sandwood Bay. Yes, Scotland." /></p>

<p>I had also done some sailing recently, around Scottish islands and Wales. I
thought then about going further and crossing the Atlantic.</p>

<p>Another source of inspiration for another life was Steve Roberts, the <a
href="http://microship.com/bike/index.html">Technomad</a>. I am a geek of
computing and radio and found his website when looking for designs for <a
href="/blog/2011/03/25/HF-Bicycle-Mobile-Experiment-Part-3.html">bicycle
mounted HF antenna systems</a>. He travelled round the USA for years on a bike
fitted with computer and radio systems. I have done some bike touring in
Europe and I thought about building a bike like this myself to go further.</p>

<p>Finally, while at work in Edinburgh I was reading In Patagonia, by Bruce
Chatwin. I realised it was wrong to stay in Edinburgh and Scotland for so long
and I should stop thinking and go out and see these places. The ideas of
sailing the Atlantic and travelling in Patagonia came together.</p>

<p>I resigned and started planning my trip. I heard that many boats cross from Las
Palmas de Gran Canaria so I flew there to look for a boat.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/58967572@N03/6431731859/" title="Cloud computing, or stupid things to carry to 6000ft by mm0hai, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7023/6431731859_5862ee9677_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="Cloud computing, or stupid things to carry to 6000ft"></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
